In this session, we're going to continue
our exploration of subtyping and generics.
In particular, we're going to discuss the
important and somewhat tricky concept of
variance,
Which means how subtyping relates to
genericity.
The material in this session might be a
little harder than what you've seen
previously.
If you want to go fast, and you don't need
to know things to the last detail.
Then it's perfectly fine if you just
browse this session, or skip it
completely.
On the other hand, if you want to go to
the roots, then this session is for you.
As a bonus, we're going to develop a
completely satisfactory model of cons
lists that doesn't have any of the
shortcomings that we have to deal with
before.
You've seen in the previous session that
some types such as lists should be
covariant.
Whereas other types such as arrays should
be not covariant.
What's the difference between the two?
Well roughly speaking the type list is
immutable where as the type array is
mutable because we can update its elements
and immutable types can typically be
covariant if some conditions or methods
are met whereas mutable types can not.
In this session we will find out precisely
what the conditions are so when types that
can be covariant and when they cannot.
In fact, it's not just a binary choice
between variant or not.
There are actually three possible
relationships between type instance c, of
c and a, and c and b, where c of t is a
parameterized type.
And a and b are types such that a is a
sub-type of b.
So we could either determine that c of a
is a sub-type of c of b.
Or we could determine the opposite
relationship, which would say that c of b
is a subtype of c of a.
Or, we could have the relationship where
neither of the three was true.
So neither c of a is a subtype of c of b,
nor is c of b a subtype of the other.
So if c of a is a subtype of c of b, we
say c is covariant.
If the opposite is true, so c of a is a
super type of c of b, then we say c in
contravariant.
And if neither of the two are true, then
we say c is nonvariant.
Scala lets you declare the variance of a
type by annotating the type parameter.
So you can determine that a class should
be covariant by writing a + in front of
the type parameter, the a here.
Or you could determine that it's
contravariant by writing a minus.
Or finally, if you write neither + or -,
then the default is that C is non-variant.
So c of a and c of b are unrelated.
So here's some food for thought.
Say you have two function types.
The Type A is a function that takes IntSet
to NonEmpty set, and Type B is a type that
takes non-empty sets to general int sets.
According to the Livka substitution
principle that you've seen in the last
session, which of the following should be
true?
Is A, a subtype of B, or B a subtype of A?
Or are A and B unrelated?
So I will argue that type A is a subtype
of type B Why?
Well, let's look.
What can you do with a type b function
from non-empty to IntSet?
While the thing you can do is you is you
park, can pass a non-empty IntSet, and
receive an IntSet back.
Can you do the same thing with type A?
Well, of course, if you pass a nonempty
IntSet to the type A, it expects just an
IntSet, so a nonempty will do just fine,
and you will get back a nonempty IntSet,
which of course is a special case for our
IntSet. So type A satisfies the same
contract as type B.
If you give it a nonempty set, it will
give you back an IntSet, but it actually
will satisfy more than B.
So that's why A is a true subtype of B...
So let's generalize this to arbitrary
function types.
So the rule we have is if we have two
function types, A1 to B1 and A2 to B2, and
the first is a subtype of the second, if.
First the result types, B1 and B2, are
subtypes, so they go in the same
direction, but the argument types go in
the other direction.
So A2 must be a subtype of A1.
So let's express that visually.
So we have the supertype A2.
To B2 here.
And the presumed subtype, A1 to B1.
So, what we say is that the A2 type is a
subtype.
Of a one, and B1 is a subtype Of b too,
and that would mean that this is a.
Especially the case of the a2 to b2
function.
Why would that be?
Let's see.
Lets look at the first functions, so all
we could do is pass an argument of A2 into
this function.
Because of this sub-typing relationship we
can pass the same argument also to A1
because A2 is a sub-type of A1.
Then we apply the.
Function a-1 to b-1, that gives us a b-1
and again because of sub-typing that
actually qualifies as a b-2.
So we could easily instead of having used
this function here, we could supply the
lower function.
Over there, and the same argument types
would map to the same, result types.
So what we've learned is that functions
are actually contravariant in their
argument types, and covariant in their
result types.
We can then express that code in Scholar,
and that leads us to the revised
definition of the function one-trade that
you've seen before.
So now I've added two variance annotations
to the parameters.
The argument type t is contravariant.
It has a minus and the result type u is
covariant.
It has a plus.
Now, can we just sprinkle minuses and
pluses over classes as we please, to make
them call a countervariant.
Well obviously not because otherwise, we
could've done the same thing with array.
Make array for instance co-variant and run
into to the problem the Java did.
So there are rules when we, when can we
annotate a type parameter with plus and
with minus.
So, to find out what the rules are, let's
look at ganity array example.
So, I, now assume that array is a class
written like this one, array and update
the updating functionality.
In array is, is captured as a method
called update.
So the problematic combination was that
the class was covariant, so the type
parameter T will have a plus here.
Whereas update took a parameter of the
same type T.
So a covariant type parameter T together
with a, a method that takes a parameter of
that type will lead to problems or did
lead to problems in the array case.
So the Scala compiler will actually check
that there are no problematic combinations
when compiling a class with variant
annotations.
Roughly, what it will do is, it will let
covariant type parameters only appear in
method results.
Contravariant type parameters can only
appear in method parameters, and
nonvariant, or invariant, that they are
used as aliases, type parameters can
actually appear anywhere.
The precise rules are a bit more involved.
But fortunately this Scala compiler will
perform them for us, so we don't need to
memorize them or.
If we go back to the function example, the
checks that this Scala compiler performer
will perform here is that the T parameter
which is contravariant, is only used as a
function parameter.
That's correct.
And the U parameter, which is co-variant,
is only used as a function result, which
is also correct.
So, function one checks out okay,
according to these checks.
So now that we've seen variants, let's get
back to the previous implementation that
we did of lists.
One shortcoming there that was that nil
was modeled as a class.
Whereas we would prefer it to be an
object, after all there's only one empty
list.
Can we change that?
Well, let's have a look at the.
Example.
So I've brought up the, list hierarchy
that we've seen in previous sessions.
What we would like to do is turn class nil
into an object.
So let's just go right ahead and do that.
So objects can't have type parameters,
because there's only a single instance of
them.
So I will delete the type parameter for
the object.
Then we get an error which says that the
Type T here is not found.
That's true because T is not longer bound
as a type parameter.
So we have to find another type In which
we, which we want to use as the argument
type of typelist.
What will be a good type?
Well, of course, we could write list of
string or list of object.
But all of that would make nil only a
subtype of a partic-, specific kind of
list.
So, what we will try instead is make it a
list of nothing.
That's promising because, as we know,
nothing is the bottom type, which is a
subtype of every other type, so it's in a
sense, universal.
It can express everything else.
But we're not done yet.
To see why, let's make a little test
object.
And say, here I want to have a simple
assignment, where I say Valex of type list
of string, and that should be the empty
list.
We get an error which says it's a long
error message.
Which says, well, it found a nil, and it
required a list of string.
So obviously, nil is not a subtype of list
of string.
And then it goes on, to say, you may wish
to define the type parameter t of list as
+t instead.
So what the compiler suggests is that,
indeed, we should make list covariant.
That we make by having a pipe parameter
here.
If we do that, then everything will type
check correctly.
So let's have a look at what happened
here.
So List of string = nil type checks,
because nil is a list of nothing.
Nothing is a subtype of string, and lists
are covariants.
So that's why list of nothing is a subtype
of list of string.
Another thing that works out very well
here, is that we have seen that in the
object little head and tail already return
nothing, because they can't terminate.
And that matches precisely the template of
list.
Because we said for a list of t, a head
should return a t and tail should return a
list of t.
Now head indeed does return the element
type here, nothing.
Tail doesn't return a list of nothing but
directly a nothing.
But that's actually something that's even
a subtype of list of nothing.
So both types are very, very precise in
what they express.
To complete this session, which was quite
a bit harder than previous sessions, I
want to introduce one more thing.
Sometimes we actually have to put in a bit
of work to make a class covariant.
So to see an example is, let's say we want
to add a method prepend to our list class,
which prepends a given element and yields
a new list.
So prepend would be defined like this.
It would say, take an element of type T,
the element type of the list, give me back
a list of T, and it would have the obvious
implementation, would create a new count
cell with the given element, followed by
the current list itself.
But that doesn't work.
Why does it not work?
So.
I leave this for you as an exercise.
Why does the following code not type
check?
The Prepend method as before in a covarant
list.
Possible answers are; Prepan turns list
into a mutable class, Prepend fails
variance checking, or Prepend's right hand
side contains a type error.
What do you think?
One way to solve this is try it out.
Put Prepend, let's put Prepend into our
worksheet and see what happens.
So what we get is an error, which says
covariant type T occurs in contravariant
position in type T of value elem. What
that says is that our co-variant type
parameter T appeared as a, the type of a
method parameter.
And we've seen that, that actually
violates the variant checking rule.
So the variance checking rule, which was
actually invented to prevent mutable,
operations in covariant classes, also
rules out something like this.
Which doesn't involve any mutability at
all.
All we do is create a new list.
Do you think that's a mistake of the, of
the rules or is there some deep wisdom to
the rules nevertheless?
In fact, the Scholar Compiler is right to
throw out lists that prepend because it
does violate the lists of substitution
principle.
Why?
Well here's something one can do with a
list of type, list of IntSet, called the
list excess.
We can do excess dot prepend empty.
Because empty of course is an IntSet.
But the same operation on a list wires of
type list of non-empty would lead to a
type error.
So if you did that wires.prependempty and
you would see a type error message like
here which says well we required a
non-empty because that was the element
type of the list but we found an empty and
the two are not compatible.
So here's something you can do with a list
of IntSet that it cannot do with a list of
non-empty set.
And because we found such a thing it
follows that according to the Liskov
Substitution Principle, list of non-empty
cannot be a sub-type of list of IntSet.
Okay.
So now we now why prepend is illegal, but
Still, there's an unsatisfactory feeling
here, because prepend is an actual method,
after all, to have on immutable lists.
So the question is, can we somehow make it
variance correct?
And, in fact, we can.
And for that, we will make use of a lower
bound.
So, here is a reformulation of prepent
which uses a lower bound for the type
parameter U.
We say prepent it takes a type parameter U
which must be a super type of the list
element type T.
It takes a U element of the type U and it
returns a list of U.
And the body of prepent is as it was
before.
And actually the, the, this passes the
variance checks.
Because it turns out that co-variant type
parameters, such as a T of list may appear
in the lower bounds of Meta Type
Parameters.
Contra-variant type parameters may appear
in the upper bounds instead.
So, you can find out yourself how this
works in detail by solving the following
exercise.
Implement prepend as shown in trait list.
The question is, let's say we have a
function that takes a list of non empty as
first parameter and empty element as
second parameter, and prepends the empty
list set to the list of non empty sets.
What would happen?
The possible answers are: this would not
type check or the result type of this
function would be a list of non empty or
maybe a list of empty or a list of IntSet
or a list of any.
The top type of all color types.
What do you think?
Now let's see how we would solve that.
The straightforward way to attack this is,
well lets try it out.
Let's add the function prepend, and the
function f, as we've seen on this slide.
And if we look at function F, its type,
and we hover over F with say.
It takes a list of non-empty and an empty
parameters as given and it returns a list
of IntSet.
So a list of IntSet is the correct answer.
That still begs the explanation, why?
So let's look first at the subtype
hierarchy.
As always we have that IntSet.
Is a super type of both non-empty and
empty.
So we call the predef method on a list of
non-empty.
So, T in this case, for the predef method,
that is nonempty.
That was our, the, the parameter of the
list.
But T takes a type parameter which can be
an arbitrary supertype of nonempty.
And one thing that must happen with the
supertype is that LM is an instance of the
supertype.
So LM the type U that is empty because
that's the type of the X that we pass to
pre-def.
Is empty a subtype of non-empty?
No, of course not.
So that's why the empty value that we pass
in here, it doesn't conform to the
non-empty type.
So what the type inferencer would choose
instead is the next higher type up here.
So that would be IntSet.
Maybe you can be an Intset, and indeed,
that would work out.
The list xs, which is a list of non empty,
is, of course, also a list of IntSet,
because of covariance of lists.
And empty is itself an IntSet.
So the type inference that would determine
that the correct type parameter for U,
indeed, must be IntSet and the type that
gets returned from Prepend a list of
IntSet.
And that's, then also the result type of
f.
So, so one thing we've seen here is that
intuitively F does exactly the right
thing.
If we take a list of non-empties and we
add an empty, the best thing that we could
get out of that would be a list of IntSets
because that's the smallest type in a
manner of speaking that contains both the
XS, the list of non-empties, as well as
the additional element X which was of type
empty.
So we see that the machinery.
With the subtype bound here, it is a
little bit complicated.
But, on the other hand, it does the
exactly the right thing.
It will lead to exactly the right invert
types for data structures that contain
elements of various different types.