Now that we've seen how we can encode
primitive types as classes, the only two
fundamental types of values that are left
are instances of classes and functions.
What we're going to look at in this
session is how function types relate to
classes, and how function values relate to
objects.
In the last session, we've seen that
Scala's numeric types and the Boolean type
can conceptually be implemented like
normal classes.
But what about functions?
Are functions special or are they also
just objects?
In fact, function values are treated as
objects in Scala, not just conceptually,
but in reality.
What happens here is that the function
type a arrow b is really just an
abbreviation for the class scala dot
function one ab.
And that class is roughly defined, as you
can see here.
In fact, function values are already
treated as objects in Scala not just
conceptually, but really.
The function type A arrow B is just an
abbreviation for the class
scala.function1, two type parameters, the
A and the B.
And that class is roughly defined as
follows.
So it's a trait in pack of Scala.
It takes the two type parameters, A and B.
And it has a single method which is called
Apply.
So apply the function to an argumentix of
type A, yielding a result of type B.
So functions are really objects with apply
methods.
What you've seen here was the definition
of four functions of a single argument,
but there are also classes, function two,
function three and so on, for functions
that take more parameters.
Currently we have those function traits
until 22 parameters, but in the future
there might be more, or we might be more
flexible in that.
Okay, so we've looked at function types.
What about function values?
Let's look at an anonymous function like
the squaring function here, which takes
and X and returns X times X.
What would that expand to in this
object-oriented view of functions?
Well, it would be a new class that we
create here called this anonfun, I assume
that the name is not used otherwise in the
program.
And that would be a subclass of my
function one trait, Int, Int are the
argument types.
And the apply method then, would be one
that takes an integer and returns the
square of its argument.
So that was the class that implements this
behavior.
Now all that's needed to do is create an
instance of that class.
That would be the object that represents
this function here.
So creating an instance is simply new and
unfun.
In fact, that definition is again quite
common and there's a shorter syntax for
it.
It's called anonymous class syntax.
So what we can do is, we can take
essentially this part here And leave out
the name, so we write just, new function
one, and int, and the definition of that
class.
So that create a new instance of a class
that I haven't bothered to give a name.
That anonymous class syntax you actually
find in Java as well, so both Java and
Scala have the same syntax in, in for, for
this construct.
Okay.
So now we've seen how we represent
functions.
But, what about then applications of these
functions or function calls?
So, let's say we have a function that was,
started life as this anonymous function.
So, it's an object.
And now we apply it to two concrete
arguments, A and B.
What would that expand to?
Well, what it would expand to is simply
calling the apply method of the function
value with the same arguments.
So a complete object oriented translation
of this code here, where you first create
an anonymous function and then apply that
function to the value seven would be, we
create a anonymous class instance, with an
apply method, name it F, and then call the
apply method of F with the argument seven.
So now you see that functions are objects.
Does the same hold for methods?
For instance, this apply method here.
Would that, by itself, be an object?
Well, that can't very well work.
Because if apply was an object.
Well, it would be an instance of this
function class, which would be, have an
apply method, which would be an object,
Which would be an instance of this
function class, which would have an apply
method.
You see the problem.
We would get an infinite expansion.
So what happens instead is that methods
such as Def, F, Boolean.
So anything that's defined with a Def are
not, themselves, function values.
But if the name of a method is used in a
place where a function type is expected,
it's converted automatically to the
function value.
And the conversion is just that we create
an anonymous function like this one here.
Which, where we say, well, give me an
argument, and I apply the method to the
argument.
That anonymous function value we've seen
how that expands to this new anonymous
class. New function one in boolean with
the apply method.
So that's how.
Functions really are treated in Scala.
A technical term which you don't need to
remember, but I just give it for
completeness here.
So this transformation here that converts
the name F to this anonymous function,
It's called, in lambda, calculus, eta
expansion.
So if you hear sometimes the word eta
expansion, then you know now what it is.
Let's do an exercise.
In package week four, where we have
defined previously the list class with its
subclasses,
I want you to define an object list with
some functions in it.
And the idea would be that users will then
be, create lists of length,
Zero, one, or two just with the syntax.
So list of open parens, closed parens with
the empty list.
List of one would be the list of the
single element one.
And so on.
So let's see how we would solve this.
I've put up the list class that we've
developed previously so the task was to
develop an object together with that class
that would give us that syntax that we
could just call list of twelve.
Lets say.
So how would we do that.
So idea is if we look at that syntax list
is used in function possession.
So what this would really expand to you
know that would be list.apply12.
So that means that we're asked to define a
method called Apply.
And in that case it would take two
arguments.
A, let's call it X1.
Of type T and X2 of type T, so the T can
be arbitrary, we have to parametrize apply
with it.
Then would return a list, so result type
is list of t.
And it would then return a list that
consists of these elements.
So that would be new of cons of x1 and new
of cons of x2 and new of middle.
And for the other two, for list of one and
list of zero, the result would be
analogous.
So, I leave out list of with single
elements.
But, for the empty list, I simply have an
apply method.
It takes no arguments.
I would give us.