As you know, in previous sessions we have
already covered two forms of polymorphism.
One was subtyping, which was usually
associated with object oriented
programming.
The other was generics, which came
originally from functional programming.
Once you combine subtyping and generics,
the subtle interactions that we are going
to explore in this session and the next
one.
In particular, we're going to develop an
important method in this session to find
out when one type can be a subtype of
another.
That method is called the Liscov
Substitution Principle.
In the last session we have encountered
the two principal forms of polymorphism.
Subtyping, where we can pass instances of
a subtype where a base type was required.
And, generics, where we can parameterize
types with other types.
In this session we will look at the
interactions between the two concepts.
There are essentially two main areas to
cover.
The first one is bounds, where we can
subject type parameters to sub type
constraints.
And the second is variance, that defines
how parameterized types behave under sub
typing.
So let's look at type bounds first.
As a motivating example, consider you want
to write a method assertAllPos or assert
all positive.
That method should take an IntSet and it
should return the IntSet it, itself, but
it should check with all elements of the
IntSet are positive.
If they're not then it should throw an
exception.
What would be the best type you can give
to assert all pos?
You might come up with this type here.
Assertallpos.
Well, it would take an insert and it would
return an IntSet and well, in the case
where not all elements are positive would
withdraw an exception but that's not
reflected in the result type.
And that's fine for most situations.
But maybe one can be more precise.
In fact, if we look at the behavior of a
assertAllPos, we see that it's governed
essentially by two equations that we set
assertAllPos of empty is empty.
And, assetAllPos of a non empty set is,
well, it's either, another non empty set
or rather the same that we passed in, or
it throws an exception.
So what we see in particular is that if
assertAllPos gets an empty argument, then
it would give you back an empty result.
And if it gets a non-empty argument, it
would give you back a non-empty result.
And that knowledge is actually not
reflected in this type here.
Well we say well it takes an IntSet and
gives you back an IntSet.
So how can we capture that additional
knowledge?
So one way to express it is this way.
We could say assertAllPos.
It takes sum type S that must be some
subtype of IntSet either empty or non
empty.
And a set of that type itself.
And will return a result of the same type.
So here the part that says less that colon
insert is an upper bound of the type
parameter S what it means is that we can
instantiate S to any type argument as long
as the type argument conforms to the
bound, conforms to insert.
We also will use the symbol less than
colon outside of type bound. So generally,
S < :: T will mean S is a sub-type of T.
So we have S and we have T, and S is a
sub-type of T.
Whereas S > T means the opposite, so S is
a supertype of T, or otherwise put T is a
sub-type of S.
So we've seen upper bounds where the type
variable ranged overall subtypes of a
given type.
Scala actually also has lower bounds.
So we could say a bound s is a super type
of non-empty.
And that would introduce a type parameter
s that can range only over the super types
of non-empty.
So in our case, of the IntSet example, s
could be one of either non-empty, IntSet
AnyRef or any.
You might ask where are lower bounds
useful and it's not immediately apparent
but you'll see later on in this session an
important use case where lower bounds are
indeed essential.
Finally it's also possible to mix a lower
bound with an upper bound.
So that you would write like here.
You could say s is bounded from below by
non empty and from above by IntSet And
that would then restrict any actual
argument for s to a type that's in the
interval between non empty and IntSet In
our case, that interval actually contains
only the two types, non-empty and IntSet
because we have this inheritance
relationship.
But in general, there could have, of
course, be more types between the lower
bound and the upper bound.
So now that we've have looked at bounds,
there is still another thing to consider.
So, we know that non-empty is a sub-type
of IntSet What about if we wrap both types
in a list?
Should a list of non-empty also be a
sub-type of list of IntSet?
Intuitively, this makes sense.
A list of nonempty sets is obviously a
special case of a list of arbitrary sets.
So from a domain modeling perspective,
list of nonempty should indeed be a
subtype of list of IntSets So we call
types for which this relationship holds,
covariant, because the subtyping
relationship varies exactly like the type
parameter.
In our case then, it would make sense to
make lists into a covariant type.
The question to ask then, of course, is
that a property just of list, or should
all types be covariant, is covariance
something that every parameterized type
should be.
So to get some perspective on it, let's
look at the concept of arrays in Java, and
also in C#.
Which is, in this respect, buck for buck,
comparable with Java.
If you don't know Java or C#, then the
only thing you need to know here, really,
is that an array of elements of type T is
written T brackets in Java.
And in Scala, we actually express this
slightly differently.
We would use a normal parameter as type
syntax array of T to refer to the same
types.
Arrays in Java are actually covariant,
just like the list type we have seen.
So one would have that an array of
nonempty sets is a subtype of an array of
IntSets.
But it actually turns out that this idea
of arrays being covariant causes problems.
To see why, consider this Java snippet
below.
We create an array of non empties A, we
assign it to an IntSet B, we assign empty
into the first element of B, and we pull
out the first element of A and assign it
to a non empty.
So let's visualize what goes on here.
In the first step, we create a new array.
And fill it with a non-empty element, call
it A.
In the second step we assign A to B and
that's actually a reference assignment.
So after this step, we would have another
pointer, B, pointing to the same array.
In the third step, we assign empty into
the first element of the B array.
So let me erase a non-empty value here,
and replace it with an empty value
instead.
In the final step, we pull out the first
element of the array.
That's the empty value.
And assign it into a non empty set, S.
So what we would get is S, of type non
empty, equals E.
Now, something's clearly gone wrong here.
Because we ended up assigning an empty set
into a variable of type non-empty sets.
So, if types are supposed to prevent
something, it's precisely this.
That we, that, that you can't do that.
So what went wrong?
So looking at the example again.
The first line would execute fine.
So would the second line, because arrays
are covariant.
But the third line will actually give you
something at runtime namely and array
store exception.
So you would get a runtime exception.
That protects the assignment of MT into
this array.
What actually happens it that, to make up
for the problems caused by coherence of
arrays, Java needs to store in every array
a type tag that reflects what, at what
type this array was created.
So when we create a non empty array, the
type tag would read, well, it contains non
empty, so let me write this here.
So the type tag would say, well it's
actually a non empty array.
And now that we have signed something in
to an element of the array, we run time
type of the thing we have signed gets
checked against the type tag.
So in our case here it would be have an
empty value but the type tag would read
non empty and that would give you a run
time error.
Now, it seems that this is not a very good
deal.
We have traded a compile-time error for a
run-time error, and we have also paid the
price for a run-time check that we have to
do.
Every array store has to undergo this,
this check against the array tach.
So one could argue that it was really a
mistake to make a raised covariant that
produced a hole in the type system that
had to be patched by a run time check.
And you might ask why did the designers of
Java do it in the end.
Well it actually turned out that they
wanted to do with they wanted to be able
to write a method such as sort.
That would work for any array.
So the way they would express that in the
first version of Java, it would say the
sort method would take an object array.
And then covariance of arrays was
necessary so that an array of strings or
an array of integers could all be passed
to an object array.
Of course, with Java five and later on,
you've a much better way of doing that.
You would do it the same way as in
Scholar, you would use a generic type.
But before, because generics were not
available in the earlier version of Java,
people made do with that.
Now, can we somehow generalize what we've
learned here?
When does it makes sense for a, for a type
to be a subtype of another?
And when should that rather not be the
case?
That's actually an important principle,
first stated by Barbara Liskov that tells
us when a type can be a subtype of
another.
Essentially what it says is if A is a
subtype of B.
Then everything one can do with a value of
type B, should one should also be able to
do with a value of type A.
So we have the Type B, that's the super
type.
The Type A is the subtype.
And we say, well, if we expect that we can
do something with Bs, then we can, should
be able to substitute an A for a B, and we
can still do the same thing with an A.
The actual definition Liskov used is
actually a bit more formal, so here it is.
The definition says, let Q of X be a
property that's provable about object X of
type B, then Q of Y should also be
provable for objects Y of type A.
Where A is less than B.
So, the original formulation coached it in
terms of what you can prove about objects,
not what operations you can perform.
Take what we've seen from Java back to
Scala.
Then, let's look at the problematic array
example but now expressed in Scala.
Here's how you would do that.
Would create an array of non empty values,
you would assign empty into the first
element of the array B, so notice that
array selection is expressed with
parenthesis in Scholar, not brackets, so
its really the same thing as a function
call.
And the underlying reason for that is that
arrays are really specializations of
functions in Scholar.
If you write code like that in Scholar,
then what would you expect to observe?
Would you expect to see a type error or
would you expect to see a program that
compiles?
And if you expect the type error then in
what line would you expect it.
If the program compiles, would you expect
to it throw exception at runtime or you
would you think it should run without
exception.
So, you have six choices overall.
Make your choice.
So the correct answer is, you would expect
to see a type error in line two.
Why?
Well, because the a value was an array of
nonempty.
Where as B was an array of IntSet.
But, in Scala, arrays are not covariant.
So you would not have a subtype
relationship between those two arrays.
And that means you will get a type error.
It will say, I have found an array of
nonempty, but I have expec, expected an
array of IntSet.