An important problem in programing is
decomposition.
Let's say you have a hierarchy of classes
and you want to build tree-like data
structures from the instances of these
classes.
How do you build such a tree?
And how do you find out what kind of
elements are in the tree?
And how do you access the data that's
stored in this elements?
That's the problem of decomposition, which
we are going to tackle in this session.
Lets look at this with an example.
Suppose you want to write a small
interpreter for arithmetic expressions.
To keep it simple, lets restrict ourselves
for the moment to just numbers and
additions as expressions.
Such expressions can be represented as a
class hierarchy.
You'd have a base straight Expr for
expressions and two sub classes, Number
and Sum.
Now if you want to explore a tree of nodes
consisting of Numbers and Sum, you would
like to know what kind of tree is it.
Is it a Number?
Is it a Sum?
And what components has it?
To be able to do that, it brings us to the
following implementation.
So here you see, I have my class
hierarchy, I have an expression and then I
have two subclasses Number and Sum.
Now for a complete functionality of
expression, if I look at an expression I
would like to know is it a Number or is it
a Sum and that's done by the first two
methods. Here is Number and is Sum.
Now, if it's a Number, then I would like
to know the value of that Number.
That would be a number, let's call it n.
And if it's a sum, then I would know, want
to know what are it's operands and that
would be a leftOp and a rightOp field.
So to do that here's the implementation of
Number.
Number is a subclass of expression and it
would now implement all the five methods
that you see here.
In expressions, we have the two
classification methods, its Number and its
Sum,
And we would have the three accessor
methods for either Numbers or Sums, which
we've numValue, which, this one applies
only to Numbers.
And leftOp, rightOp,, these ones do apply
to sums.
So to implement these five methods, what
do we do in Number?
Well, isNumber obviously is true, isSum
obviously is false. The numeric value of a
number is just the number we pass into it.
And the left operand and right operand,
they are operations that are not
applicable to Numbers. So both of them
would throw an error that says that say
well you have called a leftOp or a rightOp
method on number and that is illegal.
So let's look at Sums next.
So the idea would be that Sum of e1, e2
would correspond to the expression that is
e1 plus e2.
Its five implementations are as follows.
A Sum is clearly not a Number.
A Sum is a Sum.
The numeric number of a Sum is something
that's not applicable, that would throw an
error.
The left operand is the first argument
that we pass into Sum.
The right operation is the second argument
we pass into Sum.
So now that we've got the basic wiring of
expressions, let's do something with it.
One thing we could do is write an
evaluation function.
So the evaluation function should take one
of these expression trees and it should
return the number that it represents.
So for instance, I would like to have that
eval of Sum of the Number one and the
Number two, Should give me three.
So how would I write an evaluation
function like that?
Well, one way to do that would be to
simply ask, given an expression, what it
is?.
So, we ask this question, is it a number.
If yes, then we can return the numeric
value of that expression.
Otherwise, if the expression is a Sum then
we take, it's both two operands, the left
operand and the right operand and we
evaluate both of them using eval.
And finally, you have to guard against the
case that you might have another
expression that is neither a Number or a
Sum.
Maybe not now, but maybe in the future,
somebody will add such a subclass of
expression.
So it's prudent to have a third class
which says well, if it's neither a Number
nor a Sum,
Then we throw an error which says I found
an unknown expression and here it is.
.
Okay.
So far so good.
But there's a problem with that and that
is that writing all these classification
and access of functions quickly becomes
tedious.
We've already written fifteen method
definitions only to do something as simple
as expressions consisting of Sums and
Numbers.
And things get worse if we add other forms
of expressions.
So let's demonstrate that.
Let's say we want to add to our expression
trees two new classes.
One that represents the product of two
expressions, e1 and e2,
So e1 times e2 would be a class product
given arguments e1 and e2. and the other
new class would be Var that represents
variables.
So variables would take a string that
represents the name.
So if you want it to continue with our
scheme of classification and access
methods, then we'd need to add new methods
to, of course, those two new classes but
also to all the classes defined above.
So, a question to you.
If we wanted to do that for Product and
Var, how many new method definitions would
we need?
Here I want you to count the method
definitions in Product and Var themselves.
But also any new Accessor and
classification methods that we have to
retrofit to the existing classes, to
Expression and Sum and Num.
Possible answers would be nine, or ten,
nineteen, or maybe 25,
Or even 35, or 40.
So to answer that question, let's look
back at our existing solution.
What we want to do now is add two new
subclasses of Expression, one for Product,
the other for Vars.
And Var would have probably a name and
Products would have essentially also
leftOp and rightOp just like Sums.
So what do we need as new methods.
Well, we would need new classification
method that tells us whether a given
expression is a Product or a Var.
So there would be some new methods called
that isVar and isProdu that we would have
to add to the trait expression and also to
its subclasses.
Now, what about the access methods?
Here we would need, in addition to the Num
value, and leftOp and rightOp, also an
operation that gives us the name of a
variable.
Would we need access and methods for
leftOp and rightOp and product?
Well, you might think so, but in fact,
it's probably better to just re-use the
Accessor methods of Sum, to just say both
products and sum.
They're binary operations so they share
the accesses for the left and right and
side operance.
So that means no new access or methods for
products, just a classification method.
And we're left with three methods in,
trait Expr.
So that means trait Expr now has eight
methods and all subclasses of trait Expr,
also needs to implement these methods.
So that would mean eight methods for class
number and eight methods for class Sum.
And then, of course, we have the two new
classes, Product and Var, which also have
to implement all of the eight methods now,
isNumber, isSum, isVar, isProd, numValue,
leftOp, rightOp, and name. So that means,
overall, we have five classes,
Each of them implementing eight methods
for a total of 40 methods.
Our previous solution had three classes,
each of them implementing five methods for
a total of fifteen methods.
So the answer to the question was, we have
25 new methods.
So generally, if we continue with that
game to extend the hierachy with new
classes we find out that the number of
methods we need tends to grow
quadratically, and that's, of course, very
bad news,
Because it means that our, program size,
and ability to understand programs, will
quickly be exhausted, as we add new
classes to the hierarchy.
So the question is what to do about it.
Can we find another solution that avoids
the quadratic increase of methods?
Well, here's one which I would actually
call a non solution.
Most languages have some form of type
testing and type casting, and Scala let's
you do that as well.
So it has a method'is instance of' that
can check whether an object's type
conforms to T and it has a method called
isInstanceOf that check whether an object
as type conforms type T, so that would be
a type cast.
If the cast fails at one time because the
object is not at run time, then it will
throw a class cast exception.
So x is instance of T is really the same
thing as x instance of T in Java.
And it's asInstanceOf is the same thing as
a type cast, which is written like this in
Java.
.
The Scala form of these type tests and
type casts is as methods on the type class
any.
And the methods would take the type that
they want to test or cast against as a
type parameter.
If you compare the Scala solution and the
Java solution then you see that Scala
solution is quite a bit longer, and you
could argue less legible than the Java
solution, and that's completely
intentional,
Because, actually it turns out that
typetest and typecasts are very low level
and unsafe and that, in fact, Scala has
much better solutions.
So, the use of type test and type cast,
[INAUDIBLE in Scala because of sometimes
useful for interoperability with Java, but
the use is discouraged.
So using type tests and type class, we
could do something like that for eval..
We could say, okay, we have a class
expression. and now we n-, don't need to
put anything special inside expression.
And you would simply ask: is the
expression an instance of my number class?
Then we cast it to number in that case and
we pull out the num value from the number.
On the other hand, if the expression is an
instance of sum then we take the left
operand after casting it to sum, take the
right operand after casting it to sum and
evaluate both operands, finally sum the
results.
And the third part would be as before, if
it's neither, then we throw an error.
So if we look at the solution, then the
good part of it is that we don't need any
classification methods.
These instance of tests, fulfill that role
now,
And we need access methods only for
classes where the value is defined.
So that means that our base,, trait ede
could actually be empty.
Whereas number needs a num value.
Because and some.
Needs a left up and a right up.
But number doesn't need a leftOp and a
rightOp,, because we will call leftOp and
rightOp only after casting to Sum.
So, we need many fewer methods, which is
good.
On the other hand, use of typetest and
typecast is very low level, it is unsafe
because, when you do a type-cast you do
not know necessarily at runtime whether
type-cast will succeed.
It might also throw a classcast exception.
In this example, here we have actually
guarded every type-cast by a type-test, so
we can assure statistically that none of
these casts will fail, but in general
that's not assured.
So that's why, we recommend the people to
stay away from type-casts.
So here's a solution that looks much
better.
If, after all, all we want to do is
evaluate expressions, then we could have a
direct object oriented solution for that.
Instead of making eval a method which
exists outside our hierarchy, we just
write it as a method of expression itself.
So now, what we need to do is that, in the
base trait, we would have an expression
eval which returns int, and is abstract,
as usual.
Then, for a number, the evaluation of a
number would just give the number that's,
well, that, well, passed into the class.
That is the parameter.
And to evaluate a Sum, we simply evaluate
its left operand, evaluate its right
operand, and form the sum of those two
values.
Great.
So this is clearly much preferable to what
we did so far,
But what happens if we'd like to display
expressions now.
So lets assume we want to have here
another method, call it show, that returns
a string.
At ths place the expression.
Then of course we'd need to have an
implementation of show in Number and
another one in Sum.
That's all very well, but there's one
disadvantage here that we needed to touch
all the classes in the hierarchy and add a
method in each one of them.
So we have to touch many pieces of code,
which in a real system could be, for
instance, in different source files.
So any such change that adds a new message
to our hierarchy is rather pervasive.
But there's a more fundamental limitation
of this object-oriented decomposition
scheme that we've seen.
To see that, let's assume that we don't
want to evaluate an expression nor do we
want to show it, but we want to simplify
it, let's say using this rule here.
So we want to replace sums of products
with the same left operand with a product
of sums using the usual rule of
distribution.
How would we go about doing that?
Well, the problem here is we can't really
have a simplify method in either product
or sum.
Because the simplification involves a
whole subtree, not a single node.
So it can't be encapsulated as a method of
a single object without also looking at
other objects.
Like we could may be put simplify in the
sum operation,
But then it would have to look at its two
operands and verify that, indeed, they are
both products and that the left operand of
each product is the same tree.
Well,
Doing that, we are actually back at
classification and access methods, so
we're back to square one.
We need tests and access methods for all
the different subclasses.
So that shows that object oriented
decomposition is good for some things like
implementing the eval function, but it's
can't do other things such as a non local
simplification, and it might not be the
best solution if you have many new methods
that you want to introduce because you
have to touch all subclasses every time
you introduce a new method.
In the next session, we're going to see
another technique that will address these
problems.