We've seen in the previous session that
all our attempts of decomposition were
failing because of one reason or another.
In this session we are going to introduce
a new tool in the functional program as
tool box pattern matching.
We will show how pattern matching is a
good fit for the problem of decomposition.
So remember the task we were trying to
solve is find the general and convenient
way to access objects in an extensible
class hierarchy.
The class hierarchy we were looking at was
those of arithmetic expressions.
We had a base trait expression.
And then we had sub-classes for number and
sum. Then later on we also added
sub-classes for product and variable to
that.
And in terms of methods, we were looking
at eval, that would evaluate one of these
expression trees using its results.
As well as show, that would show a string
representation of the expression tree.
And then finally simplify, which would do
some algebraic simplifications of an
expression tree.
We've, we've seen three attempts
previously and they all had some yes
comings.
The first one was the classification and
access methods, there we observed a
quadratic explosion of the methods we had
to write.
In this class hierarchy here there were 40
methods that we had to write.
The second one was type tests and type
casts, that did the job but it was unsize
at low level.
And the third one was object oriented
decomposition.
That worked great for evaluation.
Worked, worked also great for show, except
that we had to touch all the classes to
add a new method, but it didn't work for
methods such as simplify, that require non
local knowledge, of the, of the, of the
tree.
In this session, we will see a new way to
decompose objects using pattern matching.
An important observation here is that the
sole purpose of test and access of
functions was to reverse the construction
process.
That means when we construct a node such
as, new sum of e1 and e2, where e1 and e2
are expressions.
Then we pick a particular class of nodes
sum, and we pick the arguments.
And the purpose of decomposition is to
recover what kind of constructor we used
for the note.
That it, whether it was a sum or a number,
say, and what the arguments were.
And that situation is, in fact, very
fundamental and common.
It's so common that many functional
languages, Scala included automate it.
And the technical term for this automated
solution is pattern matching.
So we get pattern matching and Scala by
way of case classes.
A case class definition is essentially
just like a normal class definition,
except that it's proceeded by the modifier
case.
So we write case, class, number, instead
of just class, number.
As before, this defines a trait expression
and two concrete subclasses, number, and
sum.
But we get some added functionality by
adding the modifier case.
The first thing we get is that the Scala
compiler will implicity and automatically
add companion objects.
One for number and one for sum.
And those companion objects will contain
factory methods that construct numbers or
sum elements directly.
You've seen last week that you can create
factory methods like that simply by adding
an apply function to an object. Because
that will let you then write something
like, for instance, number of two. We've
seen last week that this term actually
expands into number..apply Apply of two.
So it will invoke the apply method that we
have defined in this object.
The gist of it is that you can then now
construct objects simply by naming the
class and the arguments, whereas the new
keyword here you can drop.
So, that's a syntactic convenience, but
the orchard classes that we have here are
now all empty.
So, how can we access their components?
And that's what we need pattern matching
for.
So, one way to see pattern matching is as
a generalization of the switch statement
from C or Java.
In C or Java, a switch can only be applied
to numbers, now we can apply to whole
class heirarchies.
In Scala, we use a slightly different some
text,.
Instead of switch e we write e match, and
then come a number of cases.
But to express Eval using pattern matching
in Scala, what you would do is we would
say, well, match the given expression.
With a number of patterns, the first
pattern will say well if it's a number of
some given value n, then return that value
the second expression would say well if
it's a sum with sum operand e1 and then
another operand e2 then evaluate the two
operands and form the sum.
So it's quite legible.
So the general form of a pattern-matching
expression is as follows: We'd start with
a selector () expression e, then comes the
keyword match''' and then come a sequence
of cases.
Each case starts with the keyword'case', a
pattern, a right arrow and an expression.
And the meaning of such an expression
would be that we select the expression e
is matched against all the pattern.
The first pattern that matches would then
lead to the corresponding expression being
evaluated, and if none of the pattern
matches, you would get an exception, which
is called a match error.
So what are patterns built from.
One pattern we've seen was number of N so
that consisted of a constructor that
indicated a class and a variable that
indicated the argument to that class.
And in that case the argument to that
class could be any integer we can't
restrict that in the pattern.
We could also write number of underscore.
That would match the same things as the
number of n but we wouldn't care what the
argument was.
Where as in the number of n the name n
then serves to give us the numeric value
of that number and underscore just means
it's a don't care.
You cannot refer to it later on.
Patterns can also be constants such as one
or true or abc.
Or there could also be a constant set,
let's say N, where N was, like, defined as
well, N=2.2.so So we can use name
constants as well as constant literals.
And then you can take these building
blocks, and compose com-, more complicated
map- patterns from them.
So one example for that would be a pattern
that reads a sum of, let's say number one
and the second operand would be a variable
x. So that would match objects which are
sums with their left operant that is a
number.
And the number needs to have a numeric
value one.
And the right operand of the sum needs to
be a node of type Var.
And the name field of the Var can be
anything but after the pattern in the
right-hand side where we then use the
expression we can refer to x as the name
of that variable.
We'll see an example in a minute.
So here's some of the fine print.
One tricky bit is how to distinguish a
variable such as N which can match
anything from a constant.
Such as N,
Which, in this case, matches just the
number two and nothing else.
Syntactically, we need to find a way to
distinguish one from the other.
So the convention Scala uses here is that
variables always must begin with a lower
case letter.
Whereas, constants should begin with a
capital letter.
The only exceptions here are the reserved
words, null, true, and false.
But these are literals that the compiler
knows about.
There's another restriction on variables,
and that's that the same variable name can
only appear once in a pattern.
So for instance, sum of x,x is not a legal
pattern, you have to write sum of x,y
instead.
So now we know what the form of match
expressions and patterns is.
The question is how are they evaluated.
So let's take an expression of the form
that we've seen that would match the value
of the selector E with the patterns P1 to
PN in the order they're written.
On the next slide, we'll see what that
means exactly, matching an expression with
a pattern.
If a pattern matches, then the whole
expression is rewritten to the right hand
side of the first pattern that matches.
And when we do that, the reference is to
pattern variables in the pattern here out
of place by corresponding parts and the
selector.
But what does, does it mean that a pattern
matches an expression?
Well, we look at the possible forms of
patterns to determine that.
Let's say we have a constructive pattern.
So, there's a class name and some
arguments that would match all values of
type C or a sub type of type C that's also
legal.
That have been constructed with arguments
that, in turn.
Match the patterns P1 one to Pn. If, if
the pattern is a variable pattern, x, and
that matches any value.
And it also will bind the name of the
variable x to this value.
So, in the, in the associated expression
we can then use x as the name for the
value that is matched.
And the third case was a constant pattern
C, so this one matches any value that is
equal to C, where equality is understood
in the sense of equal sequels.
So these rules might have sounded dry and
difficult but it will all become clear if
we look at an example.
So let's look at an application of our
evaluation function which I have put up
here on the side with a trade sum of
number one, number two as an argument.
Well the first thing that we would do as
usual is rewrite that application by the
body of Eval, where the actual argument
replaces the former parameter.
So the result is this expression here.
The E variable here gets substituted with
the actual argument sum of number one, sum
of number two.
The next step is, we have to evaluate the
match expression.
What we need to do here is we have to
match the selector expression against all
the patterns.
The first one doesn't match, because the
constructor is different.
The second one does match,
Sum matches sum.
And that means that the two variables, e1
and e2 will be bound to number one and
number two.
And after that, the expression, all
expression will rewrite to the right hand
side expression here, which is Eval one
plus Eval two.
So that means we're left with Eval. Now,
instead of e1 we use, we would use number
one.
We,
We would use number one.
The, value that was bound to the variable
and instead.instead Of e2, we use number
two.
So, the next step, then, would be that we
have to rewrite the function application
on the left here.
So what we get here is this expression
here.
We have a selector of number one and the
match expression, which is the right hand
side of eval.
And then that's the rest that we have to
add to the result.
If we look at the match expression then
now we see the first pattern is the one
that matches, the number is the same thing
here.
The variable end that's bound to one and
that's the thing we return so one is the
number we return and afterwards we need to
do an eval of number which will give two
as by the same reasoning as what we have
seen just now.
So, there always have to three.
So far all our pattern matching methods
were defined outside of the class
hierarchy, so where there was decomposing
classes from the outside.
But it's also perfectly possible to have
pattern matching methods inside the class
hierarchy as methods of base classes
themselves.
Such as the Eval method that you see here.
So that is just the same as the previous
eval method except now we match on the
receiver object itself.
So you see how this stuff match.
And instead of writing eval of e what,
Of e here.
It would be e1.eval because eval is now a
method of, of, the trait expression.
Either one is perfectly acceptable.
Once you've done that you might also ask
well what are the trade-offs to do it this
way or with the previous object-oriented
decompositions solution we've seen, where
we had essentially be the base trait exper
and the def eval, which was empty and then
in some, there would be a def Eval,
Which was concrete and in number there
would be another.
Both of these designs are perfectly fine
and choosing between them is sometimes a
matter of style, but then nevertheless
there are some criteria that are
important.
One criteria could be, are you more often
creating new sub-classes of expression or
are you more often creating new methods?
So it's a criterion that looks at the
future extensibility and the possible
extension pass of your system.
If what you do is mostly creating new
subclasses, then actually the object
oriented decomposition solution has the
upper hand.
The reason is that it's very easy and a
very local change to just create a new
subclass with an eval method, where as in
the functional solution, you'd have to go
back and change the code inside the eval
method and add a new case to it.
On the other hand, if what you do will be
create lots of new methods.
But the class hierarchy itself will be
kept relatively stable.
Then pattern matching is actually
advantageous.
Because, again, each new method in the
pattern matching solution is just a local
change, whether you put it in the base
class, or maybe even outside the class
hierarchy.
Whereas a new method such as show in the
object oriented decomposition would
require a new incrementation is each sub
class.
So there would be more parts,
That you have to touch.
So the problematic of this extensibility
in two dimensions, where you might want to
add new classes to a hierarchy, or you
might want to add new methods, or maybe
both, has been named the expression
problem.
The name actually comes from this very
example of arithmetic expression, which
served as a case study for the discussion.
Let's finish with an exercise.
We've talked about the show function, I
would like you to implement it.
So what I'm after is a show function that
takes an expression and gives you a string
that represents that expression.
Okay.
So let's see how we would do that.
What I've given you here is, the hierarchy
consisting of the trait expression and the
two case classes number and sum that we've
seen in the course before.
What we're going to do is a worksheet in
which we are going to implement the show
function.
So what should show be like?
Well, we would want to do a pattern match
on the expression.
And then we would have two patterns.
One was number.
It could be any number x, and the other
one would be some, call it left and right.
And, In each case, we have to decide what
we want to return.
In the first case, we would just convert
the number X to a string, and in the
second case, we would just concatenate,
the result of showing the left hand
operand with a plus in the middle and the
result of showing the right hand operand.
So, if you show expression itself, we'd
have type, we can type string.
So let's test the function with some
argument tree as expression.
So, I would do show of, let's say, the sum
of, number of one and number of 44.
What would we get, are, we would get the
string one plus 44 as expected.
So if you haven't had enough of it yet,
then here is another exercise for you,
which is optional and much harder than the
first one.
The question is, if you add case classes
Var for variables and prod for products,
how would you have to change your
definition of show?
The challenge here is to get parentheses
right.
So let's say we have a tree such as a sum
of a product.
Of, a number two and a variable X.
I'm not gonna bother to write numbers and
variables in, in, the, the tree form.
Then, what you would expect is that you
could print that just like two times x
plus y Whereas, if you reversed it, and
you had a product of sum of 2x and y.
Then what you'd want to see is two + x in
parentheses times y.
Because otherwise, if you would just write
two times x plus y, that wouldn't reflect
the structure of this tree.
So the challenge is to put in the right
number of parentheses, the minimal number
of parentheses, so that the structure of
the tree is reflected in the output
stream.