In this session we'll take a quick detour
from the general topic of working with
lists by introducing a new class of data
structures, namely pairs and tuples.
You'll see how pairs and tuples can help
in program composition and decomposition,
and you'll see that by using a somewhat
larger example.
We're going to demonstrate the material in
this session with a somewhat larger
example.
The task is to define a function to sort
lists that's more efficient than insertion
sort.
One good algorithm that's particular
suitable for a functional list
implementation is merge sort.
The idea behind merge sort is as follows:
if a list consists of zero or one
elements, it's obviously already sorted so
there's nothing to do.
Otherwise, we separate the lists into two
sub lists each containing around half of
the elements of the original list.
An easy way to do that would be to simply
take the first n elements of the list and
then the second n element of the lists if
the lengths of the list is 2n.
Once we have the two sub lists we sort
them each in turn and then we merge the
two sorted sub lists into a single sorted
list.
To see the algorithm in code, look at this
function here.
So we would have a function msort for
merge sort.
It takes a list of Ints for the moment we
restrict ourselves to lists of a single
type, and it returns a list of Ints The
first thing is the splitting, so we take
the length of the list divided by two,
that's our n.
If n is zero than, than the original
length was zero or one, because division
truncates towards zero.
In both of these cases, the list is
already sorted so we can simply return it.
If n is not zero,
Then what we do is we split the list at
point N so we'll get to split that
function in a moment.
It returns essentially the first half of
the list and the second half of the list.
Then we sort both of these halfs with the
recursive call to msort and finally we
merge the two sorted lists.
The definition of merge is here, is a
function that takes two lists of Ints and
we have left out its implementation so
far.
So if we look at an implementation of
merge, then here's a possible one.
We're going to improve that later.
So merge takes two lists of Ints and it
would proceed by a pattern match.
First, on the left list, so if the left
list is nil.
Then the merge must consist of all the
elements of the right list so we return
ys.
If the left list is not Nil so let's say
consists of head element x followed by a
tail xs1,
Then we do a pattern match on the right
hand list the ys.
If that is nil then we can simply return
xs.
If that is not nil then we have two head
elements x and y and two tail lists x is
one and y is one.
And what we do is we compare the head
elements with each other.
So if x is smaller than y, then obviously
x must be the first element of our sorted
lists, so we take x followed by a merge of
all the remaining elements are from the
excess list, that's excess one and all the
elements of the ys list.
If, on the other hand, x is not less than
y, then we can take y as the first element
of the sorted list, and we follow that by
a merge of all the x elements followed by
all the other y elements that the ones
that follow y.
So, that would be y is one here.
So we've seen that the M sort algorithm
made use of the split-end function.
Let's take a closer look at this one.
So the split it function on lists returns
two sub lists, namely the elements of a
given list up to the given index and the
elements that start from that index.
And those two lists are in fact returned
in a pair.
Now lets take a little time to look at
pairs and their generalization tupples.
A pair in Scala.
Is written just x and y, where x and y are
the elements of the pair.
So here's an example, you could form a
pair from the string answer and the
number.
22.
Call it pair, and the worksheet would
respond that we have just formed a pair of
type string comma int in parentheses.
So, that's the type of this pair.
And the value of that pair is obviously
the string answer, and the value 42.
So that was a way to form pairs.
We can also decompose pairs using pattern
matching, so that you see down here.
We can type pair and we can match it
against the pattern that contains two
variables, label and value in a pair.
And the worksheet would answer that we
have just defined a label which is a
string and its value is answer.
And we have defined a value which is an
int and it's value is 42.
This, of course, works analogously also
for tuples with more than two elements.
So, you can have triples, quadruples, and
so on.
So far, all the types we've encountered in
Scala were really abbreviations for some
instance of a class type.
And tuples are no exception.
In fact, the tuple type of t1 to tn in
parens is just an abbreviation of the
parameterized type,
Scala.tuple n of t1 to tn, with, as type
parameters.
If we look at tuple expressions then E1 to
EN and parens is equivalent to the
function application skeletal tuple N of
E1 to EN.
And finally, a tuple pattern, p1 to pn, is
equivalent to the constructor pattern.
Again, scala.tuple n p1 to pn.
To make that work, we have to have a look
at the tuple class.
So all the tuple classes are modeled after
the following pattern that you see here
for tuple two.
It's a case class it takes t1 and t2 as
parameters.
And then tuple two would have two fields
which are named underscore one and
underscore two of types t1 and t2
respectively.
That's almost all.
The only other thing we need to do is work
on the ways tuples are represented.
We do not want to print them with tuple
two so we override the two string function
to give us back the usual tuple syntax, so
open parentheses followed by the field
separated by commas followed by a closing
parentheses.
So what this definition of the case class
shows is that the fields of a tuple can in
fact be accessed with names underscore
one, underscore two, and so om up to the
number of elements in the pattern.
That means that instead of the pattern
matching that we've seen.
Say, now label value equals pair.
One could also have written label equals
pair.11.
So the first element of the pair and value
equals pair.2.2.
But the pattern matching form is generally
preferred, because it's both shorter and
clearer.
So, let's do an exercise.
The merge function we've seen so far uses
a nested pattern match and that was rather
long and it was also not so nice because
it didn't reflect the inherent symmetry of
the merge algorithm.
We had, first had to do at pattern match
on the left-hand side and then a nested
pattern match on the right-hand side but,
for merge, it doesn't really matter what
is left-hand and what is right-hand side.
So.
Let's rewrite merge using a pattern
matching over pairs.
So what I want to do here is, I want to
have the same signature as merge, but I
want to start off with saying, well, let's
form a pair of xa, ys, and then match on
the pair.
So,
How would I do that?
To develop an answer for this quiz let's
use the worksheet again.
I've already opened a worksheet for merge
sort and I've put the outline of the merge
sort function as we've seen it so far in
it.
The definition of merge here is still
missing, so let's work on that.
So the suggestion was, let's do a pattern
match on the pair xs ys.
What kind of patterns would apply?
Well, the first pattern that's interesting
is if either one of the argument lists is
nil.
So the first one would be nil nys.
In that case, if the first list x-s is
nil, and then the second list y-s, is just
arbitrary, then we always return y-s,
because there's nothing to merge.
Analogously, if the first list is
arbitrary and the second list is nil, we
always return x-s.
So that leaves us with the third case,
where we say that both lists are non-nil.
Let's write it like that.
So X followed by XX1 and Y followed by
YS1.
And then in that case what do we do.
Well, we now need to compare X and Y.
If it's less than then we know that X is
the first element of our result and we
follow that with merge XX1 and YS.
And if that's not the case and Y is the
first element.
We then follow it with merge of XX and
YS1.
And what we have here is, it complains
that we need to give a result type, which
is correct.
So now it should compile without problems,
and we can now apply merge sort to some
test data, so let's define nums equals
list of two minus four, five, seven, one.
Just to get some data here and we do msort
of nums.
And it did sort them, the way it was
supposed to.