In this session we'll come back to what we
did in the last one.
Namely, proving equational properties of
programs using structural induction.
We will practice the newly learned
techniques in a somewhat larger proof.
For a more difficult example let's
consider the reverse function.
We pick its inefficient definition here
because it's more amenable to equational
proofs.
So as defining process we would have nil
reverses nil and x followed by XS reverse
is the reversal of the list xs followed by
the element X. These two equations are as
we know equivalent to the more efficient
version of fork left and closer to what we
want to prove.
So we pick them which of course does not
prevent us from using at one time the more
efficient definition of reverse.
So what we would like to do is prove the
proposition that XS reverse of reverse is
XS. So to prove this it's an obvious
induction on the list excess, the base
case is really easy. Nil reverse, reverse
is the same thing as nil reverse by the
first law of reverse which says that nil
dot reverse is nil and then we again
invoke the first law To show that, that
expression now is the same as nil, which
establishes the proposition.
Let's look at the induction step so here
we would have X followed by XS, and then a
double reverse.
What can we do with that?
Well, we can apply the second clause of
reverse, which would mean that this
expression here would, can be rewritten to
the right-hand side, excess.reverse
followed by X.
And then we have our reverse on both sides
here.
What else can we do?
Well,
That doesn't seem to be anything obvious.
So let's turn to the right hand side.
The right hand side would read simply X
followed by XS.
So what can we do that?
Well, one thing we could do is apply the
induction hypothesis which says that the
list xs is the same as the list xs
reverse, reverse.
So then we are left with x followed by xs
reverse, reverse and again, there's not
much we can do anymore to this side here.
So both sides, unfortunately, have
simplified to different expressions.
This expression here and I've that
expression there.
So we still need to show that the two
sides are the same and proving it directly
by induction doesn't work as we have seen.
What we can try instead is, we can
generalize this equation.
So the idea is that, instead of just
saying excess to dot reverse here and
here.
We replace that with.
An arbitrary list ys.
So our new lemma that we want to prove is
for, that for any list ys, ys followed by
x reverse is the same as x followed by
ys.reverse. And to prove that equation, we
can use a second induction argument, this
time on the list bias so let's try that.
So, let's look at the base case first.
So here, YS equals nil and the equation we
want to show is that nil followed by
x.reverse is the same as x followed by
nil.reverse.
That's the instansation of the lemma that
we want to show here.
So, what could we do with the left hand
side here?
Well,
By the first close of plus, plus, nil is a
left unit, so this thing simply simplifies
to list of x.reverse. reverse.
Then the next step would be to expand what
list of X is.
So list of X, as we know by its
definition, is X followed by nil.
In the next step then, we would involve
the second clause of reverse to arrive at
this expression here.
When actually there's one intermediate
step that we have to do here.
So by the second clause of reverse, what
would we get?
We would get the list that follows the
head element first so there would be
nil.reverse Followed by, this suffix and
now we can simply find nil.reverse by the
first clause of reverse is just nil.
Where as list of x expands to x followed
by nil.
So, that's how we arrive, at this
expression here.
Now what we can do here is we can again
invoke the first clause of plus, plus to
say nil is a left unit and we're just left
with x followed by nil.
There's one more step to do.
Again by the first clause of reverse we
know that nil.reverse is nil.
Or we've just now used this equation
backwards from going from nil to
nil.reverse And that's the right hand side
if you want to show here.
So we get equality here and the base case
is established.
Let's look at the inductive step.
What we need to do here is show that y
followed by ys, that's our list, followed
by x reverse is the same as x followed by
then y followed by ys reversed.
So let's see how we would go about that
let's work on the left hand side here.
First thing we can do is we can pull out
the y from its binding with the list YS,
using the second list of comcat.
So we have the Y as a head element here,
and then the list YS, followed by list of
X.
The next thing we can do is we can invoke
the law of reverse, which says well
reverse of a list that starts with Y is
the same as reversal of the rest of the
list here.
And the y becomes the last element of the
new list.
The next thing we can do is apply the
induction hypothesis because we see here
that the expression ys followed by list x
reverse, that's the left hand side of the
equation with just the list ys and we can
assume that, that, that, that equation
holds.
So we can rewrite it to the right hand
side of the equation which will be x
followed by yes.reverse. Now we can apply
the first clause of plus, plus to pull out
the accelerant.
And we can apply the second clause of
reverse to establish that Y followed by ys
reverse, is the same as ys reverse
followed by a list of y.
And again we have equality here.
So the auxiliary equation is established
and because the auxiliary equation was the
last thing was needed to prove the main
proposition, that accessory versus
success, we adapt.
So the proof methodology you have seen
here, worked in essentially three steps We
could apply a defining equation, either of
reverse or contact and we could apply it
in two different ways.
So.
What you've seen here, for instance, going
from here to here that was, we invoked the
equation left to right.
The, that was the second clause of plus,
plus, which says plus, plus on a list,
with a head element y is the same thing
as, a list that starts with y.
So we can pull out the y.
And that step is called typically, an
unfold step.
The other, equation of resending step was
what you've seen here in the last step
where we have applied an equation
backwards.
The equation for reverse right.
Y followed by ys reverse is ys reverse
followed by this stuff.
Y.
And that is called a forward step.
So what's important here is that these
equations are real equations in the
mathematical sense.
They can be applied both way-, both ways.
They're commutative.
And the last step that we typically do in
an, a proof like that is apply the
induction hypothesis.
So the proof method that we've seen is
sometimes called the fold-unfold method.
For equational proofs of functional
programs.
So, we finish the session with an
exercise, which is a bit more involved
than the previous ones, and, it's open
ended, so I won't give you a solution
immediately.
So what I want you to do is, prove another
law that's useful, that relates map, and
concatenation.
So the law says that, essentially the, a,
a, map distributes over concat.
For any lists XS, YS and function F, XS
followed by YS and then map the function
is the same thing as mapping the function
over XS, mapping it over YS, and
concatenating the results.
What you need for the proofs is the
classes of plus, plus, that you've seen,
as well as two classes for maps that you
see here.
So, again, they derive directly from the
definition of map.
First clause says to map a function over
the empty list, you would get the empty
list.
The second clause says that to map a
function over a list consisting of x
followed by xs.
What you get is f applied to the head
element x followed by the result of
mapping f over the rest of.