What does it mean for a function program
to be correct?
One possible answer would be that the
definitions in the program satisfy certain
laws.
Often these laws are represented as
equalities between terms.
In this session and the next, you're going
to see proof techniques that can show that
a given set of operations satisfy certain
laws.
The material in these two sessions is an
important dimension of functional
programming because it demonstrates one of
the core claims of FP,
Namely, that it is more amenable to
reasoning about programs.
On the other hand, the programming parts
in this course are not dependent on it,
and none of the assignments that we are
going to do will test this.
So, if you want to go fast, you can skip
the material in the next two sessions.
On the other hand, EPFL students are
required to learn this material because it
will be used in the physical exams that we
do here at EPFL.
Recall the concatenation operation plus,
plus on lists.
What would it mean to say that plus, plus
or the version concat that we've written
is correct?
When one criterion for correctness would
be to say that plus, plus satisfies
certain laws that we would expect from
concatenation.
The laws are that concatenation is
associative, so I can put the parentheses
here either to the left or to the right of
a double concatenation,
And that Nil is right unit and a left
unit.
That means, for any list xs, xs followed
by Nil is xs, and Nil followed by xs is
second xs.
The question is,
Given properties like these, how can we
prove them?
And the answer is, by a new proof
principle that we're going to introduce
now which is called structural induction
on lists.
So to introduce structural induction, it's
good to first look at its close sibling
natural induction.
Natural induction is a proof principle
that you apply when you want to proof
something for all integers greater or
equal some smallest integer b.
The idea there is that to show a property
that the property will hold for all such
integers, you just need to show that it
holds for the smallest element, b, for the
base case,
And then for all other integers, you need
to show the induction step.
The induction step is that if you have P
of n, if you assume P of n, then you can
conclude that P of n plus one also holds.
If you have proven that, then, the
principle of natural induction says that
the property P holds for all integers
greater or equal to b.
So, here's an example to recap natural
induction.
We are looking again at factorial.
So here's the usual definition of
factorial.
And we want to show that for all n greater
or equal to four, we have that factorial
of n is greater or equal to the power of
two to the nth.
So, instead of power, we also could use
the mathematical notation two to the nth.
So, we do that by proof of natural
induction.
The base case obviously is n4.
= four, that's the smallest number we have
to consider,
And there we can just do it by simple
calculation.
Factorial of four is 24, and power of two
to the fourth is sixteen, 24 is greater
than or equal to sixteen.
So, the case is established.
For the induction step then, we assume
that the property holds for n. So, we
would assume that factorial of n is
greater or equal to twonth.
To
The nth, and we have to prove the same
thing for n plus one.
So, let's see what we do.
Factorial of n plus one is equal, or here,
if we've widened that to greater or equal
two n plus one times factorial of n,
because that's how we have defined
factorial,
That's just in second clause in the
factorial definition.
And that is definitely greater than two
times factorial n because we know that n
is greater equal to four, so n plus one is
greater equal to five.
And finally, by the induction hypothesis,
we know that two times factorial n is
greater or equal than two times power of
two to the nth, because our induction
hypothesis was that factorial of n is
greater or equal to power of two to the
nth.
And we can use that induction hypothesis
freely in our proof.
So finally, in the last step, we just
simplify power, so, two times two to the
nth is, as we know, the same as two to the
n plus one.
So, this is power two to the n plus one
and that's precisely what we want to
prove.
Factorial n plus one is proven to be
greater or equal to power of 2n plus one.
So, it follows that the property holds for
all integers n greater equal to four.
So, one thing we've used here implicitly
and quite liberally is that we have
applied reduction steps as equalities to
parts of terms.
So, we have used a reduction in our proof
of saying left-hand side equals right-hand
side.
That works because pure functional
programs don't have side effects, so
reducing a term is really equivalent to
rewriting that term.
There's no other effect to be taken
account of.
That principle is called referential
transparency,
It's an important tool for equational
proofs of functional programs.
So, let's look at structural induction
now.
The principle of structural induction is
analogous to natural induction.
The idea is that we want to prove a
property, P, for all lists, xs.
And to do that, we just need to show that
P of the empty list holds,
That would be the base case.
And that second, for any list xs and any
element x, we show the induction step
which says, assume P of the list xs holds,
then you need to show that P of x followed
by the list xs also holds.
So, instead of constructing numbers
starting from a base case and adding one,
we construct lists starting from the empty
list and consing elements to the top of
the list.
So, back to our comcat example.
We'd like to show that, for any lists xs,
ys, zs, concatenation is associative.
That means, we can put the parentheses
here to the left or to the right.
To do this, we use a structure induction
on the list xs.
From the previous implementation of concat
that you see here, we can distill two
defining clauses for plus, plus.
We can say, well, if the first element xs
is Nil and is followed by a list ys, then
we get ys here.
And the second clause would say, well, if
the first list is x followed by xs1, and
then ys, then the answer would be x
followed by the concatenation of xs1 and
ys.
So, these two clauses here, they're
directly derived from the implementation.
Essentially, they codify what the
implementation does.
So, lets now look at the structure
induction.
The best case would be that our list xs
equals Nil.
So here, we would have, for the left-hand
side, of our equation Nil, followed by ys,
followed by zs. And that can simp, can be
simplified to just ys, followed by zs.
Why? Because of the first clause of plus,
plus which says, Nil, followed by ys is
ys.
Let's look at the right-hand side of the
equation, there we would have Nil follow
up by, the parenthesis to the right, ys
and zs.
But, of course, again, we can evoke the
first clause of plus, plus and simplify to
ys plus za.
So, we have an equality here, and here,
and the cases is established.
So, let's now turn to the induction step.
As the left most list, we would have x
followed by xs, and then ys, and then zs,
and the left-hand side has all parenthesis
going to the left.
How can we simplify that?
Well, one thing we can do is, we can pull
the x out of the parenthasis with the xs.
So now, xs would go with ys,
And the x would be outside of that list.
That we can do by the second clause of
concat which says, concatinating a list
that starts with x is a list that starts
with x and contanition of the rest of the
list.
So, it was the second clause of concat
that said that.
Once we have that, what's the next step?
Well, x is still within another head list,
so we can involved the second clause of
concat again.
And now, we would have x leading the whole
result of the concatination.
So, what's the next step?
Well, the next step would be that, look
here, what you see is xs followed by ys,
followed by zs.
That's actually the left-hand side of our
induction hypothesis which says, assume
you have proven the equation already for
the list xs.
So, we can invoke the induction hypothesis
and rewrite this expression here to the
expression on the right-hand side.
So, parenthesis here, now go to the right.
And that's all we're going to do with the
left-hand side.
Let's now turn to the right-hand side.
So here, we would have the parenthesis go
to the right, ys and zs, let's
concanatinate it and then we have on the
left x followed by xs.
What can we do with that expression?
Well, one thing we can do is, again,
involve the second clause of plus, plus to
pull out the X from the first list here,
And that gives x followed by xs, followed
by ys and zs.
And that is exactly the same as what we
simplified the left-hand side to.
So, the case and with it the property is
established.
Let's do an exercise.
Let's look at the second law for concat,
namely that Nil is the right unit for xs.
Can you show by induction that, that law
holds?
And how many equations do you need for the
inductive step?
Two? Three? Or four?
So, let's see how we would prove this.
Let's do the base case first.
So, the base case would be that the list
xs equals Nil.
Then we have on the left-hand side, Nil
plus, plus Nil, and that is the same as
Nil by the first clause of concat, and
that is already what we need.
So, we have a when, if xs equals Nil, xs
plus Nil is the same as xs.
So, let's have a look at the induction
step. That will be x followed by xs.
So, what we need to prove is that x
followed by xs plus, plus Nil, that should
be the same as x followed by xs.
So, how would we go about that? Well, we
have x inside a, a com, a cons here, so we
can involve the first clause of plus, plus
to put it out.
So, that would be the x followed by xs
plus, plus Nil. Second clause.
And that can be simplified to just x
followed by xs by the induction hypothesis
because we know we can be allowed to
assume that xs followed by Nil is xs,
And that is what we wanted to achieve
here.
So, we have established the case.
So, the answer to the question was, we
need two steps to establish the inductive