In this session, we'll continue our study
of high-order list functions.
We'll introduce a new class of such
functions which are called fold or reduce
combinators.
There's several variance of these
combinators, but what they have in common
is that they insert and give an operator
between adjacent elements of a list.
Another common operation on lists is to
combine the element of a list using a
given operator.
For instance, to take the sum of a list,
you would put a plus between adjacent
elements of the list or to take a product,
you would use, multiplication operation
between, adjacent elements.
To cater for empty lists, so if n equals
zero, we can, we, we deal with that by
actually taking zero plus in the sum and,
one times in the product.
So each time we take the unit value of the
operation as a first operation here on the
left.
So that way the, our definitions of sum
and product can also deal with empty
lists. And that, of course, can be
implemented with the usual recursive
schema,
So could define sum takes a list of Int,
and gives you a an Int. If the list is
Nil, then we return the unit element zero,
Otherwise, we return y plus sum ys.
Again, you might ask how can I generalize
that pattern, and in fact it can be
abstracted using the generic method
reduceLeft. So reduceLeft inserts a given
binary operator between adjacent elements
of a list.
So, if you have a list of from x1 to xn
and we say reduceLeft up and we would put
an operator between each successive
elements of the list.
If we draw that as a tree, it would look
like this one here,
So we have a list of x1,
X2 and so on until we have the last
operation that's the last element of the
list.
Once we have reduceLeft, we can express
sum and product with it.
So sum just would be take the list that
just starts with the zero and then
following the list xs and reduceLeft with
a plus operation.
So it would look like as thing here, would
be zero, X1 plus, plus x2 and so on,
With a plus xn.
And product would be the same thing except
that at the lower left corner of this tree
here you would have a one, and as an
operation you would have a times.
By the way,
Instead of writing, functions like this
one here, two parameters xy then x times
y, Scala actually lets you write that also
in a shorter way using underscores.
So you could just write, underscore times
underscore for this very same function.
The idea is that every underscore
represents a function parameter, so if you
have several ones, then each one would
represent a new parameter going from left
to right.
And the parameters then are implicitly
defined at the next out of pair of
parentheses.
So that's why here you would read this
expression as first saying, well, this
defines two parameters, x times y.
And here are my parentheses, so that's
where I insert the parameters x and y that
I have just synthesized and that gives us
precisely the function that you see here.
So sum and product can, in fact, be
expressed even shorter, like this.
Sum would be zero followed by xs,
reduceLeft with a binary operation plus.
And product would reduceLeft with a,
binary operation times.
So, by its very nature, reduceLeft can
only be applied to non-empty lists.
There's a more general function which is
called foldLeft, which can also applied to
empty lists.
The idea is that forwardLeft takes an
operation and a so called accumulator or
zero element zet as an additional
parameter and that zero element would be
returned if the list is empty.
So the idea here would be that you would
use foldLeft like this.
Here would be a list, then you would call
foldLeft with the zero element and then
you would apply the operation as an
additional argument. And that would then
expand to the following tree here,
And let's say we have the zero element and
x1, and that would be combined with the
operation, and then the other operation
would take x2 and so on until finally the
last topmost operation, would combined the
result of all the previous elements with
the last element as right upper.
So, sum and product can also be defined as
follows, using foldLeft instead of
reduceLeft. For sum, we say fold with a
plus and zero element is zero, and for
product, we fold with a times and the unit
element is a one.
So here you see some possible
implementations of foldLeft and reduceLeft
as methods in class list.
So reduceLeft, let's look at the type
first.
It would take an operation that takes two
operands of the list element type and
returns a result of the type and the
result of reduceLeft is again, the list
element type.
The list must be non-empty,
So in the case of Nil, we throw an error,
Nil reduceLeft.
And if the list is non-empty, so it comes
just of a head x and the tail xs,
Then, what we do is we forward to the
foldLeft method with a zero element x.
So that's the element that will be
returned when xs is empty and the
operation we have pass to reduceLeft.
Now that leaves us with foldLeft.
So type of foldLeft is a bit more
complicated.
Let's ignore it for the moment.
We'll get back to it.
But let's look at the body.
So if the list is empty, then foldLeft
would return its zero element.
Zeta.
If the list is non-empty, then what we do
is, we have another call to foldLeft with
zero element that's now the operation
applied to the former zero and the first
element of the list.
So lets draw this.
So, in the first iteration, foldLeft would
be applied recursively, with the
accumulator of the first element of the
list, which I call here x1, and the
operation.
Now, the second call would then apply the
operation to the zero that we pass into
the second call, this, this subtree here,
and the second element of the list and so
on. our accumulator grows with each
recursive call to foldLeft, until finally
we are,
Have an accumulator that looks like that.
And there are no further elements in the
list, so the list is empty and in that
case we would return the accumulator.
So it's a classic loop with an accumulator
that implements foldLeft.
So let's look at the type of foldLeft now.
So, we know that the list elements are all
of type T,
So I can write T: for each one of those.
The zero can be of a different type, u.
Then to make things work out, because that
subtree here is the next zero, we must
also have that the subtree has type u and
so on.
All the subtrees have type u, up to the
result of the foldLeft.
So that type annotated tree matches the
types that you see here.
Type u is arbitrary,
Zero has the type u.
The operation, then, must have the type
that takes a u and a T to a u and the
result of the final foldLeft operation is
a u.
Now we've seen that foldLeft and
reduceLeft produce trees that lean to the
left.
So it would make sense to have a dual pair
of operations that unfold to trees that
lean to the right.
These are called foldRight and
reduceRight.
Let's look at reduceRight first.
So reduceRight puts an operator between
adjacent elements, but now the parentheses
go to the right, not to the left.
So, visually represented as trees it would
like, would look like this.
So we would have the first operation takes
x1, and the whole result of producing a
foldRight of the rest of the list and at
the end, I would xn minus one and xn here.
So we get a tree that leans to the right.
Foldright is, analogous to foldLeft.
It takes, again, a zero element or an
accumulator here,
So we would, what we would see here, it
would be something similar.
It would be an operation that takes the
first element.
Then the second element of the list if it
exists, and so on, until it finally it
takes the final element of the list and
combines it with the zero here.
So, if the list is empty, reduceRight
would be undefined, just as reduceLeft is
not defined for empty lists.
So if you look at the possible
implementations of reduceRight and
foldRight and class lists, then here they
are.
So for reduceRight, it takes again a
binary operation from T, T to T.
Would say for empty list, it's again
undefined.
If the list consist of a single element,
then that's the element that's going to be
returned.
And otherwise, it's going to be the result
of the operation applied to the first
element of the list and a recursive call
of reduceRight to the rest of the list.
For foldRight, we have a small typo here,
so it takes a type parameter which is a u
and a zero element of type u and then an
operation and it's, implementation will
simply be for an empty list, we return
zero element, as for foldLeft.
For a non-empty list, we return the
operation that takes the headed element of
the list and the result of applying
foldRight recursively to the tail of the
list.
So to expand it out, if we had a non-empty
list, what we would get is, we would have
the first element of the list x1 applied
with operation of recursively applying
foldRight to the tail of the list.
So, let's say there's a second element x2,
Again recursive call until finally we
would have the last element,
Then we would hit an empty list and the
result of foldRight is set so you see the
same right leaning tree that I've shown
you on the previous slide.
Quickly look at types so the xn's again
all have type T's as before.
The zeta is type u.
And then, it follows that the operations
must also return the same type u, because
like the zeta, they are all used as a
right-hand operand offer successive
operation.
And then u is also the type that is
returned from foldRight.
So foldLeft and foldRight produce
different trees,
Left leaning trees and right leaning
trees,
But maybe they produce the same result.
In fact, if our operator is associative
and commutative,
One can show that foldLeft and foldRight
are equivalent functionally,
Even though there might be a difference in
efficiency.
But sometimes, only one of the two
operators is appropriate.
So we see this in an exercise.
Here is another formulation of the concat
function that you've seen before.
So let's look at this in a little bit more
detail.
So, what we mean here is that we have, do
a foldRight over a list xs with zero
element ys and the operation is a cons.
So let's draw that out graphically.
So, we would have x1 operation cons,
X2, operation cons, and so on,
Until to, the end of the list operation
cons,
And then we would have the list ys.
Okay.
So, how can we represent the list ys?
How can we write that out?
So let's delete that here.
Well, the way we write a list is, we write
it as a tree of cons cells,
So it would be y1 cons, y2 and so on,
until yn and Nil.
So what do we see here?
Well, it's just a single list that
consists of element x1 to xn and then y1
to yn.
So that, that shows us that, the operation
cons here, with the ys as zero element,
provides exactly the list that we need for
the concatenation.
Now, that was okay for foldRight.
Can you replace foldRight by foldLeft
here?
In fact, you can but you should tell us
what is goes wrong.
The types might not work out,
The resulting function might not
terminate,
Or the result might not be what you want.
For instance, it could be the reversed of
the result that, that you what to have get
back from concat.
.
Okay. so, to answer this question, let's
simply type the definition of concat to
our worksheet and we place foldRight by
foldLeft and we get the error message,
value:: is not a member of the type
parameter T.
So, what happened here was well, we do a
foldLleft over a list xs,
So we apply the operation to each element
of that list xs and that's a T and in fact
the operation cons is not applicable to
arbitrary elements, it's only applicable
to lists.
So that's why what the right answer is we
would get a type error in this case.