So far,
All operations on lists were first order.
That means, the functions took lists of
primitive types as arguments and returned
them as results.
In this session, we're going to change
that.
We're going to introduce higher order list
functions that work on lists and take
another function as argument.
We will see that with just a handful of
these higher order functions, we can
describe a great variety of different
tasks.
The examples in the previous sessions have
shown that functions of lists often have
very similar structure.
In fact, we can identify several recurring
patterns, such as transforming each
element in a list in a certain way,
Or retrieving from a list all elements
that satisfy a given criterion, or maybe
combining the elements of a list using an
operator.
And since we are in a functional language
which allows programmers to write generic
functions using high auto-functions, we
can apply the same techniques to functions
over the lists.
So in this session, we are going to be
interested in higher order functions over
the lists.
Our first common operation is to transform
each element of a list, and then return
the list of results.
So for instant to multiply each element of
a list by the same factor, you could write
a function scale list which takes a list
of doubles as input and a factor and
returns a list of double and what it does
is, well if the input list is nil, it just
returns it unchanged, and otherwise it
multiplies the first element of the list
by the factor, and it does a recursive
call of scale list with the rest of the
list and factor.
So, obviously, that function would
multiply each element of the list by the
same factor.
That scheme can be generalized to a method
map on the list class which can apply in
arbitrary operation to all elements of a
list.
So here's a simple way to define map on
the abstract class list of t.
We would say def map and map takes a
function from t to some.
Other type, u, which could be the same as
type t, or it could be different.
So, u is a type parameter of MAP.
And then it returns a list of u.
And then the body of MAP is just the body
of scale lists, but now generalized.
So, in the case of nil, we return the list
unchanged.
If the list is non-nil, then we apply the
function,
F to the first element X,
And we follow that with a recursive call
of xs.mapf.
In fact the actual implementation of map N
class list and this kind of standard
library is a bit more complicated for
several reasons.
First, the actual definition is in fact
terra cursive.
Where as this definition isn't you see
after the call to map you still have a
call to cons.
The second the actual implementation to
maps for arbituary collections not just
lists.
But for understanding map list definition
here we'll do very well.
So using map, we can now write scale list
much more concisely, so much more
concisely that, that it's hardly worth
writing a different function for it.
We would just say, scale list of XS and a
factor S, map XS map, with the function
that takes an X and multiplies X by the
factor.
So here's an exercise for you.
Let's take a function square list that
squares each element of a list, then
returns the result.
There are two possible ways to do that,
either with pattern matching or using map.
I invite you to try both possible ways by
filling in the three triple question marks
in the definition of square lists here and
the definition of square lists down there.
So let's see how we would do that.
In the paren.
Matching definition to take the squares of
an empty list we would surely return the
empty list again.
To take the squares of a list with a head
y and a tail ys, what do we do?
Well, we start by taking the square of y
and we follow that by a recursive call of
square list.
Of Y-S.
So far so good.
I think by now we all know how to do these
things cold.
But, let's see whether we can do it
shorter using map.
Well, to use square list with map, what
can we do?
Well, we map it by the function that takes
an X, and returns X times X.
And that's it.
So obviously the definition with map is
much shorter and I would, argue also
clearer than the one that uses
paramatching and recursion.
So here's another common operation on
lists, selecting all elements that satisfy
a given condition.
For instance, you might want to select all
elements from a list that are positives.
Here you have a function pause alps.
It takes a list of int, gives you back a
list of int.
And the para matching definition would
read as you see here.
So for the empty list we can just return
it.
If its non-empty and the first element is
in fact greater than zero it's positive,
then we include it in the result list.
So we return the first element followed
by.
Pause LM's of the rest of the list.
And, otherwise, we just do pause LM's of
the rest of the list.
So, the first element gets dropped, and we
just filter the remainder of the list with
pause LM's.
Again, this pattern can be generalized to
the method filter in the list class.
So here you see the definition of filter.
It takes now a predicate that takes an
element of the list element type t, that
gives you back a boolean, and it will
return a list of t's.
The definition is an obvious
generalization of posElems that we've seen
before.
So we match on the current list.
If it's nil then we return to middle list.
And if it's not nil and the head of the
list XX satisfies our predicate So P of X
is true.
Then we return X followed by X dot filter
P.
And otherwise just accept that filter P.
Again using filter we can write poseElems
much more concisely.
We will just write excess filter x such
that x is greater than zero.
Besides filter, there are also other
methods that extract sub-lists a list
based on some predicate.
You see the list of these methods here.
Rather than going through the list, I just
wanted to show them in action in a new
worksheet.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
take the data definitions of the previous
worksheet and create a new worksheet.
Call this, call this list far.
.
And we have our test data here.
And what I'm, what we're gonna do is lets
say the first one would be numbs filter so
all numbers greater than zero, so that
would have filtered out the -four here.
If we do, nums filter not X, X greater
than zero, what do you expect to get?
Right.
You'd expect to get just the negative
number, -four.
The other.
And as that was partitioned.
Partition is like filter and filter not in
one go.
So, if you write that here.
Then what you see is you get a pair of two
lists.
The first list contains all those elements
for which the predicate is true.
So that was the positive elements.
And the second list contains all those
elements for which the predicates is
false.
So you see the partition is just like
filter and filter not as a pair.
However it will run in a single traversal
through the input list numbers, where as
if you do first a filter and a filter not
you would get two traversals.
The next two functions are a bit different
in that they look at a prefix and a suffix
of a list.
So what I can do here is I can say, Nums
TakeWhile.
X, X greater than zero.
So what that gives me is the longest
prefix of the list, such that the
predicate is true.
So here I would say okay two is greater
than zero.
But then at minus four, I would stop,
because minus four is not greater than
zero.
So it will, any further elements will not
take part in take while.
That's the main difference between take
while and filter.
Filter will always.
Select all elements in the list that
satisfy the criteria, whereas take while
will only take the longest prefix of the
list.
The opposite of take while is drop while.
So, let's write that.
So take while and drop while relate to
each other such, just like take and drop
relate to each other.
Drop while would then return the remainder
of the list, without the prefix taken by
take while, so it would be the list that
starts with a negative element and then
goes until the end of the input list.
And finally, where we had partition, that
combined a filter and filter not, we also
have an operation that combines a take
while and a drop while.
That operation is called span.
So if we do that then what we will see is
that it will give us essentially the
combination of a TakeWhile, that was a
list two and a DropWhile.
But like Partition, it will only need a
single traversal, not two.
Let's apply the function that we've seen
so far in an exercise.
The task is to write a function pack that
packs consecutive duplicates of list
elements into sublists.
So if you apply pack to this input list
here, we would expect to get back a list
of lists, where the first sublist is
formed from, from the three consecutive
A's here.
The second sublist has just a single B.
The third sublist has the two consecutive
C's.
And the final sublist has the trailing A
here.
The idea is to use a template like this
one here, we have a defined pack to be a
generic function over type lists of T,
returns a list of lists of T, Obviously if
the list is empty, then that's what we
would expect back.
So the only case to handle is really this
case here.
If the list is nonempty, what do we do?
I've already copied my input list data and
the template of the pack function, so the
only case to fill in is when the list is
nonempty, consisting of a head, X, and a
tail, XS.
Which of the six functions here would be
applicable?
Well, what we wanna do is take off a
leading sub list and then do something
with the rest of the list.
So it's a combination of take while and
drop while and that's what span would give
us.
So let's set up a para match first rest
equals xs span and what should be the
predicate be.
Well we say take elements as long as they
are equal to x, the leading elements of
the list.
Once we have that we would say, first is
already the sublist that will constitute
the first element of our list, and the
other elements would be the result of a
recursive call of pack to the rest of the
list.
And that gives us our function, pack, so
let's apply pack to our data list.
Pack of data gives us.
A list consisting of three As, one B, two
Cs, and an A.
Just what we needed.
We're not done yet as a second exercise I
would like you to use Peg to write a
second function and code that produces a
run length encoding of a list.
Run length encodings are often used for
compressions of images and other files.
The idea is to encode n consecutive
duplicates of an element of the list as a
pair xn.
So instead of writing the element n times
we just have a single entry pair of what
the element was and how many times we have
written it.
For instance.
Is in code of the list that we've seen
before should give us.
A3, B1, C2 and again, A1.
So, let's go again to the worksheet to
solve that.
What we're interested in is a function in
code, and it should also be generic taking
a list of T, and now it would return a
list of pairs of the element and the count
which is an integer.
And what should the body of encode be?
Well, it turns out that most of the work
has already been done by pack.
Once we have a packed list.
All we need is, is a simple transformation
to get to the run length encoding.
And that transformation will be applied to
each element.
So the natural operation to use is a map.
So what we do is we start with pack of
excess.
And we then apply our map.
A pack of Xs lead to, here's a list of
lists.
So if we apply our map then we have get
each individual sub list as an argument.
Let's call that sub list Ys here and what
do we do in the map, well, we return a
pair where the first element of the pair
is the first element in the sub list and
the second element of the pair is the
length of that sub list.
There we are with encode.
All we need to do is encode of data.
To get a single test case.
And we get what we expected, a 3B, one C2,
and A1.