This session introduces more utility
methods on lists.
You'll find out what these methods do and
where they're useful, and you'll also
learn how they're implemented in terms of
the fundamental operations on lists and
[inaudible] matching.
So in this session, you're going to find
out about more methods that are useful for
list processing.
First one is the length method, so that
gives you the number of elements that are
in the lists.
You know already about head and tail, so
if you have a list that I'm now writing as
essentially a contiguous sequence of
elements.
Then head would be the first one here and
there would be rest.
The duals of head and tail are called init
and last.
So Last would, give you the last element
in a list.
And Init would give you all elements
except for the last.
Then there's also take and drop.
So take takes an arbitrary prefix of
elements in the list, whereas drop would,
they could give you back all the elements
in the list except for some prefix so it
would drop a number of elements from the
beginning and then give you back the, the
remainder of the list.
And finally, we can also select into a
list, that's written xs of n, where n is
an index, and that's expanded, as usual,
to a call of the applied method of lists.
So alternatively, we could also write xs
apply n, that the same thing,
And that would give you the element of xs
at index n,
Where as usual, in this is R numbered from
zero.
Here are some more utility methods for
lists.
You might be interested in new ways to
create lists.
The first method here is concatenation,
it's written xs plus, plus ys and that
gives you the list that consists of all
elements of xs followed by all elements of
ys.
And that's reverse which, as the name
says, will you give a list that contains
the elements of xs in reversed order and
finally that's updated.
So updated is, in a sense the functional
equivalent of mutable updates in an array
when you change an element in an array.
Of course you know that you can't do that
in a list because lists are immutable.
But what you can do, is you can return a
list that contains all the elements of the
list xs here, except at a given index n
where the new list would contain the x.
So.
It's a new list that corresponds to the
old list the x's in all elements except
one.
Besides creating, there are also two
functions for finding elements.
There is indexOf, which is very much like
indexOf, on let's say a Java string.
So it, finds, tries to find an element x
in a list xs and would give you back its
index if, of the first occurrence of x if
it's found in the list and minus one if x
does not appear in the list.
And then there is contains.
So, xs x contains x,
Is asks whether the element x appears in
the list of xs at all.
So it's the same as xs indexOf x quite are
equal to zero.
Now, let's look a little bit more at the
implementation issues.
We know that the we've had is simple field
selection, so it's a very small constant
time.
Can last be implemented just as
efficiently?
Tail, again, is just a simple selection of
the, of the second field of a list,
constant time.
Can it be implemented at the same
efficiency?
Well, let's see first how we would
implement last.
As I said, last is a method in class list,
but to study its implementation we, we
might as well define it as an external
function outside the list class.
If we do that, then last would have the
signature that you see here.
So it takes a list of t for an arbitrary
type t, and gives you back a t,
The element type of the list.
And t,
Usual implementation of last would be to
say well let's see what the list is.
Last of an empty list should give you an
error just like head of an empty list
gives you an error.
Last of a list that contains a single
element would give you just that element.
And finally, last of a list that consists
of a head followed by some tail would give
you the last element of the tail.
So we see, by looking at this
implementation, that last takes a number
of steps that's proportional to the length
of xs.
We need to take one recursion for each
element in the list here.
Let's do the same as an exercise within
it.
So, I've given you another outline of an
external function, init, analogous to
last.
It takes a list of t for arbitrary t
returns a list of t.
Its not defined of list of empty.
So all you need to do is fill in the
triple question marks for the two
patterns. What happens if the list consist
of one element and what happens in the
case where list is a general first element
y followed by a list ys?
So lets see how we would solve this.
The initial part of a list that consists
of a single element would be the empty
list.
So, we would return list of empty. The
initial part of a list that consists of a
head y and some tail ys.
What would that be?
Well, it would certainly contain the head
and then we would have a recursive call to
init ys.
So, one thing that I've just not yet said
explicitly here but which is important, is
that the patterns are actually matched in
sequence.
So, what this pattern would match is any
list of a single element.
What this pattern then would match is any
list of, length two or more,
Because we have already covered lists of
zero and one elements.
So that means that the recursive call to
init on that list cannot fail,
Because we know that the, the size of ys
is, is at least one.
So let's look at another fundamental
operation on lists concatenation.
How is concatenation implemented?
Well, you'll remember that if we write xs
and then the triple colon for
concatenation ys,
That really is the same as the call of the
method triple colon with receiver ys and
xs as the argument.
So it's a prepend of xs on top of the
right hand side ys.
Very much like the prepend function that
you've implemented last week, but now, you
prepend a whole list not just the single
element.
To find out how the implementation of that
can be done, it's actually just as good to
write a stand-alone function.
I've given you the signature of concat
here.
So, that will be a function that
concatenates and ys like you see here.
How could that be implemented?
Well, so far, everything we did was by a
pattern match on the list and question,
But now there are two lists we deal with,
xs and ys.
So what list should we pattern match on?
Well, the other observation is that, once
we were done with pattern matching
typically reconstructed lists from left to
right.
We were asking the question, what is the
first element of the result list and what
is the remainder.
Now, does the first element of the result
list, does it depend on xs or on ys.
Well, clearly it depends on xs.
So it makes sense to pair and match in xs.
So, let's do that.
We have the standard match on xs.
The empty and the case where the list is
nonempty with a head z and a tail zs.
Ys is already taken as a name here.
So for the empty list, what should concat
return?
Well, obviously, the empty list
concatenated with sum list ys is the list
ys,
So that would be our result.
If the list is not empty, so it contains a
head z and tail zs. You could, next
question is, well what is the first
element of the result list?
While it's the first element of xs, and
that would be z and the remainder.
While the remainder would simply be the
result of concatenating the rest of the
left list, which we call letters now here,
and the right list, ys.
So, that gives us the complete
implementation of concat.
Now, what is its complexity?
Well, we see that we will need a call of
concat for each element of the left list.
So complexity would be correspond to the
length of the list excess.
Sometimes we use mathematics notations
with the double bars to indicate the size
of something.
So now that we have seen concat, let's
look at reverse.
How can that be implemented?
Let's try by writing a stand-alone
function.
So we would have a function reverse,
It take xs,
A list of arbitrary element type t.
Gives us back a list that's a reversal of
xs.
Let's start with the usual pattern match
on the shape of xs.
So if that list is empty, then, the
reversal of an empty list would give the
list itself.
If that list is nonempty, let's say
consisting of a head element y and a tail
ys. What do we do?
Well, one thing we know is that the list
will end with the element y.
The first element becomes the last element
and before that, or before that, we just
have a recursive call of reverse, ys and
then comes the head element, y, in the
second list concatenated.
So that would be the definition of
reverse.
So the next question is, given that
definition, what is its complexity?
Well, let's have a look.
We know that concatenation is linear,
Text time proportional to the size of the
list on the left hand of the concatenation
operator.
So that list is a list that grows from one
to the length of excess, that's for the
first element that we concantenated would
be the length of xs minus one.
So that's linear in the size of excess.
And furthermore, we do one step for each
element in the reverse list because we go
through each element of ys, and put it at
the end of the reverse this. So that gives
us a factor of n,
For the concat times n for the reversal
where n is the size of success.
So we get quadratic complexity of reverse
which is a bit disappointing because we
all know that if you have, let's say an
array or a link list, a mutable link list
of pointers,
Then we all know how to reverse in linear
time.
We'll see later on how we might do better
and get down the complexity of reverse,
But for the moment, we'll leave it like
that.
So, here's an exercise.
The question is, how could you write a
method that removes the n'th element of a
list xs?
If n is out of bounds in the list, then we
would just return the list xs.
So, as an example, if we call, removeAt at
index one and the list of a, b, c, d, then
we would expect the get back the list a,
c, d.
The element at index one would be removed.
So, let's grab a worksheet to see how we
could answer that question.
Let's write a method signature.
It takes an Int as an index and a list of
Int,
And we want to have the list that consists
of all elements except the ones at the
index n.
So how would we do that?
Well, remember you have taken drop already
as operations.
So, the easiest way to do that would be to
say well, it's xs, take the first elements
n,
Followed by xs drop n plus one.
So it means we take the first elements of
the x,
We skip one and then we take the rest of
the x elements xs, which would be
expressed by the expression xs drop n then
plus one.