This session will be concerned with
parameterization techniques.
The question is how can we make a
definition, such as mergesort more general
so that they can be used not for a
singular argument type.
We'll see in this session how
parameterization by either functions or
objects helps in this respect.
One shortcoming of the merge-sort function
we've seen last session was that it can
only be applied to list of X.
But it makes sense to, apply the same
function or similar function also to lists
of other element types such as strings or
doubles or booleans and so on.
How could we achieve that?
Well, the most straightforward way to do
that would be let's parameterize merge
sort.
So instead of int I have a type parameter
T now.
But that wouldn't work because the
comparison function wouldn't be
well-defined.
So let's have a look at that.
Here I have the merge sort that we have
defined at the end of the last session.
Let's just replace the int by a T, and
make T a type parameter.
And the same thing here for the merge,
which takes the type parameter of the
enclosing function msort, and what do we
see?
Well, we see one error here, which says
that value less is not a member of type
parameter T.
Of course, now that our at least elements
can have an arbitrary type. We can no
longer be sure that there is, in fact, a
less than function defined on elements of
this type.
So what can we do?
Well, the next refinement of our idea
would be to parameterize merge with the
necessary comparison function.
So let's see how that would work.
We would have a polymorphic function msort
with a type parameter t.
And in addition to the list that we pass
to msor we also pass a less than function
with an lt here that takes two ts and
returns a Boolean and the contract for LT
would be that it should return the result
of comparing its two elements with the
less than.
Once we have that then we have to apply LT
in two instances.
Let's see how we would do that in the work
sheet, so I have here.
I pass an LT, which takes two T's, and
returns a Boolean.
And then I can write here, instead of x
less than y, I can write here LT of x and
y, in the merge function.
That's good, but, I have another problem
here.
For the sort here, of course, I have to
pass the correct LT function into the two
recursive calls of msort.
And finally, for the numbers here, I have
to pass the right version of LT into
numbers.
So, one way to do that would be to say,
well, let's take an int X and a Y, which
is also of int, type int, and return X
less than Y.
And that would compile.
And if we run it, we get the same result
as before.
What we can do now is we can also add a
data of another type.
Let's call, let's say fruits.
That would be a list of let's say, apple.
Pineapple,
Orange, and banana.
And we can now apply msort to the fruits
list.
All we have to do is pass the right
comparison function.
So this one here would take two strings.
And it will return the result of the Java
call x compared to y, and that, that must
be less than zero.
So compare to is a method on Java string
which returns minus one if the first
string is less than the second string, a
zero if they're equal, and one if the
first one is greater than second one.
So since we want minus one, we have to
test here less than zero.
Let's run the worksheet, and we see that
indeed, our list of fruit has been sorted
in lexical, graphical order.
In fact, we can simplify the, calls here
further, because the types of the two
function values are not necessary.
We can leave them out and the Scala
compiler will infer them.
So we could also write something like
that, and, That would give us the same
list obviously.
And we could also leave the types out in
the second function values of the strings.
The reason why that works is that this
kind of compile is figure out, it's able
to figure out that X and Y need to have
type int by simply analyzing the call of M
sort of nums, because nums is a list of
int.
It will therefore know that the type
parameter of M sort must be int and that
will determine in turn the types of the
function parameters here.
That discussion shows that it's usually
advantages if you have several parameter
lists and one of them is a function value,
to put the function value last.
Cuz then you have a better chance that the
type's already inferred by the time the
compiler will type check the function
value and that means you don't have to
write them explicitly.
So, so far, we have parameterized the
merge sort function with our own less than
operation, which is perfectly possible,
but on the other hand, we could also use a
predefined class.
There is already a class in the standard
library that represents orderings with
less than function, but also all the
other, all ordering functions like greater
than, less than or equal, and so on.
That class is called scala.math.ordering
of T.
So the type parameter T tells us what's
the type of the elements that are compared
in the ordering class.
Instead of parameterizing with the less
than function directly, we could also
parameterize msort with ordering instead.
So, wouldn't be much that we have to
change.
So in the worksheet, we'll have a look at
it.
So instead of less than, we would have a
paramenter ord of type ordering of t.
We should import that first.
Import math dot ordering.
And then instead of the less than call
here we would call the less than method of
our ordering type.
And instead of passing less than along, we
can pass order along.
And in our, actual calls, we can now use,
the predefined orderings, but the first
one would be ordering.int.
That's the ordering on integers that is
defined as a value in the ordering object,
and for the other one, it would be
ordering.string.
And the results are the same as before.
Unsurprisingly.
So, there's one remaining problem in.
Passing a round piece LT or all values are
rather cumbersome.
Would be much nicer if we could somehow
synthesize the right comparison operation
directly just given the type T.
And we can make it at least appear that
way by avoiding passing or implicit,
explicitly making it an implicit
parameter.
So the only thing here is that we write
implicit ord cut orderings.
So all I do now is I write implicit in
front of the.
What parameter.
Nothing changes so far, but what it means
is that I can now leave out the actual,
parameter in a, in a call, and the
compiler will synthesize one for me.
So I can leave out the ort here, and I can
leave out the ort there.
And I can even leave out arch in the
ordering.int or the ordering of string and
everything would still compile and run as
before.
So I can get rid, get rid of the ordering
of string as well and its still the same
thing.
So now my program is just as concise and
nice as in the case of list of int's but
it is fully parametric.
How did that happen?
How, how could we achieve that?
Well, what actually happens is that when
you write an implicit parameter, and you
don't write an actual argument that
matches that parameter, the compiler will
figure out the right implicit to pass,
based on the demanded type.
So what are the precise rules for that?
So let's say a function takes an implicit
parameter of type T.
The compiler will then search for an
implicit definition.
So that's a parameter or a vowel or an
object that's marked implicit.
And that has a type that's compatible with
T.
And finally, it's visible at the point of
the function call.
Or it's defined in the companion object
associated with T.
So in our case.
Here we have the first word that we left
out here that was visible at the point of
the function call, because the word here
is visible where as the orderings that we
left out here, they were defined in the
companion object of the ordering class and
therefore also qualified as implicit
arguments.
So once the compiler has done that search,
if it comes back with a single more
specific definition, that definition will
t-, be taken as the actual agrument.
So the arg-, that will be the synthesized
argument for the implicit parameter.
And otherwise, if the compiler finds
nothing or if it finds several possible
candidate definitions, then it's an error.
So let's test your understanding with a
simple quiz.
Consider the line in the definition of
msort where you have the two recursive
calls.
So that would be this line here.
Which.
Definition of ordering is implicitly
inserted by the compiler here and here.?
Is it ordering.int, or ordering.string, or
the Ord parameter of the N sort function?