In this session, we look at the
implementation of for-expressions.
It turns out that there is a systematic
translation scheme that maps
for-expressions to certain combinations of
higher-order functions.
So, we're going to see in this session
that the syntax of for-expressions is
closely related to three higher-order
functions,
Namely map, flatMap, and filter.
The first observation is that all of these
functions can be defined in terms of for.
So for instance, to have a functioned like
map,
I call it the mapFun that applies a
function f to every element on the list
xs.
We could write for x taken from xs yield
f(x).
That's the same thing what that map is
usually.
Flatmap would be for x taken from the
first list, and y taken from the result of
applying f to each element of the first
list, yield y.
So, that's a flatMap.
And filter finally can be expressed as a
for like this, for x taken from xs, if the
predicate p is true at x, then yield x.
So, map, flatMap, and filter can all be
expressed as for-expressions.
But in reality it goes the other way.
What the Scala compiler will do is it will
translate for-expressions to combinations
of map, flatMap, and a lazy variant of
filter.
So, we're going to see now the former of
translation scheme.
For simplicity we limit ourselves to
simple variables and generators.
So, I'm going to talk only about simple
variables x on the left-hand side of the
generator where, of course, in general,
you could have an arbitrary pattern in
this position.
So, lets look first that a simple
for-expression that consist of just one
generator for x taken from e1 yield e2,
for arbitrate expressions e1 and e2.
So, that would be translated by the Scalar
compiler to an application of map, namely
e1 map the function that takes an x and
returns e2.
The two are the same thing.
Now, that we've treated for-expressions
with a simple generator, let's look at
more complicated ones.
The first form that we want to look at is
a for-expression that consists of a
generator, followed by a filter,
Possibly followed by other generators and
filters.
That for-expression would be translated to
the one that you see down here.
So, it's again, a for, but the filter has
been eliminated.
Instead, we pull the filter into the
generator.
So, we let x range over e1, and then
there's an application of with filter,
which takes the function value x to f. So,
what happens with, with filter is that the
expression e1, the collection that gets
returned from e1 is filtered with that
predicate.
Now, that we've looked at for-expressions
consisting only of a single generator,
let's look at more complicated ones.
The first for-expressions that we are
going to look at would have a generator,
its taken from e1 followed by a filter f,
and that in turn could be followed by
further generators or filters, which are
here subsumed by d.
That for-expression can be rewritten to
the following one.
Another for-expression that contains a
generator.
And the filter has been absorbed into the
So, the generator now reads x taken from
e1 withFilter,
The anonymous function that takes an x and
gives us back the expression f.
With filter, as a first approximation you
can read it like filter.
So, what happens here, is that the
generator will be reduced to all those
elements that pass the condition f.
In fact, withFilter is a lazy variant of
filter that means it doesn't immediately
produce a new data structure of all the
filtered elements that would be wasteful.
What it does instead is it remembers that
any following call to map or flatMap has
to be filtered by the function f.
So, it's essentially a smarter version of
filter.
The third and last form of for-expressions
that we need to cover is the one where, a
leading generator is followed now, not by
a filter, but by another generator, and
that in turn, can be followed by an
arbitrary sequence of filters and
generators s.
That for-expression will be translated
into a call of flatMap so the idea here is
that, if we take the for-expression that
takes all the remaining computations,
So we generate a y from e2,
Then we do something more and then we
yield e3.
That will be a collection valued operation
because we have a generator here.
And what we need to do is we need to take
everything that comes out of this
for-expression and flatMap it.
That means concatenate it all into the
result list. That's precisely what happens
here.
So, we do, do an e1 flatMap. with a
function that takes an x, and gives us
back a for-expression that has now one
fewer generator.
So, it starts with the generator y taken
from e2 and s, and then we get back e3.
So, what happened in the first case was a
direct translation into a map.
What happened in the second and third case
was that we translated a for-expression
into one that has one less element, so it
either has one fewer filter or one fewer
generator.
This one here had one fewer filter.
The filter here has gone.
Whereas, this one here has a
for-expression, a nested for-expression,
that now lacks the first generator.
So, each of these translation steps can be
repeated, yielding simpler and simpler
for-expressions, until finally, we must
hit the simplest case, and that, then,
would translate into a map.
So, that's how the translation scheme
works.
Let's see it as, in an example.
Let's take our for-expression that looks
at the pairs of indices whose sum is
prime.
So, that was our for-expression.
If we apply our translation scheme
mechanically, we would be left with this
for-expression here.
So, the first one here, we have i until n,
That's what you see here.
It's a generator followed by a generator,
so I have a flatMap. the method
for-expression would take the generator
one until i, that's the one here that is
followed by a filter,
So we have a filter here, with a call to
withFilter, and the call to the isPrime
predicate.
And finally the whole thing gets mapped to
a map where we form the paths.
What's noteworthy is that this is almost
exactly the expression we came up with
first.
If you compare notes to what we had in the
last session, you'll find only two
differences.
One was we use now withFilter instead of
filter.
We've explained that already.
It's just to save on allocations of
intermediary data structures.
And the second one is, we do the filter
slightly earlier.
We do it as soon as we generate the second
index whereas, before we did it, once we
had generated the pair.
But that's just a minor transposition of
operations.
The end result, of course, is exactly the
same.
So, here is an exercise for you.
Remember, the queries we had on the books
data base, one of them was give me the
title of all books that have author with a
certain name.
Your task is to take this query and
translate it to a query that does not use
the for-expression, but only uses
higher-order functions.
So, how would you solve that exercise?
Well, let's follow the schema that we have
seen previously.
So, we would start with books.
And we have two leading generators so that
it would lead to a flatMap where our
function takes the variable to the left of
the generator, and we follow with a
for-expression that contains the rest.
So, that would be for a followed by
b.authors if a starts with Bird yield
b.title. But now, we have to take this
second for-expression here and translate
in term, I will, for the moment, just
write the result underneath.
So, what we see is it's a generator
followed by a filter, so that means you
pull the filter in to the generator, so
that would be for A, a taken from
b.authors withFilter and then we take the
a again,
A a.startswith Bird and we yield b.title.
Then, remove the first one.
So, we still have a for-expression to
translate.
This one here now has a signal generator,
so it would translate to a map.
So, let's do that.
We take the generator, that would be
b.authors withFilter a, a startswith Bird.
And now, we take this one here, and map
it, if the function y and return y.title.
So, that's the end result.
It's a flatMap followed by a map of a
generator that contains a withFilter.
Interestingly, the translation of for is
not just limited to just lists or
sequences or even collections.
All that we needed for the translation was
the presence of methods map, flatMap, and
withFilter because that, that was what we
translated into.
So, that means that you can use the
for-expression index for your types as
well.
All you need is to define map, flatMap,
and withFilter for a type on which you
want to use for-expressions.
And there actually a lot of types for
which this is useful what comes to mind is
kinds of collections such as arrays or
iterators, databases, XML data, optional
values, for-expressions are defined on
option as well, parses, and many others as
well.
So, to stay with database, for example,
books might not be a list or set but a
database stored of some server with data
kept on disc as long as the client
interface to the database defines methods
map, flatMap, and withFilter.
You can use for syntax for querying the
database.
And that's the basis of some popular
database connection frameworks for Scala,
which are called ScalaQuery and Slick.
And similar ideas also underly Microsoft's
LINQ, language integrated query framework,
Which lets you write expressions close to
for-expressions,
The C# versions of them is slightly
different,
And map them to databases.