In this session, we're going to look at
another fundamental class of collections,
associative maps.
Maps are special in Scala in the sense
that they are both are iterables and
functions.
We're going to explore the fundamental
operations of on maps and are going to
apply them to somewhat larger example.
Another fundamental collection type in
Scala is the map.
Maps have two type parameters, one
represents the key of the map, and the
other, the value of the map.
So, it's essentially, a data structure
that associates key of the key type with
values of the value type.
Here are two examples. The first is a map
of Roman numerals that associates strings
I, V, X with the numeric values one, five,
and ten, and the other is a map of
countries, which associates countries with
their capitals.
So, let's see this in the worksheet.
If I evaluate this, then what I get is two
im map.
The first from char to int, the second
from string to string.
And it, they have the values that I have
entered into that.
So, the first map that I have to find
would have to be of type map of string
int,
Int associates and int value with a string
key and the second map would be of type
map string to string.
It associates of string representing your
country with a string representing its
capital.
So, maps are iterables.
But, in fact, maps are also functions, and
that's because the class map key and value
also extend the function type from keys to
values.
That means maps can be used every where
functions can.
In particular, maps can be applied to some
arguments, so for instance, capital of a
country, of US, is a well-formed
application, looks likes a function call
but maps are function, so that would give
us back Washington.
But what would happen if we apply to the
function, to a value that is not a key on
the map?
So, for instance, capital of country,
Andorra.
Well, let's try out.
So, what we get is, not surprising, an
exception.
It reads, no such element exception.
The key Andorra was not found in the map.
So, what do, can we do to query a map
without knowing whether it contains a
given key or not.
In fact, what we do here is instead of
having a simple function application, we
can call, a get method on the map. So, if
we do that, then what we get here is, a
so-called option value, and it reads none,
so it would say, well, it hasn't found
anything that matches, Andorra. Whereas,
if we wrote, say, capitol of country get
US,
We would get another option value which
now read, some(Washington).
So, it's time to have a closer look at
what these option values are.
So, in fact, option is another standard
type in the Scala libraries.
Here, is its complete definition.
Option is a trait, it has a type
parameter, and there is one case class and
one object that both extended.
So, the case class is called some.
And it takes a value and if this is, is an
extension of option A and non-extends
option of nothing.
So, that means that an option value can be
one of two things.
It can be a none which means nothing was
found or it can be a some(x) where x is of
type A here and that means that something
was found and the thing that was found is
the x here. Since options are defined as
case classes, they can be decomposed using
pattern matching.
So, if we wanted, let's say, to show the
capital of a country without throwing a
keynote found exception, we could do
something like this.
We could get the country in, from the map
capital of country.
And then, we could match the resulting
option value.
If it's some capital, we return the
capital.
If it's none, we return the string called
missing data.
And then if we do showCapital of US,
We would get back Washington.
Whereas, if we did show capital of
Andorra, we would get back missing data.
Options also support quite a few
operations of the other collections.
In particular, they support map, flatMap,
and filter so you can run for-expressions
over them.
And I invite you to play with them and try
out what you can do with them.
For the examples that follow, we need two
more operations on collections that both
have analogs in query. SQL, these
operations would be called groupBy and
orderBy.
Orderby orders the elements of a
collection, according to some criteria
that can be expressed in the Scala
libraries with methods called sortWith or
sorted.
So, let's say, we have a list of fruit
here.
And we, we want to sort it such that fruit
with shorter names, appear before fruits
with longer names.
So, that we could write fruit sortwith and
then our criterion is that the length of
the first fruit must be smaller than the
length of the second fruit.
So, that's would lead to the following
result, pear, apple, orange, and
pineapple.
Or we could just sort the collection with
a natural ordering.
That's called sorted natural ordering here
is lexical graphics so that would lead to
the list that you see here.
The other operation, I want to cover is,
groupBy, which is directly available on
Scala collections.
What it does is that it partitions a
collection into a map of collections
according to some discriminator function.
That's best seen by an example. So, let's
take my fruit list and let's group it by
head.
So, head would the character that appears
first in each of these strings. So, what
that gives me is a map that associates
each head character.
So, p, a, and o,
That's the three,
With internal list of all those fruit that
have that character as their head.
So, p would now map to list of pear and
pineapple,
A would map to list of apple,
And o would map to list of orange.
So, let's do a more involved example using
maps.
What I want to do is look at polynomials.
A polynomial can be seen as a map from
exponents to coefficients.
For example, the polynomial x^3 - 2x + 2x
+ five could be represented with a map
that says, at exponent zero, we have a
five, At exponent one, we have a -two, and
exponent three, we have a one.
Based on this observation, let's design a
class polynom that represents polynomials
as maps.
So, what I have here is a new worksheet.
I've already given the rough framework of
this class of polynomials.
So, it would say, each of polynomials
should take, as a parameter and field a
map from exponent into coefficient double.
And what I want to implement is a plus
operation on polynomial.
So, let's turn to that.
How would, could a, add, let's say, two
polynomials like this one here and this
one here?
So, what we need to do is we need to merge
coefficients that have the same exponents.
So, what we would expect here is a
polynomial where we said zero was mapped
to three, one was mapped to two, three was
mapped to the sum of four and seven, so
that would be eleven, And five was mapped
to 6.2.
So, how can I achieve that?
Well, one idea would be I take one of the
maps, and then I add the adjusted
coefficient of each of the second maps to
it.
Adding means replacing the binding of the
same coefficient in the left map.
So, to define addition of two polynomials,
what I can do is I can take the first map
and try to add all the elements of the
second map to it.
Let's see how, how I would do that.
Type the first map, so that's terms, and I
will try to achieve with concatenation.
So, I would take the terms of the other.
And that would give me a new map, and I
just have to wrap that in a polygon.
Let's see what that would give.
Well, not much yet, because my map doesn't
really print very well.
You just get the default output, which
just says, it's a polynomial.
So, maybe let's work first on a good
two-string function of polynomial.
We'll get back to addition afterwards.
So, to turn a polynomial into a string,
what could I do?
Well, one thing to do it is I can take all
the terms that I have and I convert each
term into a nice expression with
coeffecient and exponent.
So, let's try to do that.
I would have a for-expression that takes
the exponent and coeffecient of each term
in my terms list.
And it would yield the coefficient,
followed by an x, that's my variable,
followed by an up arrow representing
exponent followed by the exponent.
And then, I just have to concatenate all
these elements together with a plus in the
middle.
So, let's see how we're doing.
Now, we get something nicer.
We get polynomials that we can read here.
one thing we notice it, that they are not
yet sorted.
They can appear in any order.
For instance, the last one starts one,
three, five, zero.
So, we would like to have the terms in
sorted order with the highest coming
first.
So, one idea here would be to say, well,
take the terms, convert them to a list
because we need a sequence to sort them
sort them, sort them.
So, that goes from small to large and
reverse them in the end.
So, terms, toList, sorted, reverse.
Let's see what we get now.
So now, the things are nicely sorted five,
three, one, zero.
On the other hand, unfortunately, the
result is far from being correct.
Let's see what we did here.
We have the first exponent from the first
polynomial that's fine, then we have the
cubed term from the second polynomial, but
in fact, what we really need is the sum of
the two cubed terms in both polynomials.
So, what happened here is, with the,
operation ++, what we did really was just
to essentially superimpose the terms of
the other polynomial on top of this one.
So, if the left polynomial didn't have a
term with a given exponent, that was okay.
We would just take the term of others and
it would be correct.
But if it did have a term with the same
polynomial, that term would be lost.
What we need to do in,
Instead, is have a function that, in that
case, would add together the two
coefficents.
So, how would we go about doing that?
Well, the best, way to do it, almost
always in function programming, is break
it out into its own simple function.
So, we would say, well, let's go over the
other terms, and essentially map,
Call this adjust for adjusting the
coefficient.
And that's a function we'll have to
define.
So, we define adjust, and that takes a
term so that would be a term and that's a
pair of an int and a double.
And we wanted to return the adjusted term,
Again, a pair of an int and of a double.
So, what do we need to do here?
Well, we need to see whether the key of
the term is already in the left map.
So, let's maybe pull out the key, so we
say val exponent coeffecient equals term,
so now, we have a nicely the two sides, in
variables each by themselves.
So, what we must do now is, find out
whether, the existing terms have already a
coefficient that matches exponents So
let's do that and say, terms get exponent
match.
In the case where this is,
some(coefficient) one, say,
We return a pair or a binding, that goes
from the exponent to coefficient plus
coefficient one.
And, if there was nothing in the map, then
we return the binding that goes from
exponent to just the coefficient of the
second map.
What we did here is that the arrow and the
plus have the same precedents, but we need
to put the parenthesis here, like that,
because of course we, we want to have the
exponent mapped to the sum of the two
coefficients.
Okay, so now, what we see is that the cube
coefficient here reads eleven, That's what
we need.
Good.
So, we're done with the addition.
But it felt kind ofheavy weight to do all
this computation.
Is there a simpler way?
Well, indeed there is.
So, far maps were always partial
functions.
Applying a map to a key value could lead
to an exception if the key was not stored
in the map.
What if we could make maps total functions
that would never fail but would give us
back some default value if the key wasn't
found.
There's an operation that does that, it's
called withDefaultValue and that operation
turns a map into a total function.
So, if you had written, for instance, cap1
= capitalOfCountry withDefaultValue
unknown, then we could have safely applied
cap1 to Andorra and you would have gotten
back unknown because that's the
withDefaultValue. No more keynote found
exceptions.
So, let's apply this technique to our
worksheet.
What I will do is that I will,
Instead of having a terms field, I just
call this a term zero parameter.
Then we'll create a new field, terms which
is terms0 withDefaultValue 0.0. So now,
all my polynomials are have maps that have
a default value.
We can try to test that by create, calling
p1, first polynomial dot terms of some
exponent that's missing.
And we would get back a 00 instead of the
exception that we would have expected to
see before.
With the new map withDefaultValues, we can
greatly simplify the adjust function.
We don't, we need no longer test whether
terms contain the given exponent or not,
we can delete all that, and replace it
with a simple return expression that says,
well, given the exponent, I associate it
with the coefficient of my second map,
plus whatever the coefficient was in my
first map,
And that would be just in terms of the
exponent.
And I get back the same polynomials as
before.
So, you see there's great power in working
with maps that have default values.
Often, the code that deals with them can
be greatly simplified.
So far, so good.
But there's still something slightly
unnice about that, and that's the way we
have to create polygons.
We wrote new poly, and then we have to
pass some map into each polygon.
Is there a nicer way that ideally would
let us avoid the intermediary data
structure?
So, ideally, we could just write, poly of
one to two, zero, three to four, zero,
five to six, two.
Well, for the moment, of course, that
doesn't work, because poly takes a map as
parameters and here, we have what?
Well, we have three pairs of int and
double elements.
The problem, of course, is that we could
have three but we could have also four or
any other number of pairs that we pass as
parameters to poly.
So, we need a way to pass a varying number
of parameters to the same function.
In fact, Scala does offer that ability
with its use of repeated parameters.
So, let's show this with an auxiliary
constructor in class poly.
You haven't seen them since week three, so
it's a good time to refresh.
So, the auxiliary constructor would take a
sequence of bindings, each binding is a
pair of int and double.
And the fact that it's a sequence is
expressed by the star here.
So, the star means it's a repeated
parameter.
That means, we can pass an arbitrary
number of concrete arguments for this a
form of parameter here.
Internally all the arguments are
represented as a sequence.
So, that means, that if we call now the
primary constructor, what we can pass
along as arguments is simply the sequence
converted to a map.
So, if you do that, then the spreadsheet
compiles again, and we get the same
polynomials as before.
We can also get rid of the map, of course,
in the other course to polynomial.
So, here is the final implementation of
polynomials.
As an exercise, I would like you to tweak
this a little bit.
So here, we have expressed the addition
operation with a concatenation of the
terms of the two maps, where the second
terms were adjusted.
It is also possible to express the same
operation with a foldleft. And I'd like
you to do that in the exercise.
So, what I'd like you to do is write plus
as follows.
It takes another polynomial and creates a
new polynomial where the you apply a
foldLeft operation to the other terms as a
collection and you have to figure out what
the unit element here is, with an
operation addTerm as the combining
operation,
And again, addTerm I would like you to
implement.
Once you've done that, you are able to
answer the following question.
Which of the two versions you believe is
more efficient?
The version using ++ or the version using
foldLeft? So, let's see how we will solve
this problem in the worksheet here.
So, I'm going to start to work on the
implementation of plus.
We said it should have been other terms,
FoldLeft with some zero element, so what
would that be?
Well, I'm going to argue it must be terms
because if other terms is empty, then we
clearly want to return terms.
So, the zero element will be terms here
and the combining operation will be called
add term.
So, I have to work on this one now.
So, addTerm takes now a zero element so
that's terms, a map of int and double.
And it takes a term that's taken from the
other terms list here, it is a pair of int
of double and again it returns another map
of int in double.
So, what would it's implementation be?
Well, In fact, we don't need to change
much from what it was.
So, all we need to do is that instead of
returning a single binding, we immediately
add this binding to the given terms map.
So, we would return terms plus the binding
that you have seen here.
And that helps them and that does it.
So, everything compiles and we get the
same results as before.
So now, to answer the question, which of
the two versions is more efficient?
So, I would argue the one with foldLeft is
more efficient because what happens here
is that each of these bindings will be
immediately added to our terms maps so we
built up the result directly whereas,
before we would create an another list of
terms that contain the adjusted terms, and
then we would concatenate this list to the
original one.
So, the version with foldLeft avoids this
creation of the intermediate list data
structure. So, in that sense, it looks
like it's more efficient.
So, I would vote here for foldLeft.