In this session, we are going to look at
the question of how to handle nested
sequences in common notarial search
problems.
We're going to explore a handy new
notation for this kind of problems namely,
for-expressions.
High-order functions and collections often
replace loops and imperative languages.
Programs that use many nested loops then
can be expressed often with combinations
of these high-order functions.
I will now show you that with an example.
So, the task is that we want to find all
pairs of positive integers i and j,
Such that j is less than i and that i is
bounded by some positive integer n, and i
plus j is prime.
So, for instance, if n = seven, the pairs
we want to find are two, one, three, two,
four, one, four, three and so on.
Because the sum of i and j in each case is
a prime number.
So, in imperative programming language, I
probably would use two nested loops, one
for the i's, one for the j's together with
a test whether the sum of i plus j is a
prime number, and some sort of buffer to
collect the results.
But what would be a purely functional way
to achieve the same thing?
So, a natural functional way to do this
would be to generate data structures bit
by bit until we have generated the data
structure that we need for the final
result.
So, the first data structure that we want
to generate is the sequence of all the
pairs of integers i, j such that the j and
the i are with in the bounds that we have
specified.
And then, once we have that sequence, we
can filter it to keep only those pairs for
which the sum i + j is prime and then,
we're done.
So, we're left with a problem how to
generate this sequence of pairs of
integers.
And there, the natural way to do this
would be to first generate the integers i
between one and n and excluded.
And then, for each integer i, generate the
list of pairs,
(I,1), (i,2), and so on, until (i,i-1).
So, once we have that, we can put it into
code.
The last bit can be achieved combining
until and map.
So, it would write one until n, so that
gives us the list of i from one to n
excluded. And then for each of these
integers, we map it,
Call it i to a range that goes from one
until i, i excluded.
Call the index here, j, and for each
combination of i and j that we have
produced that way, we return the pair i
and j So, let's do that in the worksheet.
I have a new worksheet called pairs.
I set the value of n to be seven, and I
copy the expression that we've seen last
in the, on the slide.
So, let's do that in the worksheet.
I've opened a new worksheet, call it
pairs.
And I want to try out to build these
sequence of pairs.
The first thing to do is set the upper
limit, let's say n = seven.
And then, I copy this expression that I
had on the slide.
So, what did I get here?
Well if I have a look at the right, then I
get a vector of vectors.
And each element of the vector is indeed
an i with a j less than the i and both are
greater or equal to one.
So, I get the pairs that I wanted to
produce.
You might ask, well, why did I get back a
vector of vectors?
Well, if you look at the class hierarchy
that we have seen in the last session,
then you will see that range is a subtype
of sequence.
Now, the, a range that we started with,
one until n, got transformed with a map.
And that map produced a sequence of, of
pairs.
And, of course, sequences of pairs are not
elemental of ranges so I needed some other
representations.
The representation I got was, in fact, a
type that sits between sequence and range.
It's called an index sequence.
So, that's essentially a sequence that
uses random access and the prototypical
default implementation of an index
sequence is just a vector.
So, what the type inference decided was to
say, well, I can't do with ranges,
Ranges can't contain pairs.
So, I go up the hierarchy and I take the
next best type that happen to be an index
sequence and I take the canonical
implementation of that type,
And that happened to be a vector.
So, that's how you ended up with vectors
of vectors.
But we have seen that's still not the
right thing to do.
We want to generate just a single
collection of pairs, not a collection of
vectors.
So, what we need to do is we need to
concatenate all the element vectors into
one single list of pairs.
So, let's see how that can be done.
We can combine all the sub-sequences in,
or sequence of vectors of pairs using a
foldRight with concatenation as the
operation.
So, if you have a vector of sequences,
That should,
And what we do is we, combine them all
using ++, the concatenation operation.
And on the right-hand side, you would have
the empty vector.
So, that would work, that would give us a
single sequence of pairs.
There is also another method here that p
is useful. This is called xss.flatten.
So, flatten does essentially the same
thing as concat it takes a collection of
collections and returns a single
collection containing all the elements in
the sub, sub-collections and if the
collection is a sequence, then the
combination will be just the concatenation
of these sub-collections.
So, a simpler way to express what we want
is our path generating expression and then
we just follow that by flatten.. We're not
done yet because we can still apply a
useful law.
Remember, the flatMap function that we've
seen in the last session, it takes a
collection valued function f and applies
to each element of the list xs and then
combines the result.
So, flatMap is actually exactly the same
thing as mapping f, so that would give us
a collection of collections, and then
applying flatten.
And map followed by flatten is exactly the
pattern that we've seen here.
So, it's a map here, followed by flatten.
So, we can, we can contract the two to
just use a flatMap here.
So, would have one until n, flatMap to
function that goes through each interval
from one to i and forms the pen.
Now, we have generated all the possible
pairs, we still need to filter them.
That's fairly simple.
So, we follow it by a filter.
It takes a pair, and it asks whether the
sum of the two elements of the pair is a
prime number.
And that works.
But it must be said that it makes most
peoples head hurt, an expression like
that.
Question is, is there a simpler way to
express the same expression?
So, let's do that in the worksheet.
Let's replace the called map here by
flatMap,
And we would get what we want here in flat
sequence of pairs.
Now, what we still need to do is we need
to filter that sequence according to the
criterion that the sum of the two elements
of the pair is prime.
So, let's do that, let's follow the
expression with a filter, takes a pair,
and it asks whether the following is
prime.
The pair's first element plus the pair's
second element.
And if we do that, then indeed, we get the
sequence we wanted sequence of pairs of
elements which sum is prime.
So, here the sum is five, seven, seven,
seven, eleven, all prime numbers.
So, this works but it's fair to say that
it makes most people's head hurt.
Is there a simpler way to organize this
expression.
That makes it more understandable. Well,
one thing we definitely could try to do is
name the intermediate results.
So, split out enlarged expression like
that into several smaller ones.
That's generally always a good move.
But it turns out there is a more
fundamental way how we can express
problems like this in a more high level
notation that's simpler to understand.
We will get to that next.
So, we've seen that high-order order
functions such as map, flatMap, or filter
provide powerful constructs for
manipulating lists and data collections.
But we've also seen that sometimes the
level of obstruction required by these
functions, make the program hard to
understand.
In this case, there's a notation in Scala
that can help.
It's called a for-expression.
So, let's introduce for-expressions by an
example.
We start with the class of person that we
seen before.
A person has a name, which is a string and
then H, which is an int.
To obtain the names of all persons over
twenty years, you could write, for p left
arrow, that gets spelled taken from
persons, if p.age greatertwenty yield
p.name. And, in fact, that expression is
equivalent to the expression, persons
filter such that the person p, has an age
greater, greater than twenty, and then map
the filter expression, such that for every
person, p, we get back its name The two
expressions are, have about the same size,
but I would argue that this one is simply
to read and understand what it produces.
For-expressions like this are similar to
for loops in imperative languages,
But there's an important difference.
A for loops operates with a side effect,
it changes something.
A for-expression doesn't.
Instead, a for-expression produces a new
result, and essentially, each element of
the result is produced by a yield
expression here.
So, if you look at the syntax of four
expressions then, here it is.
So, they are of the form four and then
comes a sequence of generators or filters
in parenthesis,
And then comes a yield, and then comes the
expression that produces the final result
elements.
So, the sequence S can consist of
generators and filters and generator is of
the form p left arrow e, where p is a
variable or more generally, a whole
pattern,
And e can be an expression, whose value is
a collection.
The idea is that we would let p range over
all elements of the collection e.
And a filter is of the form if f, where f
is a Boolean expression, and the idea here
is that the filter would remove from
consideration, all elements where f is
false.
The sequence must always start with a
generator and if there's several
generators in the sequence, the last
generators very faster than the first.
So the first one steps through more slowly
and then, for each element of the first,
the second generator will be traversed and
so on.
There is a minor variation in the syntax,
we can also write praises around the
sequence of generators and filters and
then the generators and filters can be
written on multiple lines without
requiring semicolons.
If you write it with a parenthesis, then
if we have several generators, we need to
put a semicolon between them.
Now, let's see this with two examples.
The first example is our expression that
gave us all pairs whose sum were prime
numbers so that could be expressed simply
like, what you see here.
Will it i range from one until end, will a
j range from one until i?
We demand that the sum from i + j must be
a prime number and then, we yield the pair
of i and j. I think there's no contest
which one is clearer, so this one is
rather crystal clear whereas, the other
one was quite convoluted.
The second example I want you to do as an
excercise, remember, scalar product from
last session, so that was the function
that took two vectors of doubles,
multiplied corresponding elements and then
summed the result.
Can you write a version of scalar product
that makes use of a for-expression?
So, let's see how we would solve it.
Not solve this.
So, let's see how we would solve this.
So, I write a for-expression, for.
What I want to do is I want to let x and y
range over the result of zipping the two
vectors, xs and ys.
And then, I want to return, in each case,
the multiplication between x and y.
So, that would give me the multiplication
of corresponding elements in xs and ys.
And then, all I have to do in the end is
sum it up.
So, for the sum of the whole vector.