In the last session, we have looked in
depth at a lot of different aspects of a
single class.
What we're going to do in this session is
generalize that so that we now look at
class hierarchies, where more than one
class cooperates to achieve a certain
task.
So, as a running example in this session,
we consider the task of writing a set of
classes, that implement sets of integers.
And these integers set will be called
inset and support two operations.
Include, to include an element x in the
inset and contain, which is a test whether
an element x is a member of the set.
So, to do that, I would open a fresh
worksheet.
Call it insets and the definition of the
class here.
What you see, what's particular is that
we've given you two definitions of
functions, but they do not have a body.
The equals is missing and the body is
missing, and that's permissible as long as
the class is abstract.
If I would remove the abstract, I would
get a problem which would say, class inset
needs to be abstract since method contains
is not defined and method include is not
defined.
So, let's add the abstract again.
So, you've seen that abstract glasses can
contain members which are missing in
implementation.
On the other hand, we get instances of an
abstract glass with the operator new.
So, if you would try that.
Write here, new inset.
I will get an error, which says that the
class inset is abstract and cannot be
instantiated.
So, since inset is incomplete, how would
we implement it?
Well, one way to do that would be using
the binary tree data structure.
In the data structure, there are two types
of possible tree.
A tree that represents the empty set and a
tree that consists of an integer and two
subtrees and the idea would be that you
keep always the invariant that the trees
are sorted.
So, that means if I give you an example
here, we would have a tree, let's say,
with a seven, and that would have a two
subtrees, and here, we would have maybe an
eleven, and here we would have five.
And then, the eleven could have one, nine.
And the response would all be empty.
So, that's an example of a binary tree.
And the invariant that we want to maintain
is that for each node, the nodes on the
right-hand side of this node, all have
integer values that are higher than the
node.
Whereas, the nodes on the left-hand side
all have values that are less than the
node.
Now, that this will make it easier later
on to implement, the contains test that
determines whether a given value is in the
tree.
So, let's start with the empty tree here.
The empty tree is very simple to implement
we would simply say, the contains value.
The empty tree is very simple to
implement, we would simply say that
contains is always false, because the
empty tree does, cannot contain any value.
Whereas, include is a method that returns
an inset.
So, what set would it return?
Well, it would return a non-empty set to
be defined, that contains the given
element and two empty subtrees.
So, going from the empty set to an include
set, would give us a set like that, that
contains a single node and two empty
subnodes.
Let's put that class into the worksheet.
Now, it still remains to define what a
non-empty set would be.
A non-empty set in that implementation,
would be represented by a class non-empty
that takes an element, that's the integer
stored in the node, and the left and the
right subtree which is, in each case, an
inset.
And the implementation of contains and
includes now makes use of the sorted
criterion of trees.
So that means that, for contains, we
always have to look only in one of the
possible subtrees.
If the given number x is less than the
current element value, then we know we
will have to look in the left subtree
here.
Whereas, if it's greater, we know we will
have to look in the right subtree.
If it's neither less nor greater than, it
must be equal.
And in this case, we have found the
element.
The include method follows a similar
algorithm.
If the element to be added is less than
the element in the tree then we need to
include it in the left subtree.
If it is greater, we need to include it in
the right subtree.
And otherwise, the element is already in
the tree and we can return the tree as is.
There's nothing that needs to be added.
One interesting aspect is when I say
include in the left or in the right
subtree.
What we need to do is really construct a
new tree around the element here.
One important aspect here is that we are
still purely functional, there is no
mutation.
So, when I say, we include an element in
the left subtree, what I really mean is
that we create a new tree that contains
the previous element of the tree and a
larger left subtree, where x is included
in the previous left subtree and the
current subtree on the right.
So, visually, if I would say, include the
number three in the tree that we see here.
Then, what would happen is I would create
a new node three with two empty subtrees.
That subtree would be the left subtree of
a new node with element five, and an empty
right-hand subtree.
And, finally, my tree would be a new tree
with the, as before the node seven is the
node and the same as the right-hand side
tree here.
So, we see that now, we really have two
trees, the old one and the new one after
the include.
The two trees share the sub tree here on
the right hand side but they differ in the
left tree, where, on the new tree, we have
a three in the left most bottom corner
whereas, for the old tree, we just have
two empty trees.
One way these data structures are called,
are called persistent data structures,
because even when we do changes or
so-called changes in quotes to a data
structure, the old version of the data
structure is still maintained.
It doesn't go away.
And persistent data structures are
actually one of the cornerstone of scaling
functional programming up to collections
and the like.
So, let's take the definition of class
non-empty and also, add it in the
worksheet so that we can test something.
So now, instead of new inset, I would
create a set by saying, well, if this
would be, maybe, new non-empty of three,
new empty, new empty, so it would be my
first set.
I would give me non-empty set, and I could
then write things like include a four, and
that would give me an inset, which is
another non-empty set.
Now, before we go further, let's add a two
string operation to our set so that we can
actually see what sets we have created
here.
We need two definitions of two string.
One in empty, and one in non-empty.
For empty, how would we define two string?
Well, let me just define it in a very
minimalistic way to give you a period.
For non-empty, I want to define two string
as follows.
I want to say it should be an open brace
followed by the, the description of the
left element followed by the, sorry, as
follows.
It should be an open brace followed by the
string value of the left subtree and the
element in the middle in the right
subtree, and then, a closing brace.
If we do that, then we see that here we
get a sort of visual representation of our
tree.
So, the first t1 would be an element tree,
and empty tree to the left and right.
Whereas, t2 would be the root of t2 would
be three, the right subtree is a tree that
has four as its element.
So, we see that this tree, in particular,
has maintained the invariant that trees
are sorted.
So, one new thing you see here is that
both empty and non-empty extend inset.
So, extension means that these two classes
are subclasses of the base class inset.
One consequence of that is that the types,
empty and non-empty, conform to the type
inset.
What that means is that an object of type
empty or non-empty can be used wherever an
object of type inset is required.
Some more terminology.
We say, insert is the super class of empty
and non-empty, and empty and nonempty are
the subclasses of inset.
In Scala, any class that you can define
extends another class.
Even for a class like rational, where you
didn't give an extends clause, there is a
superclass.
So, if no explicit superclass is given,
the standard class object in the Java
package, Java language is assumed.
Object is the root class of all Java
class, and also of all user-defined Scala
classes.
If you take the direct superclass of a
class and then its superclass and so on,
so all the direct and indirect super
classes of a class C, then these are
called that the base classes of C.
So, for instance, the base classes of
class non-empty or insert and then object.
So, what you've seen in the example is
that the definitions of, contains and
including classes empty and non-empty,
implement the abstraction functions in the
base class insert, they were not to be
find in insert but they, they are
implemented in the subclasses, empty and
nonempty.
It's also possible to redefine an existing
non-abstract definition of a superclass in
a subclass, but then, you have to use
overwrite.
So, in this example here, you see the, the
difference.
If you write in the base class, foo = one.
And then you redefine foo in the subclass,
which, which extends base, then you have
to put an overwrite.
So, let me demonstrate that to you in this
worksheet.
We have two classes, a base class and a
subclass.
And each of these classes have two members
named foo and bar.
The bar member in class sub, implements
the abstract definition of bar in class
base.
Whereas, the full member replaces the
concrete definition of who in class base.
If a member replaces or overwrites the
definition in a superclass, then the
override here is mandatory.
So let's say, say I leave that out,
compile.
And we will get an error which says,
overwriting might method foo in class base
the method foo here needs an overwrite
modifier.
So, why is that?
Why here Scala is actually more picky than
Java?
Well, the reason is that sometimes we do
not really know what methods you do
inherit.
So, you might actually accidentally
overwrite a method in a base class, and in
that case, is good that you have to be
explicit about it.
There's an added benefit namely when you
intent to overwrite but let's say, you
can't remember the name correctly or you
get the numbers of parameters wrong, or
things like that.
So, if I write something like that,
overwrite the foo two, then I get an error
again.
Where we say, method foo2 overwrites
nothing.
So, in that case the ovewrite will give me
the opposite protection results when I
write overwrite then I want to be sure
that, in fact, I do overwrite another
definition.
For methods that implement definitions in
base classes, the overwrite is optional,
you can write it if you want to.
And, in that case, you will be warned in
the same way.
So, if I write part two, I will get an
error as before.
But you don't have to do that.
So, you don't need to write the overwrite,
you could just write def bar.
And that's usually less noisy, so,
preferred.
So, let's get back to the insets example.
One thing to improve would be the status
of the empty inset class.
You could argue that there's really only a
single empty inset.
So, it seems overkill to have the user
create many instances of it.
And, in fact, that's very easy to achieve
in Scala.
You just use an object definition instead
of a class definition as before.
So, this object definition is exactly the
same as the class definition, except that
instead of the keyword class, you use
object.
And that will define a single item object
named empty.
There is only one of them and you don't
need or can create that explicitly with
new.
So the object empty simply exists,
technically it will be created the first
time you reference it.
Your reference to the object simply by
naming it with empty.
So, empty here and here replaces the
creation of new MT that we had before.
In terms of evaluation, singleton objects
are values.
So, empty is already a value, there's no
evaluation step that needs to be
performed.
So, since we're already looking at objects
let's, take a quick excursion and look at
what a program would be in Scala So far,
we've executed all Scala code from the
RPEL or the worksheet, but it's also
possible to create standalone
applications.
Each as applications would contain an
object and that object contains a main
method.
Let's look at this with the mandatory
Hello World Program written in Scala.
So, you would write an object, name it
Hello.
It has a main method, then as in java,
that main method will have to take an
array of string, you can ignore that for
the time being.
And the body of the main method would be a
println with Hello World.
Once you compile this program, you can
start it from the command line simply with
Scala, and then Hello.
Or you could also use Java and Hello, they
would do the same thing in this case.
Should we demonstrate?
So, let, let me demonstrate that in
Eclipse.
Hm.
Now.
So, let me demonstrate that in Eclipse.
We would, in Week three, we would not
create a worksheet, but now a, a Scala
object.
Call it, Hello.
What do I do if it's the Scala
application.
Let's see.
Okay.
Now, it's up now, yeah, okay.
Okay, let's get rid of the results.
What should we do?
Okay.
So, let's demonstrate that using Eclipse,
no, I think, I have that here, yeah.
So, okay, I said that already.
So, we create in the Week three package,
this time not a worksheet but a Scala
object, call it, Hello.
And then, we have to add the main function
which takes this.
And it would print something.
We can run this program as a program using
the green arrow here.
So, we will run it as a Scala application,
and we see on the console, Hello World.
So, that's how you would run full programs
in Scala from Eclipse.
If you want to run it from the command
line, you will also have a Scala compiler
called Scala C in the main distributions
of Scala's [unknown].
Now, let's just drop it.
So, [inaudible].
Okay, then we go back to, okay.
If you, no, that, no, we won't do that,
that's, okay.
So, that's how we would run things in
Eclipse, and then we stop, okay?
Good.
Mm-hm.
Okay.
And okay.
Yeah.
Now, we have to do it this way or
something, not the ideal because not, so,
let's do an exercise.
The task is to add a new method to our
insert class hierarchy.
The method should take the union of a set
and some other set.
So, you should extend the class insert to
be the following abstract class and
implement that.
So, how we would we go about that?
Let's first start with the abstract class.
So, here's the signature of union.
And now, we get two errors because we have
to implement it in the two sub classes.
So, let's start with empty.
What would the union of an empty set and
some other set be?
Well, that's very simple, empty set union
some other set is always the other set.
For non-empty, what would we do for
non-empty?
Well, hm, that's a good question now.
For non-empty, how would we define union
in that case?
But one idea is to use what's often called
divide and conquer.
So, a non-empty set is built from an
element and a left subset and a right
subset.
So, let's maybe union all of these
together.
So, it would say, okay, it would be the
left set union.
The right set, union the, I will set
union, include the element.
So, the good definition let's see.
[laugh] So, we go left, it's definitely
smaller, that's okay.
Yeah, we will just, then left union right
is, is still smaller.
You need other, that's smaller.
And include, yeah, okay, that should work.
Okay, let's, let's, let's do this again.
Okay.
So, for non-empty sets, how would we
define union in this case?
Well, the idea is that we split the set
into its constituents.
So, we have the left inset, the right
inset, and the element.
Let's form the union instead from
something that is smaller.
So, one of the subsets.
Let's start with left and two union right.
So, that would give us the set without the
initial element.
Then, let's finally give the union of the
other set.
And as a last action, action, let's
include the element back into the set.
So, the new union has all the parts of the
previous ones that contain the left set,
it contains the right set, it contains the
element, and it contains the other set.
So, it's very easy to convince ourselves
that indeed the two the, the, the results
set here would have all the elements of
the union and would have no other
elements.
But there's another concern and that is
well, how do we know that this recursion
actually terminates, because after all,
union calls union and we've seen already,
cases where calling yourself again would
not terminate.
So, the argument you, we could make here
is to say, well, every call to union is
actually on something that is smaller than
the set we started with.
The first call to union was on the left
subtree here, and obviously, that set is
smaller than the whole non-empty set.
The second call to union was on the union
in left and right, and then again contains
one element less than the full set that we
have here.
Because every union, every quarter union
is on a set that is smaller, it follows
that, at some point, we have to reach
zero.
And if the set is zero, then we fall back
to the case of empty sets where the union
is immediate, we just return the other
set.
So, that's how we convince ourselves that
the union that we, operations that we do
here are in fact terminating.
And once those are terminating, we can
safely add element back with an include
operation as before, okay.
What object oriented language is do in
this case?
Scala included, is to use th dynamic
method dispatch model.
That means, that the code that's invoked
by a method call depends on the runtime
type of the object, that contains the
method.
I believe that's best exemplified with,
okay, I believe that's best shown in an
example.
So, let's say, you have the code empty
contains one.
What do you do?
Well, you look up the contains method in
empty.
Remember that was, remember that was an
object empty and we had a def contains y =
False, that was its definition.
So, looking up that method and performing
the necessary substitutions, we get False.
On the other hand, if we have, so here, is
another evaluation using non-empty.
We would have a tree called new.
So, so, here is another evaluation using
non-empty.
We would have to set non-empty seven,
empty, empty, and we ask whether it
contains seven.
So, if you look back at the definition of
contain and non-empty, that's what we see
here.
And if we apply our substitution rules,
then it means this call of the method will
be replaced by the right hand side of the
contains method, which you see here.
And at the same time, the substitutions of
the parameters of the class, and the
method, and the self-reference.
So, the three elements that you see here.
If we perform the substitution, we arrive
at this expression here.
So, instead of x and ln we have we, we
have we see seven in each case, and
instead of the, this, we see new non,
non-empty seven, empty, empty.
If you perform the simplification, we get
that seven is neither less nor greater
than seven, so we fall into the else case,
and we get true.
So, for the end of this session, here's
something to ponder.
You've seen that dynamic dispatch of
methods in object oriented languages is
actually quite similar to calls of high
order functions in pure functional
languages.
The similarity is that in both cases, the
code that gets executed on a functional
method call is not known statically, it's
not apparent from the name or the type of
the thing you called, but it is determined
by the runtime value that is passed.
So, it's a fair question whether we can
implement one concept in terms of the
other.
Can we maybe implement objects in terms of
high order functions or can we implement
higher order functions in terms of
objects?
Or can we maybe go both ways?
It's a question that is fairly open and
that has a range of possible answers.
So, I just let you with that think a
little bit, bit about it and maybe discuss
with others.