In the last session, you've seen a class
hierarchy of overall three classes.
The real program of course will contain
not three but dozens or hundreds or
thousands of classes.
So there's a question how to organize
them.
In this session, we'll learn about
packages that can contain classes, as well
as how to make classes accessible with
imports.
We'll find out about this standard Scala
library that contains a lot predefined
classes already and how these classes are
organized in an hierarchy.
So generally in Scala as well as in Java,
classes and objects are organized in
packages.
You can place your class or object inside
a package simply by adding a package
clause like package progfun.example at the
beginning of your source file And that
would put then every class or object you
define later on in that package that you
have defined here.
And once you've done that, then you can
refer to the original object or class, by
its so called, fully qualified main.
So, the fully qualified name is the name
of the package and then a dot and then the
name of the object of the class.
So, for Hello, it would be
progfun.examples.Hello.
And, that fully qualified name you can use
to refer to Hello from your program or
also on the command line when you say,
want to run the Hello program you will
write scala then progfun.examples.Hello.
So let's demonstrate that using the
worksheet.
What I've done here is I've taken the
class rational from the last session which
was in worksheet, and I've put this as a
standalone class in package week three
over here.
So now what I want to do is refer to
rationals from another worksheet, call it
scratch.
So what we could do is write new
week3.Rational(1, two) and then the
worksheet would answer that it's defined a
instance of type week3.Rational and the
value is one-half.
So if it becomes too tedious to write
week3.Rational every time you want to
refer to a rational, you could also import
the rational type from the week three
package.
The way you do that is with an import
clause.
You write import week3.Rational.
Once you've done that, you can refer to
rational without the prefix, because you
have imported it previously.
Imports come in several forms.
This is the most simple one where you
import a single named thing.
There's also another form of import where
you import everything in a given package
so the form import week3. would import
everything that is defined in package week
three It's more general, it's more
convenient but sometimes it's less legible
because sometimes you really want to have
a more precise control over where your
names come from.
It's also a third form of import which
you'll see here in the second line where
you can import several names from the same
package.
So the form import week3, Hell would
import both Rational and Hello from the
week three package.
The first two forms here are called named
imports and the last form is called a
wildcard import.
And another thing to say is that we've
seen we can import from packages, but you
could in fact import from any object,
Any expression that gives you an object
and you would simply import all the
members of that object.
Some entities are imported automatically
in any Scala program.
These are, all members of packaged Scala.
All members of package java.lang and all
members of the singleton object
scala.Predef. So if you wondered
previously for instance how, where did the
require or the insert function come from,
Well the answer was they were defined in
the object scala.Predef, that's an object
inside the scaler package and the
automatic import of all members of the
Predef object made that you could use
these names without a further
qualification.
The same holds for the types Int and
Boolean that you've used before so these
are actually defined in the Scala package
and their fully qualified names are
scala.Int and scala.Boolean whereas the
name object that we've been using, that
actually comes from the Java universe
which is in which the Scala universe is
embedded.
Object is spelled out java.lang.Object.
The root object of all Java objects and we
have imported that automatically because
besides Scala also, all objects in Java
land are automatically imported.
By now you probably would like to find out
more about what classes are there and the
Scala library.
What can you do with them?
What methods do they export?
You can do all that using a set of webpage
that have been generated by a tool called
Scaladoc and you can get that by googling
for Scaladoc or by going to this page here
which gives you the root package of the
scala library and here you can see on the
left hand side a set of classes, You can,
by displaying all packages you get the set
of packages in the Scalar library. If you
go through to the packages Scalar then,
and I look at a class, let's say Predef
object that we've seen here.
And you see here an explanation of what's
in the Predef object,
If we then want to find a method let's say
assert in there, then you see here is the
definition of the assert methods that are
offered by the Predef object.
You see here each assert's comes in two
versions.
One with an error message, one without so
that's why I told you the error messages
was optional and like that, you can
explore, what's out there in the Scala
libraries.
Now, if you have browsed a little bit this
Scala doc, then you probably would have
come across set of pages that describe
traits, and you might ask well what is a
trait?
Well in Java, as well as in Scala, a class
can only have one super class.
You say for this scheme it's a single
inheritance language.
Single inheritance.
And that's actually very constraining
because quite often a, a type will have
naturally several super types or it would,
you would want to inherit behavior from
several super entities that all contribute
to the final code of the class.
To do that, you can use the concept of
Traits A Trait is essentially declared
like an abstract class.
You just use trait instead of the keyword
abstract class here.
So here for instance we would have a trait
of planar objects, where the objects would
have a height and width unspecified so
those depths don't come within
implementation.
And then you would have a surface that
would be height times width as a default
implementation.
So that would be a concrete method and
those two would be method which would lack
an implementation and so are called
abstract.
So, the idea of traits is then that,
claases, objects and other traits can
inherit from utmost one class, but they
can inherit from arbitrarily many traits.
The way you do that, you see here, so here
would be a, you would have class square,
that extends a shape superclass and then
it adds also two traits one is called
Planar and one is called Movable.
You combine the super class and all the
traits you want to inherit with, with
here.
So with this a combination that adds
another trait to some set of classes or
traits that you inherit already.
In that sense, even though the syntax is
different, try traits resemble interfaces
in Java.
Because in Java as well you can inherit
from one class, but multiple interfaces.
However, traits actually much more
powerful than interfaces in Java because
traits can contain fields and concrete
methods whereas interfaces can contain
only abstract methods.
You seen on the last slide, that the trade
planner has, had one method surface which
already gave a default implementation of
the surface property here.
That implementation can be overridden in
subclasses as always, but if subclasses do
not give an implementation, then this one
here would be chosen.
So there's only one thing you can do with
classes, but not with traits.
And that is that classes can have value
parameters like the numerator and
denominator of class rational,
Whereas traits cannot.
So traits never have parameters.
So now let's have a look at the outline of
Scala's class hierarchy.
So here you see the fundamental Scala
classes and the relationship between them.
The arrow here means that the class at the
root of the arrow is a sub class of the
class to which the arrow points.
So you see that the classes are organized
in a hierarchy.
At the top of the hierarchy, you have a
class called scala.Any.
That's a super class of every other class
and Then, you have essentially two set
trees of classes.
They are rooted in AnyVal and AnyRef So
AnyVal is the base class of all so-called
value classes and those are essentially
the primitive types that you see from,
from Java so you have Int and Long, and
Float, and Double, and Boolean, and those
types would all be subtypes of
Scala.AnyVal All the other classes are
subtypes of Scala.AnyRef AnyRef itself is
just an alias, a different name for Java
Lang Object, the root class of all Java
classes.
And here you see classes like the string
class of Java but you also see Scalar
classes such as iterabole] and sequence
and list.
We will get to know them later on.
All those classes happen to implement
another trait called Scalar.ScalarObject
object in addition to the any ref base
class.
And then on the bottom of the slide, you
see two types that are subtypes of many
other types.
They are called scalar.Nothing and
scalar.Now and we'll get to them in the
following slides.
I should say there's one other twist here
in this diagram, we see the relationships
between the numeric types, they are
actually written with dotted arrows, not
hard arrows, and that means that the
numeric types, they're not strictly in a
subtype relationship with each other, but
in a conversion relationship so you can
automatically convert and type such as
Long to Float, but it's not really a
subtype.
Why is it not a subtype?
Well subtype really means that the
conversion is the identity.
So that you don't need to rearrange the
bits in order to go from one type to the
other.
Whereas here, definitely if you to go a
Long from a Float, you do need to change
you representation of that type and what's
more in this case here the conversion is
not loss free.
You might actually lose some precision
going to a Long to a Float.
Okay now again at the top type in the
hierarchy, we have three of them.
Any, AnyRef and AnyVal. Any is the base
type of all type's and it's also the type
that defines certain universal methods.
We've already used equality, =,, = and its
opposite not equals.
Those are actually methods that are
conceptually defined in this type any, and
those methods actually mapped to the Java
equivalence which would be written equals.
That's the good method of Java.
So =,, = is essentially just a forwarder
that cause the Java equals methods unless
it's overwritten by a user code.
And also, in class, any of you would find
the method two string that you've already
seen that converts an object to a two
string.
And finally, you'll have a universal hash
code method that produces a hash code from
an object.
The two subtypes of type Any are the
AnyRef which is the base type of also
called the reference types and that's an
alias of Java Lang Objects and any vowel
which is the base type of all value types
which for the time being are just the
primitive types that Scala inherits from
Java.
So what about those, those two types at
the bottom, Nothing and Null.
Nothing is at the very bottom of all Scala
types.
It's a subtype of every other type.
And there's no value that has type
Nothing.
So you might ask, well, why is that
useful.
How is the type that has no value useful?
Well, there are actually two uses and the
two uses, it turns out they're connected.
The first is to signal abnormal
termination.
Sometimes a function would not return but
for instance would throw an exception or
abort the program and in that case you
might ask well what would the return type
of that function be? And the answer in
fact is the best possible the most precise
possible type is Nothing.
It doesn't return anything.
It will terminate abnormally.
And the second usage that you, we are
going to see shortly is as an element type
of empty collections.
So if you have, let's say, a set that
contains no elements,
You could say it's a set of nothing.
Something like that.
We will see that in a, in a second later
on So speaking of abnormal termination,
the usual way that is brought about in
both Java and Scala is using an exception
and in fact here the syntax for both Scala
and Java is exactly the same here we throw
expression where you right throw and then
comes some exception value and that throw
expression would then abort the evaluation
of the program with the given exception.
Let's do that in an example.
Let's say we have a function F def error
and it takes a message of type string.
And it should give us a throw new error as
an exception with the given message.
So calling error would immediately abort
the program.
So what we see here is that the computer
type for error was it's a method that
takes a string as an argument and it will
return nothing.
So the, scalatype checker was able to
figure out that this expression will not
terminate normally and therefore it's
[inaudible] type it's nothing.
Indeed if we call error now, some
exception value than what you would get is
not normally termination, but you would
get an exception trace that says, well,
and the exception Java Lang error was
thrown and that was the message that came
with it.
The other button type we have in the
diagram is Scala.Null Turns out that Null
is a subtype of all the classes that are,
themselves, reference types.
And it's also the type of the Null value.
Null is written in Scala as in Java.
It is a value of every reference type here
so, when somebody expects let's say a
string you could also pass it now.
So, the type of the Null value then is the
Null type which is written in the same way
just with the capital N and that type is a
subtype of every class that inherits from
object.
On the other hand it's incompatible with
subtypes of any value, so let's try that
out here, so we could write first val x =
null.
And here we, worksheet would answer that
the value of x is null and the type of
excess null with a Null. We can also then
assign x to another.
Value of, let's say type String And to see
that also works so the type...
The value of value x, with the type null,
That one actually conforms two Strings so
you can initialize the value y with the
value x.
On the other hand what you cannot do is
define a value of type Int z and
initialize that one to Null.
Then you will get an error which says that
the.
There is a type mismatch the compiler
found now.
The null value of the null type.
And it required an Int.
And then there comes a long string that
certain implicit conversions are not
applicable, which you can ignore.
So you've seen that null is a sub type
only of the reference types, not of the
value types.
Lets do an exercise.
Let's say I have the following expression.
If true one else false.
What should the type of that expression
be, in your opinion?
Possible.
So answers would be Int or maybe Boolean,
or maybe AnyVal or object or Any.
Well, to solve this question the easiest
thing would be to just enter this
expression in to the web-sheet and see
what it says right?
So if true, one else false.
What do we get?
We get AnyVal Why do we get AnyVal? Well
Let's look at the two branches of the'if'.
The first one is one has definitely
type'int'.
The second is false and that has
definitely type Boolean But then, those
two types don't match at this level So
what do we do?
Let us look back at the arrow key here.
So we see that we have Int here and we
have Boolean here, but both of these
values are also values of the supertype.
So that will be either AnyVal or Any.
And in this case AnyVal is better.
It conveys more information than Any.
So the type check actually picked the type
that matched both of these values, AnyVal
in that case, and that was as specific as
possible.
So that's why the type checker answered
with AnyVal.