Hi.
In this video we are going to show you how
to install the tools required for this
class on your machine.
This video is for people using the Linux
operating system.
If you're on a different operating system,
check the Getting Started section in the
video lectures part of the class website.
Everything that is shown on this video is
also explained in text on the Tools Setup
Wiki page of the class website.
So we go to the tool setup page, and we
see that there are three things that we
need to install for our class.
The first one is the JDK, the Java
Development Kit, which is a run-time
environment on which Scalar programs are
executed.
The second one is SPT, a build tool for
Scala, which you will also be using for
submitting your assignment solutions to
Coursera.
The third one is the Scalar ID for
Eclipse, which is the ID, which we are
going to use in this class.
Okay.
So let's get started by installing the
JDK.
In the section, installing the JDK, there
are three subsections for different
operating system, And this week, we are
going to look at the part related to
Linux.
When recording this screen cast, I am on a
Ubuntu system and therefor these are the
instructions that apply to my system.
If you are using a different Linux
distribution you will have to do the JDK
installation differently.
So on Ubuntu the only thing that we need
to do is start a terminal and install the
open JDK using app get.
To start a terminal, I just click on the
dash home in Ubuntu and I search for
terminal.
And I can launch terminal.
Since we will be using the terminal a lot
in this tutorial, I will lock it to the
launcher and make it available more
quickly.
Okay, the command to install the open JDK
on Ubuntu is the following.
So we do, apt get install on JDK 7-JDK.
And you have to enter your password, and
then app-get will ask you to confirm.
And, now it will download and install to
JDK.
Okay.
Once that apt-get has finished installing
the JDK, we want to make sure that
everything has been set up correctly.
We go back to the Tool Setup page.
And we read the section, verifying your
setup.
So, what we have to do is, starting a new
terminal, so you close the existing one
and start a new one, and then you have to
type java-version.
Now, you can see the version number of the
JDK, that you just installed.
Okay, since this worked fine, we are
closing the terminal window and moving on
to the second step.
The second step is installing SBT.
In order to install SBT, it has to be
downloaded from this URL.
So, we simply click the URL, we save the
file.
And Firefox will send it to the download
folder of my home directory.
So, we go to the home directory, download
folder, and we see this SBT archive.
So now, we have to extract the archive.
One way to do this in a Window is right
clicking on the file and just selecting
extract here.
Okay, so the SBT folder process has now
been created.
Contains indirectly, which in fact
contains the executable for SBT.
So since SBT is a program that we might
want to use in the future, I'm going to
move it to a different location.
So I cut the SPT folder and in my home
directory I create a new folder, which I
call 'applications'.
And I paste this SBT folder in there.
Okay, so let's go back to the tool setup
instructions.
So we already unpack the archive.
And now what you need to do is add in the
bin directory of the SPT installation that
we just downloaded in the path environment
variable.
In order to do that, you have to open a
file called dash rc which is in your home
directory in a tech study tour.
The easiest way to open that file is to
open a terminal.
And type in G edit and then dot bash RC.
This will open the text editor with the
bash RC file.
Now in order to add SBT to the path we go
back to the setup instructions wiki page.
And we copy that export command that we
need to add to the bash RC file.
We copy it and we go back to G Edit, and
we scroll down to the end of the file, and
just paste the command.
Now, in fact, you have to update the path
to your SBT directory with the real path
on your system.
So the place where I installed it is in
dash Home.
And then my user name, LUC, and then back
slash, applications, and SBT bin.
Okay, so I close the G edit text editor, I
save my changes.
And now I have to verify that the SBT has
been installed correctly.
In order to do that, I have to open a new
terminal window because the changes to
bash RC will not be applied to existing
terminal sessions.
So I close my terminal.
I open a new one.
And in order to test SBT, I type SBT-H.
As expected, I see a help message from
SBT, so everything is fine.
Okay, so now we close the terminal window,
and the last thing that we need to do is
installing the Scalae ID for Eclipse.
The Scala ID for Eclipse, with all the
plugins and settings that we need for the
course can be downloaded from the
following URL.
So I open this page.
New tab.
And I scroll down to the download links.
Now you just have to select, the Eclipse
distribution which matches your operating
system.
In my case I'm on a Linux system with 32
bits.
So I download this file and save it in the
downloads folder.
Okay, once the download of the Scala ID
has finished, I can close the download
window.
Close the download page for the ID.
And open the download folder in my home
directory.
Next, we unpack the downloaded Scala ID
package using the same mechanism as we
used before for SPT.
So we right click on the file, and we
select extract here.
Okay.
Again, since the Scalar ID is an
application that we will continue using in
the future, I right-click on the new
Eclipse folder, select cut, then I go to
my Home folder, and then to Applications.
I right click and select paste.
In order to start Eclipse, I simply open
the Eclipse folder, and double click on
the Eclipse executable.
When starting Eclipse, you always have to
define which work space you are going to
use.
We recommend that you create one work
space for this class, which you then can
reuse for all of the assignments of the
class.
Okay.
I will do that right now.
So I click the Browse folder to go to my
file system.
I go to my Home folder.
And they create a new folder, which I call
Prog Fun Workspace.
Okay.
And select the folder and click Okay.
And then I start Eclipse.
Okay, so this is the Scalar ID.
In order to verify that everything is set
up correctly.
We go back to the setup instructions wiki
page.
On the bottom of the page there's a
tutorial on how to create a hello world
project in Eclipse.
So I will do this right now inside
Eclipse.
In order to create the new project, you
select "File", "New", "Scalar Project",
from the menu, and you give the project a
name.
Hello World, and you click finish.
Now we will create the hello world program
file.
So we opened the hello world project.
We right click on the source folder and we
select new scalar object.You have to give
the object a name, so in this case we will
use hello and we will put the object into
a package.
In this case package greeter.
Okay.
Now the source code for Hello World can
be, again, found on the wiki page.
So we go back to the wiki page, and we
scroll down a bit to find the source code
of the Hello World application.
We select the code.
Right click and copy.
We go back to Eclipse, and we paste the
code.
Okay.
Now, when we save the file, you will
notice that, Eclipse already compiled the
file.
Since this file defines an executable
application, you can directly run it
inside Eclipse.
The easiest way to do this is
right-clicking on the help word Scalar
source file, selecting run as, Scalar
application.
You will then see the output of the "hello
world" program on the bottom of the
screen.
Good.
So, the last thing that we're going to
show you in this video is a brand new
feature that has been implemented for the
Scalar ID.
The feature is called the Scalar
worksheet, and it gives you a very
interactive console to work with Scalar.
In order to create the Scalar worksheet,
you have to right click on a package,
select new, and then select Scalar
worksheet.
You have to give the worksheet a name, and
then click finish.
Okay.
I have to make this window a bit bigger,
okay?
Every expression that you type into a
worksheet will be evaluated on the fly.
In order to demonstrate that, we go back
to the Tool Setup instructions, we scroll
down to the end and we copy the statements
that are at the end of the screen.
We go back to Eclipse and, and we paste
this code into the worksheet.
Okay, so once we save the file, Eclipse
will immediately evaluate all the
questions in the worksheet.
So what we do here is we define a value x
to be one.
We define a function increase which
returns its argument increased by one.
And, we test increase by invoking it, and
we pass the value x into the function.
And you can see, that the result of
passing x into increase, is the value two.
Now, you can easily go back in the
worksheet and change some definitions, for
instance, now we change x to be five.
And, once you save the file, the entire
worksheet is re-applied and evaluated, and
the resulting value now is six.