Welcome.
I'm going to give you now a quick
introduction of my course, Functional
Programming Principles in Scala, and tell
you how we are going to organize it.
As usual, the course will consist of a
sequence of videos which will introduce
the elements of the course one by one, and
the videos will also have quizzes where
you are asked to fill in some questions.
Those questions could be multiple choice
or also, quite often, we ask you to
program something.
After the quizzes, you will always see the
answer in the videos.
Besides the quizzes, there are also
assignments.
The assignments you have to hand in, and
you are going to be graded on the
assignments.
And if you pass the assignments, then you
will get a certificate at the end of the
course.
The quizzes, by contrast, they are just
for your own education.
You are not going to be graded on them.
There's a timeline for the course.
You can expect a new set of videos every
Tuesday morning, and including a new
assignment.
And you will have one week to hand in the
assignments, or the assignments will have
to be handed in Monday night the following
week.
We're going to use for the programming in
the course the Eclipse, IDE, Integrated
Development Environment.
And, I will show you later on how you can
download the IDE and how you can install
it.
There's also another tool we meet for
handing in the assignments that's called
SBT, the Scala Build Tool.
Again, we will go through the details how
to get and to install SBT.
Okay.
Once you are on the site, the first thing
you could do is go to Tools Setup.
Here, you'll see detailed setup
instructions how to setup Eclipse and SBT
for all the major operating systems,
Windows, Mac OS and Linux.
You could also simplify your life simply
by looking at one of the three videos that
can tell you exactly what to do to get
started.
Once you've done that, you could go next
to Assignments, getting, going to get
started in the assignments.
And then you'll see an example assignment
which is optional.
We will grade it but it won't count
towards your points for the course.
That's essentially takes you through the
steps of drafting an assignment, drafting
an, an exercise submitting your solution
to the assignment so that then when we
start at the real assignments, you already
know all the mechanics for that.
That's all there is to know for now.
Have fun with the course and the
assignments.