Hi there, in this video we're going to
show
you how to get started with Scala and
IntelliJIDEA.
First of all you have to
download IntelliJIDEA from it's official
website JedPrice.com/idea.
Notice that IntelliJIDEA comes in two
editions.
Ultimate, the commercial one, and the
Community
Edition which is free and open source.
Support for Scala is fully available in
the Community Edition.
Once the file is downloaded, go ahead and
open it.
If you're using MAC OS X, simply drag the
application to the applications folder.
If you're a Windows user, the built
in installer will guide you through the
process.
If you're a Linux user, just unzip the
package to any folder.
When we run IntelliJIDEA for the first
time it offers us to import settings.
Here we don't have any previous
installments, so we simply skip this step.
Now, before we create a Scala project or
open one, we have to download the Scala
plugin.
Click the Configure menu and then click
Plugins.
Here we see the list of plugins already
installed.
To install additional JetBrains plugins,
click this button under the list.
If you sort the list of plugins by the
number of
downloads, the Scala plugin is sure to be
at the top.
Select this Scala plugin and click to
install it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
After the plugin is downloaded you will be
offered to restart the IDE.
Make sure you do.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, let's see how to create a
simple Scala application and run it using
IntelliJIDEA.
Choose the Create New Project menu and
select Scala Project Type.
Since we're going to use SBT as the build
tool, choose the SBT option.
Notice that when you create a Scala
project, you have to choose a project SDK.
If you have no Java SDK configured, click
the New
button and choose the home directory of
your Java SDK.
Every time the project is being loaded,
you have a chance to
pick up a few tips and tricks on how to
use the ID.
When you run the IDE for the first time,
it
shows you how to open the Tool Windows
hidden by default.
You can access Tool Windows using the
button in the bottom left-side corner.
The IDE has created an empty Scala project
with Java and Scala source roots.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's create a class and define a method
there returning a hello string.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Since we want to be sure our code is
correct, we'll write an appropriate test
before implementing that method.
To do that we need to add a Scala test
library to the project.
Let's do it with the SBT file.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
When we change SBT build files, the IDE
offers us to synchronize these changes
with a project.
Once we confirm to refresh the project, it
takes
a bit to download and configure the added
libraries.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
As you can see, the Scala test library has
been added to the project.
Now we're back to the class.
Let's use the Navigate to Test action.
As we don't have any tests yet, the IDE
offers us to create one.
Let's name the test say hello method works
correctly.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now I'll create a new instance of the
hello class.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Make sure the method returns hello Scala.
Now use the Context menu to run the test.
As expected the test fails.
Time to implement the method.
Run the test again and make sure it's
green.
Now I'll show you how to use Scala
Worksheets.
You can create one in the Scala source
root via the Context menu.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's create a hello instance and call
it's method.
When the code is ready, click the Run
button on the tool bar.
The results appear almost immediately.
That's all for creating a new project, now
let's see how to import an existing
project.
Let's go to the Assignment Page
and download a sample project.
[BLANK_ AUDIO].
Then go to File > Import Project.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And choose a Build.SBT file to import
from.
Confirm to open in the current window.
Sometimes it may take awhile to download
the libraries listed in the build file.
Once it's done we can explore the project
files.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Or run the tests.
Last but not least is the Terminal Tool
window.
It helps you access the Command Line
without leaving the IDE.
It is useful for
running SBT tasks,
among other things.
[BLANK_AUDIO]