Hi.
In this video, we are going to show you
how to install the tools required for our
class on your machine.
This video is for people using Mac OSX.
If you're using a different operating
system, check the getting started section
on the video lectures part of the class
website.
Everything that we show in this video is
also explained in text on the Tools Set Up
wiki page on the class website.
So, let's have a look at this page.
As you can see, there are three things
that you need to install on your machine
in order to prepare for this class.
The first one is the JDK, the Java Runtime
Environment, which is used to execute
Scala programs.
The second one is SBT, a build tool for
Scala, which you will also use to submit
your assignment solutions to Coursera.
The third one is the Scala IDE for
Eclipse, which is the IDE that we are
going to use in this class.
Okay, so, let's get started by installing
the Java debug kit.
Every section in this tutorial has three
sub sections one for each operating
system.
Since we are currently on Mac OS10, we
will look at how to install JDK on Mac
OSX.
In fact, Mac OSX either comes with Java
pre-installed or it will install it
automatically for you.
To verify, if you already have Java, you
have to open a terminal application.
So, you open the Finder, we go to the
Applications folder and we open the
Utilities folder.
In utilities, there's the application
named terminal.
Since we will be using the terminal a lot,
in this class it makes sense to drag it
into your dock.
Okay, so we can close the Finder window,
open a terminal.
And now, we want to verify if we have Java
installed.
In order to do that, you type Java minus
version into the terminal.
On this machine I don't have Java
installed yet.
So, I will get the window which tells me,
to open Java, I actually need to install
it.
So, the only thing you need to do is click
the Install button.
Of course, you have to agree to the
license agreements.
Okay.
So, once the Java installation has
finished, we just click Okay and we run
Java minus version again.
Now, we see the version number of the Java
installation that has been installed.
Okay.
So, we close this terminal window and we
move on to the second tool that we need to
install.
The second tool that we need to install is
SBT.
In order to install SBT on your system,
you can either use the homebrew package
manager or you can do a manual
installation.
In this video, I will do a manual
So, we download SBT from this URL.
Once the download has finished, we
navigate to the file in the Finder, and we
double click it to extract SBT.
Okay.
So, since SBT is an application that we
will reuse in the future, we will move it
to a different location.
So, I open a new Finder window, and in my
home folder I create a subdirectory named
applications.
Now, I take the extracted SBT folder and I
move it to my newly created Applications
folder.
Inside the SBT folder, you have a bin
subdirectory, which contains the
executable files for SBT.
So, let's close the Finder window and go
back to the tutorial.
So, we downloaded SBT, we unpacked the
Archive, and moved it to the Applications
folder.
And, and what we need to do last is adding
the bin directory of SBT to the path
environment variable.
In order to do that, you have to open the
file.bashprofile which is located in
your home directory.
If the file doesn't exist yet, you will
have to create it.
Okay, so let's open a new Terminal window
and lets check if the bashprofile file
already exists. So, we type
ls.bashprofile.
In my case, the file does no exist yet
but it might very well be that you
already have it.
So, in order to create or edit a file, we
can use the Nano Text Editor, which is a
very simple command-line text editor.
We type, nano.ashprofile and hit
Enter. So now, we need to add one
export command to dispatch profile file.
We go back to the setup instructions, we
copy the export command.
Right click, Copy, and go back to the
terminal, and paste it using right click
Paste.
Now, in fact, we have to change the path
of our SBT installation to match the path
were we actually extracted SBT.
In my case, this was /users/luc, my
username, /applications, and then SBT bin
Now, we can exit the Nano text editor
using Control+X, and we will save the
changes to the file by confirming with Y
and then hitting Enter for the file name.
Okay, now, we need to verify if SBT has
been installed correctly.
We close the Terminal window and we go
back to the instructions.
In order to verify the SBT installation,
we have to start a new Terminal window,
and we have to type SBT-H.
If the installation was successful, then
you'll see SBT Help message appear on the
screen.
Okay, so, we close the Terminal window, we
go back to the set up instructions and we
go to the last tool that we have to
install, the is Scala IDE four eclipse.
In order to install this Scala IDE, we
have to open this website and scroll down
to the downloads.
Now, you have to find the version of the
Scala IDE which matches your operating
system.
In my case, I am on a 64-bit Mac OSX.
So, I click this link.
Once the download of the Scala IDE has
finished, we open the Download folder in
Finder.
We unpack the Scala IDe by simply double
clicking the file.
Since, the Scala IDE is on applications
that we will reuse in the future, we will
also move it to our Applications folder.
So, I open a new window, I go to my
Applications folder, and then move the
Eclipse folder into my applications.
In order to open the Scala IDE, you simply
go into the Eclipse folder and you double
click the Eclipse file.
When starting up Eclipse, you have to
define which your, workspace you want to
use.
We recommend that you create one work
space which you can then reuse for all the
assignments of our class.
I will do this now by clicking the Browse
button and going to my home folder.
Okay.
So now, here I will create a new folder
named ProgFun Workspace.
I will select the folder and click Open.
By clicking Okay, Eclipse will start up
using that new workspace.
Okay, in order to test the Scala IDE,
we'll go back to the tool set of
instructions page.
We can close the Download page, and the
Tool Setup page explains you to create a
simple Hello World project in the Scala
IDE.
I will show you how to do this now.
So, you go to Eclipse and in the menu ,
you select File, New Scalar Project.
You give the project a name, for instance,
Hello World.
Okay.
In order to enter the source code for the
Hello World application, we have to create
a new Scala object.
So, we open a project, and we right-click
on the Source folder, and select U Scala
object.
We give the object a name, in this case,
Hello.
And we define in which package job check
we defined, so we put here the package
greeter.
We confirm by clicking Finish.
Okay, now, the source code for the Hello
World application can be found on the
Tools Setup instructions.
So, we go back to the wiki page and we
scroll down to find the source code that
we need.
We select it, copy it, go back to Eclipse
and just paste it into the file.
We saved the file and, you can notice that
once you save the file, Eclipse will
automatically compile the entire project
for you.
In order to execute the Hello World
application, you simply have to right
click on the hello.scala source file,
select Run S, and select Scala
application.
You will see the output of the Hello World
program in the, in the eclipse console.
The next feature that we are going to show
you, is a brand new feature named the
Scala worksheet.
In a Scala worksheet, you can type
arbitrary Scala expressions and see them
evaluated on the fly.
It's a great tool to learn and explore
Scala.
In order to create the worksheet, we right
click on the Create Package, we select New
Scala Worksheet.
You have to give the worksheet a name, and
click Finish to create it.
Okay.
I will increase the size of this window in
order to see all the, all the worksheet.
Now, to try out the worksheet, we have
prepared some instructions for you that
you can paste into this newly created
object.
So, if you go back to the set up
instructions, and scroll down to the
bottom of the page, you will see a few
lines of code that you can copy and paste
back in this freshly created Scala
worksheet.
Okay.
Once you save to file, Eclipse will
automatically evaluate at all the lines
that are part of the worksheet and show
the result of the evaluation on the right
hand side.
In this example, we assigned the number
one to the value x.
We define the function increase which
returns its argument increase by one.
Every test increase by invoking it and
passing x into the function.
You can see that increase of x returns
two.
Now, if you go back to Worksheet, and
change the definition of x, for instance
to be five, as soon as we save the file,
the whole buffer will be reevaluated.
And you can see that the result of the
invocation of increase is now six.