In this session, we will introduce stream
as a new data structure.
Streams are like list but they tailored
evaluated only on demand.
We would see how this lets you write very
elegant solutions to search problem.
In the previous sessions, you've seen a
number of operations on immutable
collections that provide powerful tools
for communitorial search.
For instance, if you wanted to find the
second prime number between 1,000 and
10,000, you could write an expression
strictly according to this specification.
Go from 1000 to 10000,
Filter with this prime predicate,
Take the second element.
This is much shorter than the recursive
alternative, which you see down here,
where there's a function second prime,
which finds the second prime number in a
given interval between from and to, and
that in turn calls a more general function
nthPrime, which takes the nthPrime number
in again, an interval between from and to,
and that nthPrime has the usual recursive
set up to iterate through the interval
between from and to.
Feasible, but definitely much archaic and
less elegant than the simple expression
here.
However, the shorter expression also has a
serious problem.
It's is evaluation is very, very
inefficient, because what we do here is we
construct all the prime numbers between
1000 and 10000, only ever to take its
second element.
Presumably there are many more prime
numbers between 1000 and 10000.
So you could say, well,
Maybe my bound, 10,000, is too high, I
should reduce that,
But without knowing a priori where the
prime numbers are, I would always risk
that the bound is too low and I would miss
finding the prime number.
So we are in the uncomfortable position to
be either really bad in performance
because the bound is too high or risking
finding the prime number at all because
the bound is too low.
However, there's a special trick that can
make the short code also efficient.
The idea is that we want to avoid
computing the tail of a sequence until
that tail is needed for the evaluation
result, and of course, that might be
never.
That idea is implemented in a new class
which is called the stream.
Streams are similar to lists but their
tail is evaluated only on demand.
So, here's how it can define streams.
They are, can be built from a constant
Stream.empty, so the empty value and the
stream object, and a constructor
Stream.cons.
So to build a stream that consists of the
number one and two, you could write
Stream.cons one, Stream.cons two,
Stream.empty.
And, of course, streams can also be
defined like the other collections by
using the stream object as a factory,
So you could write simply stream of one,
two, three.
A third way to produce streams is with a
toStream method, which can be applied to
any collection to produce a stream.
So in example, you see here, we have a
range one to 1000 and turn it into a
stream with a toStream method.
It's interesting to see what the result of
that call is so what we see here is a
stream of Int, which is written like this.
It's a, it's a Stream(1, ).?
What that mean is that a stream is
essentially a, recursive structure like a
list so we have a one here, but the tail
is not yet evaluated, so that's why the
interpretor worksheet has printed a
question mark here.
The tail will be evaluated if somebody
wants to know explicitly.
Let's look at stream evaluation in a
little bit more detail using ranges as an
example.
Instead of the usual range and then
toStream expression, I have decided that I
wanted to work from first principles and I
wrote a streamRange function directly
here.
So that's the usual recursive function, if
the lower bound is greater or equal to
higher bound, I return the empty stream,
Otherwise, it's a cons of the lower bound
and a recursive call of streamRange(lo +
one, Hi)).
If you compare that to the function that
does the same thing for lists, here is
listRange and turns out that the two
functions are actually completely
isomorphic.
They have exactly the same structure,
Only one returns a stream, the other
returns a list,
And the empty stream here corresponds to
the Nil case for the lists and the cons
case for the streams corresponds to the
cons operator for the lists.
Yet their operational behavior is
completely different.
If we look at listRaange first, what would
that function do if we have listRange
(one, ten).
What would the thing do?
Well, it would create a list with the one
here and so on,
Until I have the ten here and I have a
Nil,
So it would generate the complete list in
one go.
Whereas for a streamRange, what would
happen is it would create a first cons
pair with a one here and then the rest
would be a ?.
So it wouldn't be generated, instead,
there would be an object that would know
how to reconstitute the stream if somebody
demands it.
If I take the tail then of this
streamRange result,
Then, somebody wants to know I would
create the second element of the stream
and the third element would have a ?,
And so on until potentially somebody
forces wants to know all the elements in
this stream, in which case, in the end, I
would have the same structure as for the
lists. But before I would have partially
constructed streams, it always end in,
essentially the ?, which stands for
unevaluated stream.
In most respects, Streams are actually
like List, in particular, Streams support
almost all the methods of a List.
So for instance, to find the second prime
number between 1000 and 10,000, the
problem we started with, it could simply
write it this way, so instead of writing
the range directly, we convert the range
to a string, then we apply the filter
method on stream and we apply the apply
method on a stream with the one as the
argument.
There's only one exception where streams
don't follow list and that's the cons
operator.
So if you write x :: xs, that's always
produces a list, never a stream.
But there is an alternative operator which
is written #, :: which produces a stream.
So x.
#, :: xs is actually the same as
Stream.cons (x, xs),
And that operator can be used in
expressions, as you see here, but also in
patterns..
So let's look at the implementation of
Streams.
It's actually quite close to the
implementation of Lists.
So let's start with a base trait, there's
a trait Stream[+A] and it extends a Seq[A]
just like lists do, and it has the same
fundamental operations as lists, namely
isEmpty, head and tail.
And again as for lists all other methods
can be defined in terms of these three
fundamental ones.
So if we look at complete implementation
of Streams than actually these also follow
closely the ones for lists.
There's one difference, however, that for
Streams, the economical implementations
are defined as members of the Stream
object, so that's why we write
Stream.empty, which corresponds to list
Nil and Stream.cons,
Which corresponds to the :: class.
The implementations of the empty and cons
is actually very close to the ones in
List, so, cons would have the following
implementations of isEmpty head and tail,
isEmpty is falls.
Head is the first parameter you pass and
tail is the second parameter you pass in.
For empty, it's the same thing as for
lists again, isEmpty is true in head and
tail, were true exceptions because, of
course, they're not define for, empty
strings.
So the one thing where the cons class and
the cons method here differ fundamentally
is this here.
So for the cons method for streams, the
tail parameter is a by name parameter,
As you, as it shown by the leading arrow
here.
Whereas for the list cons class, the tail
parameter is a normal call by value
parameter.
That's the only difference that matters
between strings and lists, and that's the
only thing that explains this dramatic
difference in runtime behavior.
So because of, tail is a call by name
parameter, it means that, when I first
construct a cons cell for a stream, the
tail is not evaluated.
It, it will be evaluated the first time
somebody dereferences the name tail, and
that's here.
So that if somebody calls a tail method,
the tail parameter will be dereferenced
and the rest of the stream will be
evaluated.
That's it.
The other stream methods are then
implemented analogously to the list
counterparts.
So for instance here, you see the filter
method, it does the usual thing.
If the string is empty it returns it. If
the head satisfies the predicate P, then
we do a cons(head, tail.filter(p)), and
otherwise we do a tail.filter(p).
So what in particular happens here is that
if I do a filter on a stream whose head
satisfies the predicate, then I do a
computation tail.filter(p) here, but that
computation is the second tail parameter
of a cons construction.
So that means that the evaluation of
filter down the spine of the stream will
be delayed again, until somebody wants to
find out what the result of the taking the
tail of the result stream is.
So here's a little quiz where you can test
whether you understood how streams
evaluate.
I have modified the StreamRange method by
adding a print statement here that prints
out the low bound every time stream
streamRange is called.
So, when you now write streamRange of 110
with this method and then take(3) and then
toList,
What would you expect gets printed?
Nothing or one of these results here?
So let's see how we would reason about it.
Have you seen when we take the
streamRange(1, ten), we just evaluate the
first element here and the rest is, is yet
unknown.
The take method on Streams, if we look at
its definition and evaluate it, then it
would do nothing special, it would
essentially again return as a stream where
the only node the first element.
But then if we finally convert the stream
to a list, then of course, we need to
force it because our list can't be left
unevaluated.
So by the time we do that, we create a
list with three elements one, two, three
and the rest is Nil,
That's the result.
And to produce that list, we have to go
down three elements in the orig, original
argument stream in the streamRange.
So what I expect is that we would print
one, two, three, And you can test that
yourself by submitting the streamRange
program at this expression to a worksheet.