In this session we come back to the
problem of proving properties about
programs.
Where before, we covered just lists, we
will now look at more job data structures,
Maybe trees.
Remember in the intro to this course, I
told you that functional programming is
important because it's very close to the
mathematical theories of data structures.
We put that to a test.
Now we will develop such a theory for
integer sets and prove an implementation
correct with respect to the theory.
As was the case in the previous proving
sessions, the material in this session is
optional for the online class.
If you're a student of the Life EPFL
class, you should follow the material,
because it might be relevant for the exam.
But we can generalize the structural
induction principal for lists to arbitrate
these structures.
The principal then becomes the following.
We want to prove a property P of T for all
trees of a certain type What we need to do
to do that, is we need to show that P of L
holds for all leaves types of the tree.
And for each type of internal node T which
has let's say sub-trees as one, two SN, we
need to show that under the assumption
that PS1 and PSN all the sub, all the
sub-trees satisfy the predicate than P of
T holds.
So let's use this proof technique to show
some interesting facts about IntSet.
We call our definition of IntSets from
previous sessions.
We had an abstract class IntSet with
operation include and contains, and then
we had two different implementations.
Once was, one was an object empty and the
other was the class nonempty, and there
was an invariant.
We assume then that was that the elements
in a tree were ordered.
That means that the left subtree of any
nonempty tree contained elements that were
smaller, or smaller than the current
element.
And the right subtree contained elements
that were larger.
And our implementations of contains and
include made use of that invariant.
So we would like to prove that
implementation of IntSet correct.
But what does it even mean?
What do we mean by, by proving the
correctness of an IntSet implementation?
Well, one way to define correctness would
be to define some laws that our
implementation should just, should
satisfy, and then prove that the
implementation indeed does that.
So in the case of IntSet, what laws could
we come up with?
The first law says the empty set does not
contain any, any element so empty contains
x is always false.
The second law says that if we add an
element x to a set, an arbitrary set and
then ask whether the set contains x, then
we are certain that we will get back true.
And the third law says that if we add an
element x to a set and then ask whether
the set contains some other element y.
Then the answer is the same thing as
simply S contains Y.
So, it didn't matter the fact whether we
added X or not.
The answer will be invariant under that.
In fact, one can show that these three
laws completely characterize what it is,
to be an n set.
So, the, we have now an algebraic
specification of IntSet which is complete.
But it still remains how to prove these
laws.
So, let's start with the first one.
Empty contains x equal false.
Well that one is actually easy because
that's a direct consequence of the
definition of contains and empty.
Have a quick look at it, so here you see
empty contains any element would give us
false.
The second proposition says that if we
include X and S and then ask, whether the
set contains X, we would get true.
And that we can prove by a structure
induction on the set S.
The base case would be the set S is empty,
so we are left with the expression, empty
include X contains X.
Now, empty include X, we know what that
is, by the rule of empty.include.
That would give us a nonempty set X with
two empty subsets, and we ask whether that
one contains X.
And, the answer here is true because of
the clause of, contains in a nonempty set
where we know that if we ask for the
element at the top of the tree then the
answer is True.
We can compare to the implementation of
nonempty to verify that.
So that was the base case.
What about the induction step?
So the induction step would be that we
have a tree, call it nonempty.
With free element zet.
L and R and we have to proof the
proposition that include x and contain x
is true for each of these trees.
We actually have two cases here.
We could have the case that the Z is the
same as the X, or that the Z, the element
of the nonempty, is different from the X.
Let's take these two cases turn by turn.
From the first case, I assume that the Z
equals six, so I'm left with tree nonempty
XLR, and have to show that include X
contains X equals true.
So what can we do in this case?
Well, we can look at what's the definition
of include.
If we look that up then we find that
including an element to a tree that
already has that element at the root is
the original tree.
So this expression here.
Would simplify to that one here.
And then looking up the contain operation,
we, we find that asking contain.
On a tree that contains that element at
the root would give you back true.
So the whole expression simplifies to
true.
So that handles the case where we, we're
left with a non-empty tree, and the root
element X of the tree was the same element
as the one we included, and contains
check.
What if the root element is different?
There again we have two choices.
Either the root element is smaller than
our element x or it's larger.
So let's look at the case where it is
smaller.
So we would, we have a, a tree a non empty
y, l, r include x, we ask whether it
contains x and we would like it to return
true.
So, the.
By the definition of nonempty include, we,
we can rewrite this term to this one here.
Why?
Well, because we know that X is greater
than the root element Y, so we would have
a recursive include at the, on the right
hand side of the tree.
Okay, let's look at contents now.
Again by the same reasoning, we would have
that contents test of a tree like that,
would translate into a contents test of
its right sub-tree.
So that would be root include X contains
X.
And now we can apply the induction
hypothesis, which says for all sub-trees I
assume that the property is proven, so I
am left with true.
There's a third induction step to do where
now the root element of the tree y is
greater than x, but this one is completely
analogous to the previous one so I'm going
to omit it.
Now, let's prove the third proposition.
That proposition reads that.
Xs include Y contains X is the same as XS
contains X provided X and Y are different.
So, if X and Y are different, it makes no
difference whether I add Y to the set and
ask whether and, it contains a given
element, X, or whether I ask the set
directly.
And to proof again would be by structure
induction.
So assume first that the element that we
add is smaller than the element we test
for.
The dual case where the element we add is
larger is completely analogous so we don't
need to do both cases.
The base case, then, would be that the set
is empty, so we include an element y into
an empty set, and then we ask whether it
contains x.
And to show is that that's actually the
same as asking the empty set whether it
contains x directly.
So, empty include Y, gives us nonempty Y,
empty, empty.
Asking whether that contains X, gives us
empty contains X.
So, more precisely we go in the right
subtree, because that's where the X is
bigger than Y, so that's the empty here.
And that concludes the proposition.
That's what we needed to show.
Now we have to do the inductive step.
So the inductive step is a tree, non
empty.
With some root node Z, and a subtree L,
and a subtree R.
And unfortunately, the five different
cases to consider.
So the first case is that the root of the
tree is, is, is the same as the node X.
Second one is, it's the same as Y.
The third one is, it's smaller than both Y
and X.
The fourth one is, it's between Y and X.
And the fifth one is, it's larger than
both Y and X.
So let's look at some of these cases in
turn.
The first two cases are easy.
Lets first assume that the root of our
tree is x.
So we have this expression here.
Non empty XLR include y contains x.
So if we include y in a tree like that,
then what happens is that we actually go
to the left sub tree and include y here.
Because by assumption y is smaller than x.
So we ask whether that tree contains x,
and here the answer is obviously yes
because the tree contains already x at the
root.
So by the definition of non-empty contains
we get back true.
What we wanted.
The second case would be that the root of
the tree is the same as y, and if we look
at the right-hand side non-empty xlr
contains x.
Then by the same reasoning that one is
also true.
So the equation is established.
The second easy case is where the root of
the tree is the same as Y.
So now we include Y in a tree that already
has root Y and that of course is the same
as the original tree.
That doesn't change anything and that
again is what we wanted.
So now we come to the more difficult
cases.
The first case is that we are left with
the three non-empty ZLR, where set is
smaller than Y and X.
And in that case we'd need to show again
that, that expression here is the same as
just non-empty ZLR contains X.
So what can we do here?
Well, again we apply the law of non-empty
include to conclude that yes, we have to
include the element Y to the right
sub-tree, because Y is greater than Z.
Then we, apply the definition of contains
to conclude in turn that, yes, we have to
look at the right sub tree.
Because X is also greater than that.
And then we can apply the induction
hypothesis to say, R include Y contains X
is the same as R contains X.
Because we assume the theorem to be
already proven for R.
And that, in fact, is the same as
non-empty ZLR contains x, because if we
simplify that expression, we see that
because x is greater than z, we look again
at the right sub-tree r, so again we have
established the equality.
The next case is where z is now between y
and x so we have the same situation as
before but the value of z now is between y
and x.
So what we do in this case here is that
including y into the tree here, we go to
the left of tree because Y is smaller than
that.
Asking the contents.
We go to the right of tree because x, x is
larger than set so we look actually we
include and we test in different subtrees.
So we're left with r contains x.
And that actually is already the same as
non empty set ZLR contains x by the
definition of non empty contains work
backwards.
Because again, for this tree here, we
look, again in the right subtree.
So we've see that, in this case here,
we've established the equa-, equality
without resorting to the induction
hypotheses.
Because the inclusion and the test fell
into different subtrees.
So the third case is where that is larger
than both y and x.
And that's actually a complete dual of the
third case where that was smaller than
both y and x.
So I have written down the proof here, but
I will not go into the details one by one.
These are all the cases, so the
proposition is established, so this proof
was quite involved, but on the other hand
we were also showing something quite
significant.
Namely the correctness of a non trivial
implementation of sets of binary trees.
I would argue that the complexity of the
purely functional equational proofs often
compare favorably, with what you would
have to do in an imperative language.
If you haven't had enough of proving yet.
Here's an exercise for you which is, in
fact, quite hard.
I come back to the question of adding
union to IntSet So here's a way to do it,
which is actually a bit more efficient
than the first solution that I've shown
you in the worksheet.
So we would have, the union operation of
the empty set is, of course, the other set
that we add to union.
And then union of a nonempty set would be
defined like this.
We take the left.
Sub-tree, we union it with the, the right
sub-tree, unioned with the other set, and
finally include x in, into the resulting
tree at the end.
So what I would like you to do is, to
prove the correctness of union, which is
translated into the following law.
What you would like to have is that if we
take the union of two sets, and we then
ask whether it contains an arbitrary
element x, that this is equivalent to
asking whether either x has contain x or y
is contain x, so both sides should be true
and false for the same sets and for the
same elements.
The task then is to show this proposition
by using structure induction on XS.