One nice aspect of laziness, is that it
makes it easy to deal with infinite amount
of works.
Just do everything only when it is
demanded.
Following this principle, we look at ways
to define and manipulate infinite streams.
You saw that all elements of the stream
except the first one are computed only
when they're needed to produce a result.
One maybe surprising possibility this
opens is to define infinite streams.
So, for instance the stream of all
integers starting from a given number,
could be define like this.
It would say, def from of an n equals the
stream consisting of n followed by from n
+ one.
And normally, of course, this would be a
non-terminating recursive computation but
because the stream const operator is lazy
in its right operands, the from n + one
here would be actually calculated only if
somebody is interested in the second
element of the stream that's defined here.
So, using from, we can now write infinite
streams, for instance, the string of all
natural number would be from zero or the
stream of all multiples of four could be
the stream of all natural numbers, mapped
by times four.
So, each, take each the natural number,
multiply it by four, that gives the stream
that returns all multiples of four.
So, let's see this in a worksheet.
I've already define from, so,
And the stream of natural numbers would be
from zero,
Stream of multiples by four,
Would be the natural numbers mapped by
times four.
To see it in action, I could then take m4s
and take, let's say, first hundred
elements,
And convert the whole thing to a list
which would force it so there would indeed
see the list that contains the first
hundred multiples of fours.
But, of course, I could go higher I could
take, take the first thousand and I would
get the first thousand elements and so on.
Now, one problem where we can put these
techniques to good use is in the
calculation of prime numbers.
There's actually a very ancient algorithm
called the Sieve of Eratosthenes to
calculate these numbers.
The idea is as follows, we start with all
integers starting from two. So, three,
four, five, six,
And so on.
We take the first number, that's a two and
that's a prime number.
We will then eliminate all multiples of
two so that will be the six, the eight,
the ten.
The first number left in the resulting
output stream is three, and that's a prime
number.
We then eliminate all multiples of three,
so the six, is already eliminated, twelve
is already eliminated, fifteen.
The first number that's left in the stream
is five, and that's a prime number.
We eliminate all multiples of five, and so
on.
So, each step, we take the first element
of the remaining stream of numbers.
That one is a prime number.
We eliminate all its multiples and we
repeat.
So, here's a function that implements this
principle to the letter.
To sieve a given stream of numbers S, what
we do is we take the first number in the
stream,
So that would be our presumed prime
number.
And we follow it with all numbers that are
not multiples of the first number.
So, we take the rest of the stream, and we
filter it with the predicate that we say,
well, the number [unknown] the S, the
first number.
The s.head, must be different from zero.
So, once we have the sieving method,
obtaining all prime numbers is really
easy.
We simply say the prime numbers is sieve
of all the integers from two.
Let's try it out.
Primes takes, let's take the first prime
numbers and convert it to a list.
And there you go.
The first prime numbers here on the right.
So, let's get back to square roots one
more time.
The previous algorithms we've seen for the
square root algorithm always mixed
determination criterion is good enough
with the method to calculate new
approximations.
With streams at our disposal, we can now
express the concept of a converging
sequence without having to worry about
determination criteria.
So, we could write a stream that
represents all the successive
approximations of, of a square root of a
given number.
The thing we would do is we would have the
usual improved method.
And then, we would say, well, we have a
lazy val guesses which is a stream of
double, and the guesses start with one.
And each successive value is obtained by
mapping the improved function over
guesses.
So, this might look highly alarming to
you, a little bit like a snake eating it's
tail, because what happens here is that
you apply a map operation on the value
that you're about to define.
So, won't this blow up in an infinite
recursion?
Well, again, no.
Because we have the operation stream cons
here, which is lazy in its right operand
So, everything actually works out as it
should.
You can convince yourself by going to the
worksheet.
I have given you precisely the same stream
method.
So, let's try to apply this to a number.
Let's say four.
Take the first ten elements and print it
out.
So, what we would get is a perfectly good
stream of approximations to the number
four,
Which after a couple of iterations,
converges to 2.0.
So now, we have decoupled the idea of a
converging sequence from determination
criterion.
Of course, we can add determination
criterion later.
We see that here.
So, we have to find the is good enough
function as before, and we can then
subject our square root stream to a filter
method of all the elements that are good
enough approximations.
So, let's do that in the worksheet.
I've added a good enough method and then,
let me just filter that.
Filter is good enough with respect to my
number four.
And again, I want to show, again, I want
to show the first ten elements.
So, what you see now is you get a stream
of solutions that are all already good
enough approximations to the actual square
root value, so you could just take the
first one of that stream, and return that
as the result of your computation.
So, here's a quiz for you.
Consider the following two equivalent ways
to define an infinite stream of multiples
of a given number N.
You could write, from one map times n, as
we've seen,
But you could also write from one filter
modular N equals zero.
Both expressions would give you the stream
of multiples of N.
But which of the two expressions generates
its results faster?
Would it be that expression here or the
filter down there?
So, let's see how these two expressions
would behave.
Let's take, for the sake of the example, N
equals three.
So, the first expression would produce,
first, all the elements of the natural
numbers starting from one, and immediately
multiply each of these by three.
So, it would yield, in that order, three,
six, nine, twelve, and so on.
The second expression would produce all
natural numbers as before.
And then, it would filter these numbers to
keep only those that are divisible by
three.
So, it would keep the filter operations
that would now keep every third number in
the stream.
So, by that argument, the map operation is
more efficient because it doesn't generate
unnecessary stream elements that are
filtered out afterwards.
So, my vote goes to answer one.