This concludes the course.
Thank you for making it through to the
end.
I hope you had fun following it.
There's, of course, much more to be said
and to be learned.
I will leave you with a quick overview of
what we covered.
I'll point out some topics that might be
interesting for a future course.
And, I will also give you some links to
get further material, and to stay in
touch.
So, over the last seven weeks we have
explored the traits of functional
programming and then brought it in the
Scala language.
The most important ones of these include
the use of high-order functions
everywhere, the use pattern matching and
case classes,
The absence of mutability,
So no mutable state,
And immutable collections is the workhorse
of most algorithms,
And finally, the flexible play with
evaluation strategies.
You've seen strict, lazy and by name
evaluation, including a method to reason
about evaluations using the substitution
model.
I hope you've experienced that as a
coherent set of notations and methods,
that's a useful toolkit for you and your
daily programming practice.
And that's also a different way of
thinking about programs.
But if you want to find some more material
on Scala, there's a wealth of stuff out
there.
There's actually, we've a Scala Ref Card
or a cheatsheet that's been produced by a
student in this course.
Thank you [inaudible].
So,
We are going to put that up on the site.
Here's his initial version that appeared
in a discussion thread.
And it gives a very useful summary of, the
course contents.
For a slightly different outlook, you
could also go to Twitter and their Scala
School.
So they use that to teach Scala to
essentially all the new programmers who
have to use Scala,
Twitter.
It's a fairly concise, but also
comprehensive tour through most of the
core concepts of Scala.
And also, a lot of practical matters like
how to build it, how to test it, how to
interoperate with Java, how to use
Twitter's core concurrency libraries that
are written in Scala and so on.
If you prefer a book, then I believe the
standard reference book for Scala is the
book I cowrote, Programming in Scala." It
appeared at Artima.
There's a link to the free first edition
from the resources page of this course and
there's also a discount coupon for the
second edition.
Or if you want something shorter there's
the Scala tour in the Scala documentation
that gives you a quick overview of all the
core concepts of Scala.
If you want to stay current in Scala, then
one good idea is to just join a meetup.
There are 85 groups of Scala users out in
the world.
The largest ones has over a 1,000 users,
that's a New York group and it might to
fun to spend some evening with other Scala
enthusiasts, and to exchange ideas and
tricks.
Another thing you could do is go to the
typesafe.com site, and follow the blog
there, which contains a lot of cutting
edge material on, Scala and also the
middleware built on it, which is akka and
play! or you could also subscribe to the
newsletter and get news, by e-mail.
Finally, another interesting blog is the
one put together by Cake Solutions, which
gives you a weekly update of everything
that's new in the land of Scala.
So, it was quite a tour what we did over
the last seven weeks and I believe that
you have learned a lot about functional
programming,
But there's also a lot that still remains
to be covered.
I see several topics that I would really
love to cover in another course that
didn't have space in this one.
The first one would be functional
programming and state.
So, so far, we've explored functional
programming in its pure form.
There wasn't a single assignable variable
anywhere.
In actual programs out there and most of
them, there would be some state portions.
So the question poses itself, what does it
mean to mix functions in mutable state?
And what changes if we add mutable state
to functional programming?
Does anything break?
Do we have to be careful with some things?
What exactly is it that would change and
what that would be different?
The next topic that's also fascinating is
parallel execution.
I've argued in the introduction of this
course that functional programming is
relevant, because it makes parallel
execution easy.
We didn't have the time to go into that.
We didn't write parallel functional
programs.
That's something reserved for another
course.
And funnily there's the topic of domain
specific languages.
You've already seen that Scala let's you
write very high-level libraries that
really model the user's domain from the
user's stand point rather than exposing
many implementation details.
If you push that further, you would arrive
at, through domain-specific languages that
could be expressed as libraries in Scala
as a host language.
Another angle on the problem is to write
your domain-specific language not as an
embedded library, but as a standalone
language.
And then, you would be interested to read
and evaluate programs written in that
language.
The programming class I teach at EPFL
covers these three topics in a separate
seven week module.
If there's enough interest, I hope to be
able to present these topics in another
online class at some point in the future.