We have now put the lot of the material
developed in this course to work in a
concrete case study.
The task is to find a pure functional
solution to run on problem the so-called
water pouring problem.
Another variant of the problem is found in
the course by Peter Norvig, called Designs
of Computer Programs and Udacity where
Peter develops a very nice solution in
Python.
The solution developed in our course
differs from his in some respects, first,
it's purely functional, and second, it's
also more general.
You might find it instructive to compare
the two solutions, if only to see that
there's different ways to skin a cat.
The final program we are going to develop
in this course is the solution to a
well-known problem called the
water-pouring problem.
The idea is as follows, let's say you are
given a faucet and a sink,
And a number of glasses.
Right now, I will just draw two of them,
of different sizes.
So, just for the sake of the example,
let's assume this glass has size four
deciliters, and this glass has size nine
deciliters.
What you need to do is put use of a given
quantity, let's say, for the sake of the
argument, six deciliters of liquid in one
of the glasses,
It doesn't matter which one.
However, you're not giving any marking on
the glasses.
So, the only knowledge you have is the
total capacity of the glasses.
And the moves that are available to you
is, you can either fill a glass completely
using the faucet or you can empty it in
the sink or you can pour from one glass to
the other, until either the glass from
which you pour is empty, or the glass into
which you pour is full.
Now, the classical water pouring problem
uses two glasses of the given sizes and
the given target size of six deciliters.
But we are going to generalize that a
little bit.
We want to have an arbitrary number of
glasses of arbitrary given capacities, and
an arbitrary target capacity in one of the
glasses.
So, let's see how we would model this
problem.
First, how do we represent the state of
the glasses?
Well, the idea would be to represent a
glass as an int ranging from zero to the
number of glasses minus one and then our
state would be a vector of int that would
give us, for each glass, the number of
decilitres that are in that glass.
And then the question is what kind of
moves do we have?
Well, we have three, we can empty a glass,
you can fill a glass, or you can pour from
a glass to another glass.
So, let's see if we have, let's say, the
two glasses of size four and nine, and we
start in a state where both glasses are
empty so that would be state zero and zero
how that would evolve? So, one thing we
can could do is we could fill glass number
zero.
And that will bring us into the state four
and zero.
Or we could fill glass number one.
And that would bring us into the state,
zero and nine.
From there on, we could pour, starting
from this state here, from glass zero into
glass one, that could, would give us the
state zero, four, the action with be pour
zero to one.
Or, we could for instance, pour one to
zero here.
Then, we would end in a state where the
first glass has capacity four its full.
And the second glass, has five ounces in
it because that's what remains.
Sometimes, moves lead back to state that
we've visited before.
For instance, if we empty the glass one in
this state here,
Then we would be left with a state four,
Zero, which we can also reach shorter by
just a single move here.
Now, you've seen how moves span out.
Question is, how do we find now the right
solution?
How do we generate moves so that we find
the right sequence of moves to lead us to
our target capacity, let's say, that's six
here?
So now, that we know what moves are, let's
see how we can use them to find the
solution to our problem.
The idea would be that we generate all
possible move sequences, call them paths,
Until we hit on one that contains one of
the glasses with the right target amount
of liquid in it.
So, we would then start from an initial
state of all glasses empty.
And then, generate all possible moves to
new glasses.
Once we have generated all possible moves
of length one, we will generate then all
possible moves of length two and so on,
Like an onion,
Until possibly we hit on a path where we
would have one of the glasses with the
target amount of liquid in it, in this
case, six.
The idea then, is that we generate these
path sets from inside out, starting with
the shortest ones and progressively
lengthening the paths until we hit one
which is the right one, or, that's another
possibility, until we have exhausted our
search space and there is no solution.
So now that we have an idea for a
solution, let's see how we can put it in
code using the Scala Eclipse IDE.
What I going to do is I will, I am going
to create a glass.
I'll call it pouring to contain the
elements of the problem.
So, pouring should take as a parameter, a
vector of all the glasses and their
capacity.
So, that would be a vector a vector of
int.
One entry per glass, and for each entry,
its capacity.
The first thing I'm going to do is, I'm
going to work on states.
So what is a state?
Well, a state is a vector of integers.
One thing we could do to make that clear
is make a type alias, saying, state equals
vector of int.
The next thing to do is, well, let's
define what the initial state is.
So, the initial state would consist of all
empty glasses.
So, what we're after is a vector of the
length of capacity consisting of all
zeroes.
There are several ways to do that.
Probably, the most elegant way would be to
use a map.
So, what should I apply in the map while
it's a function that takes a glass, an
integer, and returns zero for any integer
it gets.
Good. So now, we have the initial stat,
how can we move from that state?
Let's define what are our moves are.
The idea there is that I would have a
glass for each move.
Let's make it a case glass for
convenience.
And they all would inherit from a common
base trait move.
So, I would have trait move here.
And I would then define three case
glasses, empty.
Fill and pour that all extend move.
So now, that we know what types of moves
are available to us, we still need to
generate all possible moves, so all
possible moves would be empty, an
arbitrary glass.
Fill an arbitrary glass or pour from an
arbitrary glass into another.
So, let's generate those.
As a, as an eight here, I have defined one
auxiliary state of structure, all glasses
that will be arranged, that goes from one
until capacity length..
So, what would the possible moves are?
Well, one way to do that would be to
define it as for-expressions.
Let me do that.
So, let's say for g taken from glasses,
Yield empty g.
So, those are the first moves available to
me, empty and arbitrary glass.
Other moves are for g taken from glasses,
fill g.
And finally, for from, taken from glasses
to,
Taken from glasses if.
From is different from to.
We can't pour from one glass into the
same.
Then yield, pour from and to Okay.
So, let's set up a test to see what we
have so far.
I'm going to create a new worksheet.
Call it test.
And what I am going to do is, I will set
up an instance of my glass.
We have to define a vector of initial
capacity of glasses.
Let's say, the first glass has capacity
four and the second has capacity seven.
And now, what I want to do is I want to
say, well, what moves are available to me?
And what we see here is I get a vector to
say empty zero, empty one, fill zero, fill
one, pour zero, one pour one, zero.
So, those are all the moves that I have.
But, of course, I could also generate
another glass.
Let's put another glass nine in here.
And then I would have more moves that you
can see over here.
So, three empties, three fills, and six
pours.
Back to our glass.
The next thing to consider is how moves
change states.
There are a number of ways we could record
that.
What I'm going to do here is I'm going to
write a method change in the move trait
that will have to be implemented by each
case glass.
So, change is defined on a move and it
takes a state.
And it gives us a new state.
So, that would track how each move changes
the state.
Let's implement this method for each of
our case glasses.
So, for the empty case glass, how is the
state changed?
Well, we thought the new state would be
the old state.
With the updated methods, so that, there's
a change at one point in the state.
At what point is it?
Well, at my glass, which now will be
empty.
So, it's the old state updated at the
point of the glass where it's now empty.
But remember, that updated doesn't destroy
the state, the old state will still be
available, it's just that, a new state
object that gets generated by this updated
method.
Updated is a purely functional method
here.
Good.
So, let's see for fill.
Here, our change would be that the glass
is updated not to be zero, but to be full
to its capacity.
So, glass gets updated to capacity of
glass.
And finally, for pour,
There, the problem is a bit more
complicated, because it depends whether
one glass can fully fit into another or
not.
So, what I want to do is, I want to first
define the amount that gets poured from
one glass to the other.
So, what would that be?
Well,
It could be that we take everything that
is in the from glass in the given state,
provided that there's enough room in the
to glass.
Or if there's not, then it could also be
that we fill the to glass to its capacity.
So, it would be state of capacity of to
minus state of to.
So, the amount is the smaller of the
current filling grade of the glass we pour
from and the free space in the glass in
which, into which we pour.
Now, that we know the amount to pour, the
state can be updated straightforwardly.
So, it's the old state updated at the from
glass, where the new value of the from
glass is the previous value minus amount.
And the new value of the to glass is the
previous value of the to glass plus the
amount.
So now, that we've seen moves and the
changes they do to states, it's time to
look at paths.
So, paths would be sequences of moves.
I'm also going to define a class for
paths, so I define a path by its history,
which is a list of moves.
And the idea would be that the history is
taken in reverse that makes it easier to
extend the path with the new moves.
So, that means that the last move in the
path comes first in that history list.
So, what I use for operations on our path?
Well, one operation I would be interested
in is, what state does it lead to?
So, let's define that end state.
And will, that would be a state.
How do I define that?
Well, one way to do it would be by a
pattern match over the history list, and
that would be a recursive function.
So, let's try that.
So, let's call this, track state of
history.
And we would have a auxiliary function,
Which would be defined by a pattern match
over an argument list.
If the argument list is Nil, then we
return the initial state.
If it consists of a move and some
remainder excess one,
Then what we would do is we would track
the state of the rest, remaining list.
Remember, the last move comes first in the
list.
And then, we would apply the first move to
change the result of that.
So, that's simply move, change the result
of track state.
Because track state returns the state, and
move is a change method that changes the
state to give the new state.
So, that computation of end state works,
but let's look at it closer for a moment.
Let's look at it graphically.
So, what we have here is we have
essentially done a set of changes with
moves, where each cursive call is a
previous version of the history, until
initially when the list is Nil, we return
initial state.
So, what does that remind you of?
Well, it's a foldRight.
So, it's a foldRight where we go through
the list, and we combine it each time with
the change operator.
But we can reformulate it as follows.
We take the history, we do a foldRight.
We state the initial state at the lower
right as initial state.
And our operation is,
The one way we take each move from the
history and we change each state on the
right.
And that will do exactly the same thing.
Now, the new formulation is, without a
doubt, much shorter and some would argue
more elegant, than the recursive pattern
matching solution.
But for most people and particular
beginners, it's also much harder to come
up with and maybe to read.
So, if you or your team would decide at
some point that you prefer the recursive
explicit pattern matching solution, that's
perfectly okay.
So, what we can do now is we can delete
our previous auxiliary method track state.
We have now condensed it into the
foldRight and obtain a solution that's
much shorter for pass.
So, what else do we need to do on a path?
Well, one useful operation is no doubt to
extend it with another move.
And that would just be a new path where
the move precedes the history that we have
so far.
And finally, it's always good to be able
to print objects in an intelligible manner
so let's define a two-string function.
So, to print the path, we want to print
its history.
But you probably want to reverse it first,
so first moves first and later moves,
later.
And we want to print it, let's say, with a
space between different moves.
And finally, it's also good to know where
the path leads to, so we are, interested
in its end state, so let me write it this
way.
.
So, that was paths.
Well, that's defining the initial path.
The initial path then would be the path
that contains the empty history.
Now, we have all the elements that we need
for our solution.
Let's take a quick look at the diagram.
So, you see here that we would have a
method that extends a set of paths with
new moves, successively of longer and
longer lengths.
So, the way we will put that in code is
that we have a function very similar to
the from, from integers.
Only now, we don't start from an integer
and say, generate all successive integers,
We from a set of paths.
And we generate a stream of set of paths,
so that means you generate longer and
longer set of sets of paths in a string.
So, one thing to take care of is the
boundary condition what if path is empty.
In that case, there is nothing to evolve
so we should return the empty string.
If paths is not empty, what do we do?
Well,
The idea is we need to generate all the
possible new paths that, I have the paths
in the set as a prefix.
And from then on further more, evolve the
stream.
So, let's do the first thing first.
So, let's call the new paths, more.
So more gets generated by a
for-expression.
We let path iterate over all the paths in
our set.
And then for each of them, we generate a
next path by extending the current path.
And extending the current path, we do with
all possible moves.
So, the way we do that is that we have the
call moves map path.extend.
For each of the possible moves, we apply
the operation extent with that move to the
path and that gives us a new path.
And all those mixed paths would yield my
more set.
Now, that I have my next generation set
more, I can use that to define the full
stream that starts with the given path
set.
And that is followed by the evolution of
my next generation more.
So, I, it would start with paths, then
more.
Because that would be the paths for the
next iteration from more.
Then more of more.
So, twice paths of, of lengths two added
to paths, and so on.
So, that's my path-generating function
from, I can use that to now define the set
of all possible paths.
So, let me call that pathSets.
And that would be from applied to the set
that consists only of the initial path.
So, what that set gives us is, in the
first set, it gives me set of initial
path.
In the second element, it gives me the set
of all paths of length one that start with
initial path.
Then, all paths of length two and so on,
until infinity.
So now, that we've that much, we can have
a quick look in the worksheet to see what
we get.
So, let's take a problem, and take all the
path sets.
Maybe reduce the size of the problem like
this. So, we would get a stream,
Which is the vector of 0,0.
And then, because it's a stream, it
doesn't evolve any further.
So, let's do the usual trick, and say,
let's take three elements and convert to a
list, and see what we get.
And we get an impressively long list of
possible moves that are all the moves that
we generate here in the int states.
So now, that we have all possible paths,
let's see how we would find the solutions.
So, let's define a function solution.
It takes a target, which is the volume
that we want to see in one of the glasses,
an int, and it should give us back a
stream of paths that have the target
volume in the end states.
So, how would we go about defining that
function?
Well, the idea is to go through all the
pathSets and from each of the pathSets,
pick the paths that are solutions, that
have the target volume in their end state,
and finally, to concatinate them all in
another stream.
So, the result stream would then consist
of all solution paths ordered by their
length.
So, let's do that.
So, it would be a for-expression where we
first go through the pathSets which are
taken from the pathSets value here.
And then, for each pathSets, we go through
all of the paths in that set.
And then, we want to demand that the path
is a solution.
So, what would that be?
Well, it would be that the end state of
the path contains the target volume.
Then, the path is a solution and, in that
case, we return it in the resulting
string.
Now, that we have the solution sets, let's
put it to a test in our worksheet.
Let me define problem that solutions of,
of let's say, six.
And I get the solution, let's see what it
is.
So here, we would have a sequence of moves
that yields to the vector 4,6.
That's fine.
Let's try something else.
Let's maybe try the original problem with
nine.
Then, we see it, unfortunately, it takes
already a long time.
That's not so good so it seems we have
found a solution but not a very efficient
one.
So, let's go back and see what the problem
could be.
So, one problem is if we look at the
diagram, that we move blindly.
That means we generate from each possible
state,
Let's say, we have a state here,
We generate new states, but we will also
generate a lot of old states.
So, we do a sort of random walk on the
states, constantly revisiting also old
states.
And these old btates don't really bring
anything to the solution Because when we
go back to an old state, that's not a path
we want to consider because we, by
definition, there is a shorter path that
leads to the same state.
So, the problem we have is that all this
exploration is rather aimless.
And a better way to do it would be to
exclude an state that we have visited
before.
So, let's try to do that.
So, the idea would be that, in my stream
generating function, I would have a second
set, now a set of states that represent
the explored states.
And I will now restrict my moves to those
that don't lead to a state that's already
explored.
So, what I would write here is, let's say,
explored is not allowed to contain the end
state of next.
Now, it, I still have to fix up some bits
that now yield type errors.
So, the first thing is in the recursive
call to from, I have to pass a new
explored set, so that would be the old
one.
And also for each of our moves, our path,
and also, for each of the paths in more,
its end states.
So,
That would be more map end state.
Finally, for the initial call to from, I
would have the set of states that's
initially explored is just the initial
state.
Okay, so with that solution, we can try
again.
And now, we have a solution to this
problem, which is slightly longer than the
one we've seen before, also, in very
little time.
We can also try something else.
We can add more glasses, such as, let's
say, nineteen.
And we want to find seventeen.
We can try that.
And again, we would get solutions fairly
quickly.
Let's look at the problem again.
We have a workable solution.
It's reasonably efficient.
Can we make it more efficient?
Is there, is there room for optimization?
Well, one area where we could optimize is
the endState method.
So, endState gets called a lot, you see,
in the, in the exploration of possible
solutions.
And each endState is a foldRight over a
complete history.
So, a recursive function over the history
as paths get longer, and state becomes
more and more complicated to compute.
There again, you could say, well, why
recompute the end state of a path?
Can't we just restore the end state once
and for all in the path and that would
avoid the recomputation? So, let's try
that.
So,
What I'm going to do is I'm going to put
the endState in the path.
That means, I can remove it here.
And because it should be available from
the outside, I make it a L parameter, so
now I can see it.
And now, I have to compute a new endState
when I compute a new path.
So, what would be the endState be of the
path that consists of the given move last,
and the history before that.
Well, it would be the change effect on the
move, on the previous endState.
So, that's the new one, where if you add a
move to a path, then we add the new
endState that consists of the change
effect of the move on that endState.
And the initial path then would be,
The endState is the initial state.
And if we do that and tested again, we
find the same solutions.
And maybe, it's a tad quicker.
It definitely will become more apparent as
paths would get longer.
So, that completes the solution.
So, what we did is, we modeled the problem
in a glass pouring.
We first modeled states, and we modeled
moves and the changes they have on states.
And we generated all the moves in this
variable here.
Then, we modeled paths as their own class.
And finally, we modeled the state
exploration function from as a
for-expression.
And the function that picked out all
solutions from the generated paths as
another for-expression.
So, this was quite a complex program. In
particular, there is a lot of choice of
representations.
So, we picked specific glasses for moves
and paths but we could also have taken
some encoding.
We picked object-oriented methods.
We could also have done some naked data
structures with functions.
Present elaboration is just one solution
not necessarily the shortest ones but I
believe it's actually quite clear from a
domain modeling standpoint.
Now, you might ask what are good guiding
principles for a program like that?
In the end, it comes down to experience.
As the saying goes, you can learn
programming in ten days, and then you
improve for ten years.
But there are a couple of guidelines
anyway, that are useful.
So, I believe the first guideline is, name
everything you can.
Function programming is great because it
allows you to break up things in really
small pieces,
Expressions that consist of maybe just
three words.
Make use of that.
Some of the assignments I've seen have
crammed dozen or more operators on a
single line.
Taking advantage of the conciseness of
functional programming in Scala.
But I don't actually think that's good
style.
So, break things up in little pieces,
Give a name for each piece, that makes
programs much more intelligible and
readable.
So, for instance, we put the change method
inside the move classes, because a move
changes things.
So, it makes sense to define change right
where you have the move.
And finally, when you do a design, keep in
mind that you always want to keep degrees
of freedom for future refinements.
So, think of what might change in the
future and how you could encapsulate this,
the implementations from clients so that
you could change it in the future without
changing any of the client code.