In this session, we cover lazy evaluation.
Roughly, laziness means do things as late
as possible, and never do them twice.
We will apply laziness to streams, and
trace how it helps evaluation in a
concrete stream query.
The implementation of streams that you've
seen in the last session solves the
problem of avoiding unnecessary
computations when the tail value of the
stream is not needed, but it suffers from
another very serious potential performance
problem.
And that is that if tail is called several
times the corresponding stream will be
recomputed each time tail is called. And
of course that could by itself cause up to
exponential blow up in program complexity.
Fortunately this problem can be avoided by
storing the result of the first evaluation
of tail and reusing the stored result
instead of recomputing it the second and
third times and all other times around.
We can convince our self, that this
optimization is sound, since the pure
function of language and expression,
produces the same result each time it is
evaluated.
So instead of re-evaluating the same
expression several times.
We could just squirrel away the first time
we have produced the result, and reuse
that result every time.
That scheme is called lazy evaluation, as
opposed to the call by name evaluation
that we've seen in the last session.
And also as opposed to the strict
evaluation for normal parameters and wild
definitions.
Lazy evaluation is a very powerful
principle because it avoids both
unnecessary and repeated computations.
In fact, it's so attractive that a
programming language, Haskell, has been
built on top of it.
So Haskell uses lazy evaluation by
default, everywhere.
You could argue, well, why does Scala not
do it?
Well, there's one, or maybe two problems
with lazy evaluation which are essentially
rooted in the fact that lazy evaluation is
quite unpredictable in when computations
happen.
And how much space they take.
You could argue, in a abstract, pure
functional language, it shouldn't really
matter when computations happen, and
that's true.
But once you add mutable side effects,
which Scala also permits, even though we
haven't used them in this course, you can
get into some very confusing situations.
So what Scala does is it uses strict
evaluation by default, like the absolute
majority of all programming languages, but
it still allows lazy evaluation of value
definitions with the lazy val syntax form.
So if you wrote lazy val x equals
expression, you would get a lazy
evaluation of the value x here.
So what that means is that just in a call
by name evaluation that you would get with
def x equals expression.
The expression here would not be evaluated
immediately at the point of the finish,
and it would be delayed, will be delayed
until somebody wants the first time the
value of x.
But afterwards the behavior between def x
and lazy val x diverge.
For def x of course you have the behavior
that every time you call x the expression
is reevaluated, whereas for lazy val the
expression is reused every time except for
the first one.
So let's test this understanding with an
exercise.
Consider the following program.
We have a function expr and it defines
three values X, Y and Z.
Each definition is preceded by a print
statement that prints that the definition
is now evaluated.
And then finally we have an expression
that makes use of X, Y and Z, so it does Z
plus Y, plus X plus Z, plus Y plus X.
If you run this program, what gets printed
as a side-effect of evaluating expr?
Here you have some choices.
Is it one of these four or maybe something
else?
So let's see how we would approach this
problem.
When we evaluate X, probably first have to
evaluate the three definitions.
We have a vowel definition here, the
right-hand side gets evaluated immediately
and would print an X.
The lazy vowel on the def would not be
evaluated at the point of definition, they
would be delayed.
Then we would get into the result
expression where we first demand the value
of Z, so that would print a Z.
Then we demand the value of y so that
would force the lazy valid would print the
y.
Then we would demand the value of x.
This one is already evaluated, so nothing
would be printed.
Then we demand the value of z again, so
that would give us another z of y again.
Well, now y is evaluated.
So we would just reuse the result we've
evaluated the first time around.
And finally the x is again evaluated.
So the string that gets printed is x z y
z.
Lazy vowels, we can adopt our
implementation of string.coms to make it
more efficient.
And the change is again very simple, the
only thing that changed is that instead of
a def tail equals tail, we use a lazy
vowel tail equals tail.
And that's all that's needed.
With the changed it means that as before,
we will evaluate tail only when it's first
demanded.
But unlike it was before, we will reuse
the evaluation of tail every.
Time after the first one so we will avoid
the unnecessary repeated computation.
So, all this avoiding of unnecessary
computations looks really great, but maybe
you're not yet convinced.
How can we really be sure that our,
execution will, in fact, avoid unnecessary
portions of computations?
Well, one way to be sure is to put it to a
test using the substitution model.
Using evaluation with our substitution
model.
Let's do that with the expression we
started with.
So stream range 1,000, 10,000, filter is
prime, apply one.
Let's start reducing that, and see what
happens.
So the first thing that happens here is
that we have to expand string range.
And here, I've given you the expanded
definitions with the actual parameters
replacing the former ones.
The next thing that happens is that the
if, then, else is evaluated.
So that would give me the cons expression
that we see here.
Let's abbreviate this expression with the
cons to C1, so what I would have is C1,
filter is prime, apply, one.
The next thing to do is, we need to expand
the filter function.
So, here you see it's definition, and then
the rest that needs to be done is apply
one on that.
I have to evaluate the IF then ELSE, so C1
is definitely not empty, because it's a
cons, so I would be left with this ELSE
part of the first IF here.
And I have to evaluate the head of the C1,
the string, that would give me 1,000,
because that's the first parameter past
two counts.
So I'm left with this expression here.
Now the next thing to do is evaluating is
prime.
I'll leave that out, because we've done
that already, but it's pretty clear that
is prime of 1,000 should return false.
So I replace the call by false.
I evaluate the F which gives me the, this
expression here.
And I've evaluated the tail of the C1
constant.
Now if you go back to the C1 constant what
it was.
It was a [inaudible] with the stream range
expression.
So when I evaluate the tail, that's what I
will get.
But what I'm left with is the expression
string range of 1,001, 10,000.
And then the same thing as filter is
prime.
Apply one.
In other words, the same expression I
started with, only instead of the 1,000, I
have the 1,001 here.
And that evaluation sequence continues
until I hit the first prime number, which
in this case would be 1,009.
So this expression would expand by a
sequence of reduction steps, to finally
stream range 1,009, 10,000, filter is
prime, apply one.
I evaluate stream range again.
Is the expression.
And I want to abbreviate that expression
to c2.
So I'm left with c2 filters prime apply
one.
I evaluate the filter function on c2, and
that gives me an, a sequence of
expressions.
Cons 1,009, and then this here, because
1,009 is a prime number, so it would be
included in the result of filter.
So the next thing to evaluate is the call
of the apply function on this cons
expression here.
I've plugged in here the definition of
apply, which I have given you below, it's
the usual definition where a body would
expect.
So we are left with an expression, like
this one here, which is an if then else to
ask whether one equals zero, which is
false.
So that would simplify to the second part
of the if then else, which you see here.
Now, what we need to do is we need to
evaluate tail.
That would in turn, force the express tail
part of these, this console.
So we would get C2 tail at filter is
prime, apply zero.
The next thing to calculate, again, is the
tail over here.
So that now would give us the next stream
range.
The.
Tail part of c2.
Again, filter is prime apply zero.
So what we see is we again, left with
essentially, the expression we started
with, only now we have.
1,010 here and we have zero here.
Where we started with 1,000 on the left
and one on the right.
So that process would continue until we
hit the second prime number, 1,013.
And now the computation is about to wrap
up.
So the stream range function would expand
as usual.
We make it a shorthand.
Call it C3, for this expression.
So we, we have C3 filter is prime, apply
zero.
We apply the filter function that would
say, well, 1013 is a prime number so let's
include it in the list.
Have the tile expression here.
Apply zero of that.
We apply, evaulate the apply function and
that would pull out the first element
1013.
And that's the result of the computation.
Poof.
That was quite tedious to follow that far,
but imagine how more tedious it would have
been if we had to evaluate actually all
the prime numbers between 1,000 and
10,000.
Here you could convince yourself that
indeed, we never look beyond 1,013, all
the other prime numbers remain
undiscovered and unevaluated in this