So the last two weeks have introduced you
to functions.
You've seen ways to extract and compose
functions using high order functions,
currying.
You've seen ways to write beautiful
programs with just functions.
But all these functions used for were
essentially other functions and primitive
data such as[INAUDIBLE] or Boolean.
What we're going to do in this week is
add a new dimension to programming and
that, ways to compose and extract data.
And the way we're going to that is by
introducing object and classes.
Okay, so in this section we learned how
functions can create and encapsulate data
structures.
As an example, let's consider rational
numbers.
We want to design a package for doing
rational arithmetic.
A quick reminder from high school
mathematics.
A rational number x over y is represented
by two integers, which are called the
numerator x and the denominator y.
Now, in a sense, we can already do that
with what we know from skala.
We could define two functions
addRationalNumerator and
addRationalDenominator.
And they et, each get all the bits of the
2 rational numbers as arguments.
So both functions would get the
numerators and denominator of the first
rational and the numerator and the
denominator.
Of the second one and then they would
implement the usual add workings for
rational arithmetic.
However, it would be difficult to manage
all these numerators and denominators.
It's a much better choice to combine the
numerator and denominator for rational
number in a data structure.
In Scala we do this by defining a class.
So here you see an example.
We write class, rational and then we have
two arguments call them x and y and then
the rational class would have two
methods.
Def's.
The one is called numer, and it's the
same as the x argument.
And the other is called denom, and it's
the same as the y argument.
So what that does, what that definition
introduces is two entities.
A new type, that we can use henceforth,
which is named Rational.
And also, a way to construct rationals to
create elements of this type.
Way to construct this encapsulated in a
constructor.
Scala keeps the names of types and values
in two different namespaces.
It always knows from the context whether
you mean the type or a value.
So there's no conflict between the two
definitions the constructor and the type
of a rational.
A type in a programming language is
essentially a set of values.
Now the values that belong to a class
type are called objects.
We create an object by taking the
constructor of the class and prefixing it
with the operator new.
So a new rational 1, 2 would create a new
element of the type rational where the
nominator is 1 and the t nominator is 2.
Let's try this out in a worksheet.
So I will make a new package for the week
three.
And I create a new websheet in the
package.
Call it rationals.
The one thing I am going to do after the
first object, which was as usual as my
scratch package to try things out, is
define my class of rationals.
So I say rational and I have the two ints
as we've seen on the site.
And that's it, so what we do here is we
create a new rational that's 1 and 2 and
what we see is we have created a new
value like 0 of type rational And the
value print, as rational at, and then
some number.
The number happens to be the hash code of
that rational number.
That's just the particularity of the JBM,
if you don't define how things should
print, that's the way they print.
Okay, so lets continue the rational
sample, and define the numerator to be x.
And the denominator to be 1.
And what we could do then is, we could
call this rational say x, we could take
the numerator of x, and what we see.
No big surprise, is one.
Whereas if we take the denominator we
would get two.
So you see that objects of class varation
will have now two members called numer
and denom and that the members are
selected just like in Java with an infix
dot between the object name and the
member name.
So the next step is to do some arithmetic
on rationals.
We want to define the usual arithmetic
functions, addition, subtraction,
multiplication, division, using the
standard rules that you see here.
Now, one thing we could do is we could
use the class rational as a pure data
type.
Just as something that gives us the data
and.
Define the operations as functions
outside so addRational would take two
rationals give you a rational, it would
create a new rational according to the
matic, matical formula that multiplies
numerators and denominators of the two
rationals in the way That you see here.
And to make things print nicely we could
also define a makeString function that
takes a Rational and produces the
numerator of the Rational and the
denominator of the Rational separated by
a slash.
So now we can write new Rational(1, 2)
and new Rational(2, 3), add the two with
addRational, put user string with
makeString, and we would get 7/6,
following the usual arithmetic loss.
But one can also go further and package
the arithmetic functions that operate on
a data abstraction in the data
abstraction itself.
So those functions that are put into
classes are called methods.
In our example we could imagine that
rational numbers now would have, in
addition to the methods numer and denom,
also the methods add, subtract, multiply,
divide, equal and toString.
Let's do this in the worksheet.
Let's design an addition function.
Add.
Add takes 1 rational as its argument and
it would then produce the numerator times
the argument's denominator.
Plus the arguments numerator times its
own denominator that's the humerator of
the new rational.
And it's denominator would be just the
two denominators multiplied.
One thing important here is that the
addition function here takes only a
single parameter not two.
Where is the other one.
While the left upper end of add is really
the rational number itself.
The rational number for which we define
the class.
So let's see how that would work in the
worksheet.
We would write let's write another
rational, maybe, 2 3rds.
And then, let's write x.add of y.
We still don't see very much because our
rational class doesn't have a good way to
print itself.
So let's change that, we do the change
that by adding a toString function to the
class.
A toString function will be called
whenever an element of the class should
be printed.
So what would toString be or one thing to
do it would be two sides numer plus the
slash plus denom, where the plus is
string concatination.
Okay, we see an arrow here.
What do we get it says there we override
a method.
And we need an override modifier.
I'll explain that later on, what that
means.
And now let's just do as the, clip
suggests, and we see that the rational,
all rational numbers now print nicely.
Okay, let's do an exercise.
In your worksheet, add a method neg to
class Rational that is used like this:
x.neg should evaluate to the negative of
the rational number x.
And the second step, now add a method
subtract or sub, to subtract 2 rational
numbers.
And the final question that you have to
answer, using your worksheet, is with the
numbers x, y, zet as given on the
previous slide, what is the result of x
minus y minus zet.
Okay, let's see how we would do that.
We take 1st the test case, let's take
those 3 definitions and paste them into
the work sheet, replacing the previous
one And get to work.
So the first thing we need to do is
define the function neg.
So neg should have a, a result type
Rational.
And what we would do is we return a new
rational with the numerator negated and
the denominator as it is before.
The next thing we have to do is to find a
function subtract with like add takes
another rational.
And returns another rational.
So what would we do there?
Well of course we could write, define it
with a formula not unlike the one for
add, the one for subtract directly
divised from that.
A more elegant way would be to say well
we add the parameter negated.
So what's the advantage of doing it this
way is that we do not repeat ourselves.
We do not have to write this rather
complicated formula twice, so that's
usually called the DRY principle, don't
repeat yourself, and it's a very good
li-, guideline for software development
whether it's functional or not.
So once we have that, let's add the test
case so that would be x subtract y
subtract that and we get the answer
negative 79 divided by 42.
So in this session you have seen classes
and objects as a fundamental way to
organize data.
In the next session we are going to learn
several new things about classes and
objects.
It actually pays to save the worksheet
that we have worked on for this session
because we will find good use for it in
the next session as well.