Over the last two weeks you've seen
several ways to express functions, to
compose them, to use them in your program.
In this session we are going to review the
language constructs that you have seen so
far in one syntax summary that you can use
as a reference.
In fact there's a standard way to describe
elements like that with grammar and one of
the most commonly used notations for such
a grammar is called extended backwards now
form.
So in that standard backwards now form a
vertical bar would denote an alternative.
Brackets would denote an optional element
zero or one occurrences of an element and
braces would denote a repartition zero or
more occurrences of an element.
Let's start with types.
We've seen two form of types, so we would
have a bar here.
A type in our language is a simple type or
a function type.
A simple type so far is just an
identifier, and the function type is
always contains an arrow.
And on the left hand side of this arrow
could be either a simple type, or a set of
types in parenthesis.
Another way to put it would be the
following.
A type can be either a numeric type.
So we've seen int and double.
But there's also bite, short, character,
long, and float.
That's the same as the primitive types in
Java.
Or it could be the boolean types that has
values true and false as we have seen.
Or it could be the string type.
Or it could be a function type such as int
to int or a pair of ints to ints.
Later, we're going to see more form of
types than these.
Let's look at expressions.
So here you see the complete syntax of
expressions.
I'm not going to go into detail but it's
there for you as reference.
Let's look instead at categories of
expressions and some examples.
So an expressions can be an identifier,
such as x or, IsGoodEnough, or it can be a
literal, such as zero or 1.0, or "abc".
Or it can be a function application, such
as square root of x.
Or an operator application, such as y + x.
Or a selection.
We've seen math.abs that selected the abs
method from the math module.
Or a conditional expression, such as if (x
< zero) - x else x.
Or it can be a block, like the one that
you see here in braces, or finally an
anonymous function such as x arrow x plus
one.
The last syntactic category are
definitions.
We have seen so far function definitions
and value definitions.
Function definitions start with a def,
followed by an identifier, followed by
zero or more parameter lists, followed by
an optional result type, followed by an
equal sign and finally an expression.
Value definitions are simpler, they
consists of val, then an ident, then an
optional type, then equals, then
expressions.
Parameters can be by name, or by value.
So a parameter is an identifier, then a
colon and then comes a type, but you can
prefix the type with the arrow, and you've
seen that means a call by name parameter.
So that's all the syntax that we've seen
so far, that we've needed so far in our
examples.
We will add more elements as we need them
over the coming weeks.
So those are all the language elements
that we have used so far.
You will notice that they're all related
to functions and that we have spoken very,
very little about data.
You had only some primitive data types
like doubles or ints or booleans.
This is going to change next week where we
are going to study new ways to indroduce
data that are centered around classes and