Over the first two weeks we have introduced a model of evaluation of programs
based on term rewriting. That was the so-called substitution model.
It's a fair question to ask whether when we have now these new concepts,
classes and methods and self-references, whether these concepts can be ported to our
evaluation model. Whether they can be extended to cover these as well.
In this session you're going to find out how this is done.
So far we've only developed this model for pure functions.
We have defined the meaning of a function application using a model based on substitutions.
And now we extend this model to classes and objects.
The first question we need to ask is how is an instantiation of a class
like new C with some argument expression evaluated.
The answer is surprisingly simple.
We will evaluate the expression arguments,
e 1 to e m.
Just like the arguments of a normal
function.
And that's it.
In fact the resulting expression new c of
some values, v one to v m is already a
value.
So we just take these new instance
creation expressions as values.
Next question.
Let's suppose we have a class definition,
like the one you see here.
Where we have a class C with a method F.
And the formal parameters of the class are
named X1 to XM.
And the method F has parameters Y1 to YM.
The function parameters or the class
parameters can both be empty.
And for simplicity we have omitted any
parameter types.
Now the central question is if we have an
expression like that.
We have a class instance new C of V1 to
VM, and we call them F at F, and pass it
further arguments values, W1 to WN.
How is that evaluated?
Let's see how we would answer these
questions.
So as a reminder we would have the class,
C, and that has the X parameters.
And then it has a function f.
And that would have the y parameters.
And a body B.
If you have an expression like this one
here, then it is re-written not using one
substitution as for plain functions, but
three substitutions.
The first substitution is the one you have
seen before.
We would have to replace the actual, the
formal parameters of the function f with
the actual argument values w1 to wn, so
that's that substitution that you see
here.
The next substitution affects the class.
So we have former parameters of the class,
this also have to be replaced by the
actual argument values that we have here
when we create the class.
So that it gives us the second
substitution.
The third substitution is important,
because the body of the function F here
could contain
reference to this, the current class
itself and of course that reference to
this outside of the class wouldn't have
any meaning.
So we have to replace it with something
else.
What do we replace it with?
Well, the idea is simply the receiver of
this call.
So the value new C v1 to vm
itself, so that's the object that
takes the method call and so that's the
object that replaces "this".
So you see, there's three substitutions at
play.
It's quite a bit more complicated than in
the purely functional model, but it's
still the same model so we can model
evaluation with exactly the same
mechanisms as before.
So let's demonstrate that with an example.
We're looking at the method called new
Rational 1, 2 dot numer.
As a reminder, I've put up the essential
parts of class rational here.
So let's see what happens for this method
call here.
I put up the formal definition.
We have three substitutions at play.
There's a substitution for the class
parameters where the actual values one,
two replace the x and the y.
For the method in this case, there's
nothing to replace because numer doesn't
have any parameters.
And finally, any occurrence of this would
have to be replaced by the object itself
so that we would be new Rational(1, 2).
In this case, it turns out that the right
hand side of numer is very simple, it's
just x.
So the only piece
of this substitution that applies is
the left most one here.
One for X and the result is one.
Let's do a more complicated example, let's
see whether new Rational of one two is less
than new Rational of two three.
How would we go about that?
So here you see the definition of less.
So we would have three substitutions again.
There's the substitution of one and two
for x and y, as before.
Then there's the substitution of the
argument here, a new rational of two,
three for the That parameter of Less.
And finally, there's a substitution that
replaces the "this" in less's body by the
receiver of the call, new Rational of (1, 2).
And all these three substitutions are
applied to the body of less that you see
here.
So here, it's written out in slightly
nicer fonts.
But that's the body that you see here.
Note that I have made explicit that this
is the argument for references
because we need that for the substitution
model to work correctly.
So what that means is that, if I apply the
substitutions, then the "this" gets
replaced by new Rational (1, 2).
So that's the two occurrences you
see here.
And the "that" gets replaced by new
Rational (2, 3).
That's the two occurrences that you see
here.
And if we then apply the further
substitutions for numer, and an analogous
substitution for denom, then we arrive at
this expression here, which reduces to
true, as usual.
So one more thing we want to cover this
session is operators.
You see, in principle the rational numbers
defined by our class are as natural as
integers, and mathematical abstractions
just as good as integers.
But for the user of these abstractions
there's currently a noticeable difference.
You write if x and y are integers, you
write x plus y.
But if R and S are rational numbers, you
need to write r.add(s).
So that's not very natural, and in fact,
in Scala we can eliminate this difference.
To do that, we proceed in two steps.
At the first step, we introduce
in fix notation for methods.
It turns out that any method with a
parameter can be used like an infix
operator in Scala.
So instead of having to write r.add(s),
you can write just as well, r add s.
R dot less s becomes r less s, and for
maximum it's the same thing.
So the two things mean exactly the same
things.
The left sides expand to the right sides.
You can do that for any operator that you
have in Scala.
The second step is about relaxing the form
of identifiers.
Normally in programing languages,
identifiers are alpha numeric, so they
start with a letter, then they are
followed by a sequence of letters or
numbers.
In Scala you have an alternative
form of identifiers where identifiers can be
symbolic.
They start with an operator symbol, such
as plus or minus, anything other than a
letter or a digit, and they're followed by
other operator symbols.
In this treatment, the underscore
character underscored that we use a
relaxed notion of identifiers in Scala.
Normally in programming languages, an
identifier is alpha numeric.
It starts with a letter and it's followed
by a sequence of letters and numbers.
In Scala, operators are also treated
as identifiers, and to achieve that we
have introduced a second form of
identifiers which we call symbolic.
Such an identifier starts with an operator
symbols such as plus, or minus or question
mark, and is be followed by other operator
symbols.
In the definition, the underscore
character, as usual, counts as a letter.
And there's a final twist, we can also mix
alphanumeric and symbolic.
We can start with an alphanumeric
identifier, followed by an underscore,
then followed by some operator symbols.
So here I give you some identifiers in
Scala.
x1, times, +?%&, that's not necessarily
an identifier I would recommend you use,
vector underscore ++ or counter underscore =.
And all these names are legal
identifiers in Scala.
So let's see how we could apply that to
class rational.
Let's start with the first operator, less
here.
So a better name for less would be just
the less than or equal sign.
Then we would change max accordingly.
To say if this less than that, and the
program here compiles again.
And the usage of course, it would be the
same thing.
I would write X less than Y.
For maximum, I think maximum is a nice
operator as it stands, but I can write it
infix.
Now that we've dealt with less and max.
What about add and sub?
So for add, we would, of course, find
plus.
For sub, we would, find minus.
And the definition of sub would be this
plus that dot neg.
And in the code here, I can now use the arithmetic operations
as I'm used from mathematics.
Now the final operations to look at would
be neg.
You've seen that we can replace all the
arithmetic operations on rational by the
natural mathematical symbols.
But there's still neg which sort of sticks
out because, instead of neg, we would want
to write prefix minus.
So how can we achieve that?
So if you look at the error message here,
it tells us, well, unary underscore minus is
not a member of rational.
So what that means is that, because the
prefix operator minus is really different
from the infix operator minus,
there's a special convention in Scala.
We have to call it unary minus.
And if we do that, then,
we see that, now everything works out, and
we also get prefix operators.
One thing to guard against is that if a method name
ends in an operator symbol, then you need
at least a space between that and the
final colon.
Because otherwise, a colon is actually a legal
symbol.
So the colon would just be merged
with the operator name, to form one long
operator minus colon.
So that would be here, an error, that you
see.
So, you've seen that we can now use the
usual mathematical expressions like, x
times x plus y times y.
But, there's one issue still, namely about
the precedence of the operators.
As you're used, the times here binds
stronger than the plus, so implicit
parenthesis go like this. But you might
ask, well how is that actually achieved if
all operators are user defined, how is the
precedence between those operators
established?
Well, there's actually one universal rule
in Scala, that the precedence of an
operator is determined by its first
character.
And here's a table of all the characters
and the precedence categories.
You will note that the table is very
similar to precedence in a language such
as Java or C, and that's no accident.
So, the first thing to do is to say, well
the lowest precedence is every operator
that starts with a letter.
So alphanumeric operators have lowest
precedence.
Then we take essentially the precedence
groups of C and Java.
So the next lowest is bar, followed by
caret, followed by ampersand, followed by
less than, greater than, equals, bang.
The colon is inserted the colon is not in
java so we inserted in here then plus
minus and finally times, slash and percent.
And every character which not in this list,
every symbol character which is not in
this list is assumed to have a higher
precedence than everything else.
You might say why these rules and not
others and I don't really have a good
answer for that.
The only answer is that it's important
that everybody uses the same precedence
rules because otherwise it's very hard to
read other people's code.
So that's why Scala has opted for a
single rule that determines the precedence
of each operator.
So as an exercise for this session, I
would like you to ask to provide a fully
parenthesized version of this string of
this expression here.
What I mean by that is that you should
put every binary operation into
parenthesis in a way that the structure of
the expression doesn't change.
So let's see how we would go about that.
In this string here, what's the operator with the highest precedence?
Well it turns out it's the ?^
because question mark was not in our list
yet it's a symbolic character.
So those are assumed to have the highest precedence.
So we are safe making a pair of
parentheses around this one first.
The next highest one then would be the plus that we see here.
So that gives us here a pair of parentheses.
Followed by the equals sign here.
So the arrow here would be in parentheses.
Of the remaining three, the next highest
one would be the caret.
Then the bar, and finally the lowest precedence
would be the less.
So that's the fully parenthesized version of
the string I'm after.
Now, this might be a fun exercise
but you see that, if you are actually
asked to read a string like that, then that's
maybe less funny.
Of course it's perfectly fine to define a
mathematical operator such as plus or bar.
For something where this operator makes
sense.
And in some domains it's also perfectly
fine to define new symbolic operators that
have a special fixed meaning in these
domains.
But please don't go overboard inventing
fancy operator names for all
the operations in your API.
It's usually not appreciated by the users
because they will have a hard time
understanding that and also will have a
hard time setting the parentheses as you
see here.