In this session we're going to apply much
more of what we've learned about high
order functions in one coherent example.
The task here is to find fixed points of
functions and the application of the task
will be to our well known square root
example.
So what is a fixed point?
A number x is called a fixed point of a
function f if f of x equals x.
Let's see that in a graphical example.
Let's suppose we have the function that
maps x to one plus x over two.
So the graph of that function would look
like this.
And that would be the diagonal.
And that would be one.
And the fixed point would be where the
diagonal hits the graph of the function.
That would be two.
Turns out that for some functions we can
locate the fixed points by starting with
an initial estimate and then applying f
repetetively.
So, we start with x, then we compute f of
x, then f of f of x, and so on.
And for these functions at some point the
value will not vary any more, or the
change will be sufficiently small, so that
we can declare that we have approximated
the fixed point.
So for functions that satisfy that
property, we could write the following
fixed point algorithm.
I will go into the worksheet and start it
directly.
So that algorithm is if you look at it
closely it's a closed derivative of what
we did for square root.
We have essentially an iteration method
that test whether our guess is close
enough to the, to the result and if it's
not then we iterate and beyond the improve
methods that we had in the square root
would now be this f method that we pass as
a parameter.
So let's try this method out.
For our function that maps x to one, one
plus x over two.
So let me write fixed point.
X to one plus x over two.
Initial value one.
And you would get something that's very
close to two, as expected.
So now that we know how to do fixed
points, can we somehow get new insight in
the, our square root function?
Previously we gave you Newton's method
essentially as fact.
That's the sequence that you have to use
for your iterations.
Can we somehow derive that sequence?
When in fact, yes.
So here's a specification of the square
root function.
What is square root of x?
Well, it would by a number y, such that y
squared equals x.
That's what it means to be a square root.
Now that we can, now we can do just simple
algebraic manipulation.
So, we divide both sides of this equation
by y, so we get square root of x is the
number y such that y equals x divided by
y.
But what that means is that square of the
x is the fixed point of the function y to
x over y because if you put y in and you
get x of a y and x of a y is the same as y
then that equation is satisfied.
So a solution of the equation is the same
as a fixed point of this function again.
Now, with that knowledge we can try to
revisit our implementational square root.
Make it simpler by just plugging it in
into our fixed point find a function.
So, that would give square root of x
double equals fixed point of this function
that maps y to x over y, and some initial
value, 1.0.
Let's try that out in the worksheet.
So we would have def square root of x
double, equals fixed point of y maps to x
over y and one as the initial value.
And let's try with our square root of two.
And we get, unfortunately, an infinite
computation, this doesn't converge.
Why not?
What happens?
Well, to find out more we can use print
run as a debugging help.
So let me just add a print run statement
at a good point.
So, I guess a good point is in the iterate
function, where we could say, for each
iteration step.
We want to write what the current guess
is.
So we write guess equals, and then current
guess here.
So if we do that, then we see that.
Our guess, oscillates between one and two
all the time.
And if you do the computations for square
root, I encourage you to do that and you
will find that yes indeed if you trace the
execution using the substitution model
then that's precisely what will happen.
So, how can we do better?
One way to control these oscillations that
we were seeing is to prevent the
estimation from varying to much and one
way to do this is by averaging successive
values of the original sequence.
So instead of going 1,2, 1,2 we take the
average of two successive values that
would give us 1.5 and that would set us on
the right path to convergence.
So let's try that.
So what we want to do is, instead of
saying x over y, we want to take the
average of the two values.
So that would be y plus x over y divided
by two.
And we get back to the square root
functions that we've seen in the first
week.
In fact, if we expand the fixed point
function fixed point and plug in the
definition of this average temping
function of, for, for square root, then
what we will find is that we get back a
very similar square root algorithm than
the one we've seen last week.
So it's no surprise that we get the same
results back.
So the previous examples have shown that
the expressive power of a language is
greatly increased if we can, can pass,
functions as arguments.
I'm going to show you next that it's also
very useful to have functions that return
other functions, and I'm going, going to
show you that with fixed point as the
example.
Let's go back to our observation that
square root of x is a fixed point of the
function that map y to x over y.
We have taken that observation, we have
seen that square root doesn't converge
that way, but we could make it converge by
averaging successive values.
This technique of stabilizing by averaging
is general enough to merit being
abstracted into its own function.
Let's see what this function would look
like.
It would have the function average down.
It takes an arbitrary function from double
to double.
It takes the value x of type double and it
then performs the, it computes the average
of x and f of x.
Let's do an exercise.
Given fixed point and average damp, can
you write a square root function that uses
both functions.
So, let's see how we would solve this
example.
I have given you the average damp function
that we developed on the slide.
What would square root be now?
So square root would be a fixed point of a
function that maps y to x over y with
initial value one.
But that was the one we did that didn't
converge.
So, what we do is we use average damp.
On that function here.
And if we run it, we can, we get the
expected square root result.
So what average stamp is, is it's a
function that takes a function, namely
this function that is at, at the root of
the square root specification, and it
returns another function, namely the
function that is essentially the same
iteration but with averaged stamping
applied.
So it's a function that takes a function
to another function.
If you look at this definition of square
root, then I think you would agree that
it's probably very difficult to write
something that is clearer and shorter than
this very definition.
It came from the specification of what it
means to be a square root.
We said we derive that the solving the
equations for square roots means taking
the fixed point of this function.
We determined that we needed to take
averages to dampen the oscillation, so we
use this average damp function in the
middle, and we are done.
So in summary, we saw last week that
functions are essential abstractions.
Because they allow us to introduce general
methods to perform computations, as
explicit and named arguments in our
programming language.
And this see, week we've seen that these
abstractions can be combined with high
auto functions to create new abstractions.
So, that's a very powerful way to compose
and abstract programs.
And as a programmer it's always good to
look for opportunities to extract entry
use.
It's not true that the highest level of
abstraction is always the best one.
Sometimes it's actually better to stay a
little bit more concrete.
But it's important to know the techniques
of abstraction so that you can use them
when they're appropriate.