In this session, we are going to cover an
important concept in functional
programming.
Higher order functions let you pass
functions as arguments and return them as
results.
One thing particular about functional
languages is that they treat functions as
first class values.
This means that.
Like any other value a function can be
passed as a parameter to another function
or returned as a result.
We'll see in this session that this
provides a flexible way to compose
programs.
Functions that take other functions as
parameters, or that return functions as
results are called higher order functions.
So, that's the opposite of first order
functions.
A first order function would be, then, a
function that acts on data types, simple
data types such as [inaudible] or longs or
lists, but not other functions.
Whereas, a higher order function acts on
other functions.
Let's see an example.
Let's suppose we want to take the sum of
all the integers between a and b.
So we could write something like this.
Sum iints, it takes the, the bounds as
parameters, the and the b.
And we ask well, if a is greater than b,
then there is nothing to sum.
And we would return zero as the, logical
value for that.
And otherwise we would return a + a
recursive call of sum ints of a+1 and b.
Good.
Now that we've done that, let's vary the
problem a little bit and consider taking
the sum of the cubes of all integers
between a and b.
So here's the cube function.
Take an x, return x times x times x.
Some cubes then would be the same as some
ints.
But, where we used an A before now we
return cube of A.
And otherwise, it's the same thing as some
ints.
Recursive call to sum cubes in this case.
Next, let's take the sum of all factorials
of the integers between a and b.
Well, you see the principle by now.
The program, again, is exactly like sum
ints and sum cubes, except that where
previously we computed the q, we compute
the factorial.
Of course, these are all special cases of
the mathematical sum of the values of f of
n, where f is the given function, and n is
taken from the interval between a and b.
The questions is, well if mathematics has
a special notation for that, shouldn't
programming have one as well.
Can we factor out the common pattern into
a single method.
So here's how that's done.
Let's define a function sum which takes a
parameter F of type INT to INT, and to two
bounds A and B, both INTs.
And let's generalize the previous, three
definitions as follows.
We write, if A greater than B, then zero,
otherwise, take F of A plus sum of F and A
plus one.
B.
So the new thing here is that F is a
parameter of the sum function.
It's not a given function.
It's a parameter.
Once we have that, we can then write our
function sum in sum cube, sum factorial as
follows.
Sum.
Ints would be simply sum of id of ab,
where the id function simply returns its
parameter unchanged.
Sum cubes would be sum of cube and AB,
where the cube function is as what we've
seen before.
And finally, sum factorial is sum of fact
and AB, where the fact function is, again,
the factorial function.
So what we've done, effectively, is reuse
the pattern that defines the sum function,
so that we had to write that only once.
And we could reuse it in the three
definitions of the particular sums.
One thing that's new here is a function
type.
Function type is written A aero B, where A
and B are types.
And its a type of a function that takes
some argument of type A, and returns a
result of type B.
So for example Int aero Int, is a type of
functions that map integers to integers.
Looking at the previous example again, we
have successfully shortened the definition
of some ins, some cube, some factorials.
But there's an annoying detail.
You have to name all the little auxiliary
functions that we do here.
So, we've gained some eh, programme called
here but we've spent more in the
definition of all these auxiliary
functions.
So we've seen that passing functions as
parameters can lead to the creation of
many small functions, and sometimes that's
tedious.
Compare the situation to other types such
as strings.
We could write something like Def STR
equals ABC and then print an STR, But we
don't have to.
We can just as well write print on ABC
directly and that's because strings exist
as literals.
Since functions are important in our
language, it makes sense to think of
introducing literals for functions as
well, and that's what we do next.
These literals are called anonymous
functions, because they do not have a
name.
So here is how we write anonymous
functions.
There is an example let's consider the
function that raises this argument to a
cube that would be written as you see
here, sorry, takes a parameter X of type
int, and then there comes an arrow and then
comes the value of the function In this
case, case X times X times X.
So X colon INT is the parameter of the
function, and on the right hand side of
the arrow is the body.
In fact, the type of the parameter can be
omitted if the compiler can infer it from
the context.
And if you have several parameters, you
can write them in a list separated by
commas.
So, for instance, that function here.
What would that be?
Well yes the summation functions so it
would take two integers X and Y, and give
you the sum of X and Y.
You could ask, are anonymous function
essential for Scalar?
Just as, let's say, conditionals or value
definitions are essential.
Or can they be defined in some other way?
It actually, it turns out that every
anonymous function can be expressed in
some other way, using a def.
So let's say you have an anonymous
function with n parameters x1 to xn and a
body e.
You can always write this as the function
def f.
Then come the parameters, then comes the
body, and then you follow that by a
reference to this function that you have
just defined.
Sometimes you might have to write the
expression in a block, so that it, it
doesn't, the name doesn't get confused
with something else.
Because we can always rewrite anonymous
functions, we can therefore say that they
are syntactic sugar.
They make writing functions sometimes
easier, but they're not essential in the
sense that they do not add anything to the
fundamentally expressive power of the
language.
So to come back to the sum INTs and sum
cubes example, using anonymous functions,
we can write these now in a shorter way.
Sum INTs would be just the function sum,
where the function we pass is the identity
function, written X arrow X, and to
balance our, the parameters, and sum cubes
would have as the function parameter X
arrow X times X times X.
And if we do that, then we do not need
anymore the auxiliary definitions of
identity or cube.
Let's do an exercise.
The sum function uses linear recursion,
can you write a tail recursive function
instead?
Note that, unlike factorial, some really
could profit from this tail
recursion optimization.
Because of the interval between A and B is
large, you might get a lot of different
recursive steps so you might risk a stack
overflow.
So let's rectify that, and design a
tail recursive function instead.
I've already given you a template for this
function.
It uses a nested function loop.
And all you have to do is replace the
triple question marks here and here.
So let's see how we would go about that.
The first one here is we, in the loop
function we have a test that says well if
something is true then probably that would
be the termination.
So when do we terminate.
Well we terminate if the lower bound A is
greater then the upper bound B.
And what do we return in that case?
Well, since we have used the accumulator
trick, we would return the accumulator.
Once we have that, we can look at the
initial call, so as the first parameter,
we would pass the initial lower bound A.
And as the initial accumulator would have
to be what.
Well, we know accumulator is the result
that we return, and the interval is
initially empty,
so that would have to be zero.
And finally, in the recursive call, we
would assume that the initial bound gets
incremented by one.
And the new accumulator is F applied to A
plus the previous accumulator.
You can test this function.
Let's apply this function to lower bound
three, upper bound five.
And you would get 50, as expected.
You have seen higher order functions as
essential building blocks of functional
programs.
In the next session we are going to play a
little bit more with higher order functions
and introduce new ways to express them.