In the last session, we have explored a
formal model of evaluation of expressions
which was called the substitution model.
And we have seen that there's more than
one way to evaluate an expression.
We have identified the call by name and
call by value evaluation strategies.
And in this session, we're going to
compare them a little bit further in
particular in what regards termination.
If you look at call by name and call by
value and how their related termination
then, we know that both of our
reevaluation strategies will always reduce
the same value provided term evaluations
terminate.
But, what if evaluations do not terminate?
We have seen in the last session that some
of the expressions actually do not give a
value in a finite number of steps.
So, there we have an important theorem
which says that if the call by value
evaluation of an expression terminates,
then the call by name evaluation of that
same expression will terminate also.
And furthermore, the other direction is
not true.
So, call by name termination does not
imply call by value termination.
So, let's see an example.
Can we find an expression that terminates
on the call by name, but not on the call
by value?
Okay, so let's see how we would go about
that.
We define a function first that takes
simply two parameters, x and y and returns
the first one x, so it forgets about y.
And then, we consider the expression first
of one and loop, so we pass a
non-terminating computation into the
second parameter.
And a call by name, what, what will
happen?
Well, call by name will reduce the first
expression without reducing the argument.
So, it would just yield one in a single
step, the first argument.
And the variation would stop in a value,
obviously.
And a call by value, we have to reduce the
arguments to this expression so we have to
reduce loop.
And, well, we know that loop reduces to
itself, so we would reduce the arguments.
Infinitely often, the whole expression
would always reduce to itself and we would
make no progress.
So, that's another example of an infinite
loop.
In Scala, we normally use call by value.
You might ask, well, given the advantages
of call by name that it terminates more
often, why call by value?
Well, it turns out that, for expressions
in practice, call by value is often
exponentially more efficient than call by
name because it avoids this repeated
recomputation of argument expressions that
call by name entails.
The other argument for call by value is
that it plays much nicer with, imperative
effects and side effects because you tend
to know much better when expressions will
be evaluated.
Since Scala is also an, an imperative
side, call by value is the standard
choice.
Except that, sometimes you really want to
force call by name, and Scala lets you do
that also.
You do that by adding a, an arrow in front
of the parameter type.
So, this function constOne takes an x
parameter int and a y parameter of type
arrow int.
And that means that the parameter y is
also an int, but it will be past call by
name.
So, to demonstrate the difference between
the two parameters, let's trace the
evaluations of two expressions, constOne
one plus two loop, and constOne of loop
and one plus two.
So, the first one, constOne, one plus two
loop is, well the first parameter is call
by value, so we have to reduce that to
three, so that will be three and the rest
will be kept as it was before.
The second parameter, we do not need to
reduce because it's a call by name
parameter, so we are done with the
argument lists.
We can apply the function and the function
would just always reduce to one.
So, it would in fact, would ignore both of
it's parameters.
That's the first expression.
The second expression here we would have
constOne of loop and one plus two.
While here we have to reduce the first
argument because it's call by value, and
we get into the same situation that loop
produces to itself.
So, no progress and we get another
infinite cycle.