Last week, you have gotten to know
functions as essential building blocks of
programs.
This week, we'll still be concerned with
functions.
We will get to know several ways to
construct them and to compose them.
Finally, next week, we are going to look
at data and objects.
In the first session of this week, we are
going to look again at recursion, and we
will find out that there are actually
several ways to express recursion.
First let's review function application.
You know from the last session that
there's one simple rule.
You evaluate a function application F
applied to arguments E1 to EN
by evaluating the arguments, expressions
E1 to EN they would resulting the values
V1 to VM say.
And then replacing the application of the
function by its body.
And at the same time replacing the forming
parameters of the function by the actual
arguments V1 to VM.
This rewriting rule can be formalized by
rewriting the program itself.
Say, you have a program with a function
definition def f with parameters x one to
x n and a body b.
And then, somewhere else eh, you have a
function call f applied to value argument
values v 1 to v n.
That program can be rewritten to a
programme that contains the same function
definition but the function application has
now being replaced by the body of f,
B, and at the same time the former
parameters x 1 to x n have been replaced
by the argument values.
And the rest of the programme is assumed
to be unchanged, which is assumed to be
these triple dots here.
That's areas of the programs that we do
not touch.
This notation, we want for x 1 the end
for x n is called a substitution.
What we mean by it, is that all
occurrences in b of the values x one to x
n have been replaced by
the corresponding values v1 to vn.
Here's an example,
consider GCD, the function that computes
the greatest common divisor of two
numbers.
We know an implementation for GCD it is
since a way long time, since ancient
greek, its known as Euclid's algorithm.
To compute the greatest common divisor of
two numbers A and B, what do you do.
First if B is zero then A is a common
divisor of both A and B and otherwise you
compute the greatest common divisor of.
First b, and then a modular b.
Percent sign here is as in Java and C,
means that A modular B, the modulus of A
and B.
Let's try this algorithm in action.
Gcd, fourteen, 21.
How is that evaluated?
Well, you would expand GCD, so that would
give you, if 21 = zero, fourteen else GCD,
21 and fourteen modular 21.
And you simplify the condition, 21 = zero
is false.
Next you simplify the if-then-else using
the rule we have developed previously.
So if false, fourteen else, GCD of 21 and
fourteen modular,
21 would give the else part.
Once we have the else part, we reduce its
arguments to values.
That gives us an other call to GCD which
we expand, and the process repeats.
I have signified that here with a multiple
errors to say these are reductions that
take more than one step.
We get GCD fourteen to seven, we get GCD
seven, zero, and finally you get the
condition if zero equals zero, seven else
some other call to GCD.
And that finally, since the condition is
true here, we get seven.
Okay.
Let's look at another rewriting example.
Factorial.
Classical algorythm for factorial is the
following.
You're said to take the factorial of a
number n.
You ask again if n equals zero,
then the factorial would be one.
Otherwise it would be n times factorial of
n minus one.
Let's apply that algorythm to factorial of
four.
So that would expand to the following
conditional.
If four equal zero, one, that's four times
factorial four minus one.
You evaluate the if then else, that gives
you in a couple of steps, four times
factorial of three.
The second part.
Reducing further gives you four times
three times factorial of two.
And so on, until you finally reach four
times three times two times one times one.
That was the last, the first case of
factorial and that reduces to 120.
Question,
what is the difference between these two
sequences?
GCD and factorial?
Well, one important difference is that if
we come back to GCD, we see that.
The,
reduction sequence essentially oscillates.
It goes from one call to GCD to the next
one here, to the next one here, to the
next one here and finally it terminates.
In between we have expressions that are
different from the simple call like if
then else's but we always
come back to this shape to the call of
GCD.
If we look at factorial, on the other hand
we see that in each couple of steps we add
one more element to our expressions.
Our expressions becomes bigger and bigger
until we
end when we finally reduce it to the final
value.
So, that difference in the rewriting rules
actually translates directly to a
difference in the execution, in the actual,
execution on a computer.
In fact, it turns out that if you have a
recursive function that calls itself as
its last action, then you can reuse the
stack frame of that function.
This is called tail recursion.
And by applying that trick, it means that
a tail recursive function can execute in
constant stuck space, so it's really just
another formulation of an iterative
process.
Could say a tail recursive function is the
functional form of a loop, and it executes
just as efficiently as a loop.
So if we go back to GCD, we see that in
the else part, GCD calls itself as its
last action.
And that translate its, to a rewriting
sequence that was essentially constant
size, and that will, in the actual
execution on a computer, translate into a
tail recursive call that can execute in
constant space.
On the other hand, if you look at
factorial again, then you'll see that
after the call to factorial n minus one,
there was still work to be done, namely,
we had to multiply the result of that call
with the number N.
So that call here is not a tail recursive
call, and it becomes evident in the
reduction sequence, where you see that
actually there's a buildup of intermediate
results that we all have to keep until we
can compute the final value.
So that factorial would not be a tail
recursive function.
Both
factorial and GCD only call itself
but in general, of course, a function
could call other functions.
So the generalization of tail
recursion is that, if the last action of a
function consists of calling another
function, maybe the same, maybe some other
function.
The stack frame could be reused for both
functions.
Such calls are called tail calls.
After having gone through the exercise,
you might ask yourself, should every
function be tail recursive?
Well, not really.
The interest of tail recursion is mostly
to avoid very deep recursive chains.
Most implementations of, the JBM, for
instance, limit the maximal depth of
recursion to a couple of thousand stack
frames.
So if your, the input data is such that
these deep recursive chains could happen,
then yes it's a good idea to reformulate
your function to be tail recursive, to run
in constant stack frame, so as to avoid
stack overflow exceptions.
On the other hand, if your input data are
not,
susceptible to deep precausive chains
then
clarity trumps efficiency evert time, so
write your function the clearest way you
can.
Which often is not terricosive.
And don't worry about the steck frames
that are spent.
As Donald Knuth has said, premature
optimization is the source of all evil.
And that's the model that's very valuable
to follow.
Coming back to factorial.
You might have observed that factorial
grows really very, very quickly.
So, even after very low number of
recursive steps it will already the,
exceed the range of integers, or even long
integers.
So, in that case definitely it was not
worth making factorial a tail recursive
function.
So, we did that only as a, an exercise so
that you have the techniques ready when
you need them.
So let's do an exercise on tail recursion.
You've seen factorial, and we've seen
that, that version of the function was not
tail recursive.
So now the task is to design a tail
recursive version of the same function.
Okay,
so the most convenient way to solve this
exercise is using another worksheet.
I have already created a new package in
our proc fun project called week two, and
in that package we have a
worksheet excercise in which I have
already written the signature of factorial
but I've left out the implementation.
So, how would we implement that in a
tail recursive fashion?
Actually, it turns out that we need
another function, called loop, that takes
two parameters, not one.
I'll give you an outline of loop here.
So, the idea is, it would take an
accumulator.
That's also an int, and the current value
and it would ask if, the current value is
zero then it wouldn't return one as
before.
But the accumulator
and otherwise, it would return something
else.
And we would start the program with loop
of an initial value of the accumulator and
the current value of n.
So the question is, what do we need to do
to fill in the question marks here?
The first task is to fill in something for
the initial value of the accumulator.
Here it's pretty clear that, we say, well,
if n equals zero then the accumulator is
returned so it has to be the right value
for n equals zero.
And that would be one.
So we pass one here.
The second question is, what do we do in
the case where n is not equal to zero.
And the idea there is we would call again
into the loop with the accumulator times
and the current value and n reduced by
one.
And the thing still doesn't compile
because we have forgotten to give a result
type to loop.
Once we do that, factorial compiles.
And we can test it
so let's do that.
So that would give 24 as expected.
In this session we've gotten to know tail
recursion as a special case of recursion
that corresponds to a loop in an
imperative program.
In the next session, we are going to cover
new ways to compose functions.