So far our syntactic vocabulary was really
minimal.
Essentially all we had were functions and
function applications.
In this week we are going to introduce
two more syntax constructs, namely
conditionals and value definitions.
In every language you need a way to choose
between
two alternatives and for that Scala has
the conditional expression if-else.
It looks like a if-else in Java, but it's
used for expressions, not statements.
You see an example here.
We define an absolute function which takes
an x, which is an
int, and it says while if x greater or
equal to zero, x.
Otherwise, minus x.
What you see here is that the if-else is
actually an expression.
It's not a statement where you have to set
a variable and then return a variable.
It's an expression.
The x greater than zero here is an
expression
of type Boolean and such expressions we
sometimes call predicates.
So Boolean expressions are formed
essentially in the same way as in Java.
So you would, could write true or false as
Boolean constants.
Not b then is written then b for negation.
Conjunction b and b.
Another b would be written b and ampersand
ampersand b.
This junction is written with a double bar
and you would have
the usual comparison operators from equal,
equality, inequality to all the
comparisons.
Generally if an expression is a legal
expression in Java, then you
can expect it to be a legal expression in
Scala as well.
Okay.
So, we have seen now the syntax the
formation rules
of Boolean expressions, but what about
their meaning and we
have come to define meaning by the
substitution model and
we are going to do the same thing for
Booleans.
So how do we define meaning for Boolean
expressions?
Well, simply by giving rewrite rules that
give you here on the left
some templates for Boolean expressions and
on the right how they would rewrite.
Take the first one.
Not true would give you false.
Not false would give you true.
The third rule is about and conjunction.
It says true and some other expression e,
doesn't matter which it is, would always
be the same as e, and false and some other
expression e would always be false.
The rules for or are analogous to the
rules for and.
They have the duals of those.
So true or e would then always be true of
course.
Whereas false or e for any expression e
would be e.
What's interesting about that is that and
and or don't always need their right
operand.
That's the e here to be evaluated.
Whenever you write e in a, in a sense, you
can just pass the arbitrary expression.
And here for instance with a false and e
reducing to false,
we would have that always without even
looking inside the expression e.
So e doesn't need to be a value.
It doesn't need to be reduced to a value.
And we say that these expressions use
short-circuit evaluation.
Of course in expressions in most other
programing languages, Java included, do
the same thing
but now we have a concise model that shows
essentially a rule for when this happens.
So let's see how we would go about that.
We're looking for rewrite rules for
expressions of the following form.
It would be if some condition Boolean.
Some then part e1, else, some else part
e2.
One good distinction as well.
The evaluation will depend on what the
Boolean value b here is.
So let's write one rule for where b is
true.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
What would that rewrite to?
Well, it would rewrite to the then part
e1.
And conversely, if the Boolean condition
is false, then
the conditional which we write to the else
part, e2.
So those are the two rules that we are
after that characterize the behavior of
the conditional completely.
Here's another piece of new syntax.
We have seen that function parameters can
be passed by value
or by name and in fact the same
distinction applies to definition.
The def form is in a sense called by-name
because its right hand side is evaluated
on each use.
There's also a val form which is by-value.
For instance if you write val x equals 2
and then val y equals square of x, then
the square of x will be evaluated right
here
instead of when we first refer to the name
y.
So the right hand side of a value
definition is evaluated at the
point of the definition itself and
afterwards the name refers to the value.
So in our case the y reference here would
refer
to the number 4, not to the expression
square of two.
The difference between val and def as a
definition form
becomes apparent when the right hand side
does not terminate.
So to do that, I can take the repo.
Let's generate another looping expression
again,.
There we go.
And now if we say def x equals loop, then
nothing happens.
We just defined another name for loop,
whereas if I defined val x equals loop,
then my repo dies and doesn't, I have to
take it out explicitly with a Ctrl+C.
So def x equals loop is okay, but val x
equals loop will lead to an
infinite loop because the right hand side
loop
will be evaluated at the point of the
finishing.
Let's do an exercise.
What I want you to do is write functions
and
and or such that for all argument
expressions x and y,
and x y is the same as the double
ampersand
and or x y is the same as the double bars.
And of course you shouldn't use bar or
ampersand in your implementations.
When you think about it, it's also good to
think
what are good operands to test that these
equalities hold.
Okay, let's think about how we would write
the and function.
First, give it signature here.
So it takes two Boolean and what should it
return?
Well, one guideline would be let's just
look at the rewrite rules for and.
It says, well, if the first condition is
true, then it would rewrite to the second
one.
Y, if the first condition is false then
the result would be false.
And true, false is false as expected and
true true.
So here we would expect true.
It's true also as expected.
Is true and false the only value we should
test and with?
Well, maybe not.
What about non-terminating arguments?
Let's try that.
And false and loop.
What would we, would we expect here?
Rewrite rule says false and loop you
rewritten
to false so that's what we would expect
here.
But what we get is nothing.
So, we get a, an, an infinite loop.
You have to interrupt the execution by a
signal.
So obviously, there's something wrong
here.
How do we correct it?
Well, if you look at it, the thing that
went wrong here
is that you passed the second argument y
as a value parameter.
If we do that then it means that it will
always be evaluated, we, whereas
what we need is to be able to pass it just
simply as an expression.
So let's try to change that.
We make here the second parameter a call
by-name parameter
and give it the same implementation and
now we can redo our
expression and false loop and get false as
expected.